<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/hoax.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GH-19CUK-18381104">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Black Ghost on the London and Birmingham Railway</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Originally published by</resp>
               <name>John Bull</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
               <name>Gabi Keane</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This project encoded newspaper and periodical articles on ghost hoaxes in the
               Victorian period. This publication of the text serves as data in a collaborative
               laboratory edition for the 2022 NEH Institute "Advanced digital editing: modeling the
               text and making the edition" at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Ghost hoaxes in 19th-century British news media</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>All texts in this collection were sourced from British periodical and newspaper
               archives, transcribed,and encoded. The citation below was provided by the archive and
               appears exactly as given.</p>
            <p>
               <bibl>"A Black Ghost on the London and Birmingham Railway." <publisher>John
                     Bull</publisher>, <date when="1838-11-04">4 Nov. 1838</date>, p. 526. 19th
                  Century UK Periodicals, http://tinyurl.com/yajx2huh. Accessed 1 August
                  2017.</bibl>
            </p>
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This document is part of a larger digital collection of stories of ghost hoaxes from
               the 18th and 19th century London newspapers and periodicals. The project explores the
               beginnings of mass print media in a metropolitan area at a time when technology and
               education made reading increasingly common and inexpensive.</p>
            <p>The corpus holds 36 individual documents, which reflect a diverse mix of reporting on
               various hauntings in and around London between 1804 and 1889. The PDF and JPEGs from
               online databases were transcribed using ABBYFineReader OCR, then corrected and
               occasionally manually transcribed if document quality necessitated it. After
               normalization in plain text, all documents were upconverted to TEI XML.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>Earlier texts have had some spelling normalization due to errors in OCR.
                  Typographic em dashes are longer than modern em dashes, so all dashes have been
                  normalized to modern em dash length.</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation>
               <p>All extraneous white space used by printers to avoid overlapping with letters has
                  been removed. All quotes are simply tagged with the q tag.</p>
            </quotation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>For some time past the policemen and navigators employed on the <placeName>London and
               Birmingham railroad, near the central station, at Wolverton</placeName>,
            have been dreadfully alarmed by the appearance of <rs ref="ghost">a supernatural figure
               gliding up and down the line, at more than railroad velocity, enveloped in cloud of
               white smoke instead of steam</rs>. <rs ref="or">This figure, which resembles a man of
               colour, is supposed by the superstitious and terrified workmen to be no other than
                  <rs ref="ghost or">the ghost of a gigantic black</rs>, designated <persName
                  ref="#blackshag">Black Shag</persName>,</rs> and who, about two months since, was
            buried alive by the falling in of a quantity of earth at a place called
            <placeName>Sandy Hole</placeName>. The body of <persName ref="#blackshag">Black
               Shag</persName> was got out, and buried in
            <placeName ref="#holytrinity">Wolverton Churchyard</placeName>. Since that period <rs
               ref="ghost">his ghost has been extremely troublesome</rs>. Sometimes he has appeared
            to the excavators when engaged at mining any dangerous part of the road, with <rs
               ref="ghost">a huge pair of horns on his head, and as black as soot</rs>; and, after
            capering about in the most mysterious and awful manner, would exclaim, <q
               who="#blackshag">Take warning by my fate,</q> and immediately vanish. <rs ref="ghost"
               >At other times he is seen bearing the resemblance of a tall black, and eliding along
               the road with amazing velocity</rs>, choosing the <soCalled>witching hour of
               night</soCalled> for his extraordinary pranks. Several policemen, as well as
            excavators, have been so terrified by <rs ref="#blackshag ghost">the ghost of
                  <soCalled>Black Shag</soCalled></rs>, that they have thrown up their employment;
            and one man lies now in an alarming state of illness at the above village, from the
            shock he received at seeing this mysterious visitor, who is the talk of the whole
            neighbourhood.</p>

      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
