<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/hoax.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GH-19CUK-18360924">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Ghost! A Ghost!</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Originally published by</resp>
               <name>Cleave's Weekly Police Gazette</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
               <name>Gabi Keane</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This project encoded newspaper and periodical articles on ghost hoaxes in the Victorian period. This publication of the text serves as data in a collaborative laboratory edition for the 2022 NEH Institute "Advanced digital editing: modeling the text and making the edition" at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Ghost hoaxes in 19th-century British news media</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>All texts in this collection were sourced from British periodical and newspaper
               archives, transcribed,and encoded. The citation below was provided by the archive and
               appears exactly as given.</p>
            <p><bibl>"A Ghost! a Ghost!" <publisher>Cleave's Weekly Police Gazette</publisher>, <date when="1836-09-24">24 Sept. 1836</date>. Nineteenth
                  Century Collections Online, http://tinyurl.galegroup.com/tinyurl/9RxC29. Accessed
                  11 Mar. 2019.</bibl></p>
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This document is part of a larger digital collection of stories of ghost hoaxes from
               the 18th and 19th century London newspapers and periodicals. The project explores the
               beginnings of mass print media in a metropolitan area at a time when technology and
               education made reading increasingly common and inexpensive.</p>
            <p>The corpus holds 36 individual documents, which reflect a diverse mix of reporting on
               various hauntings in and around London between 1804 and 1889. The PDF and JPEGs from
               online databases were transcribed using ABBYFineReader OCR, then corrected and
               occasionally manually transcribed if document quality necessitated it. After
               normalization in plain text, all documents were upconverted to TEI XML.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>Earlier texts have had some spelling normalization due to errors in OCR.
                  Typographic em dashes are longer than modern em dashes, so all dashes have been
                  normalized to modern em dash length.</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation>
               <p>All extraneous white space used by printers to avoid overlapping with letters has
                  been removed. All quotes are simply tagged with the q tag.</p>
            </quotation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>

   <text>
      <body>
         <p>For some days, early in the week, the good folks of <placeName ref="#haggerstone"
               >Haggerstone</placeName> were in a state of considerable excitement, in consequence
            of something, which was <rs ref="ghost">supposed to be an unearthly object</rs>, having been for several
            successive nights seen in the neighbourhood of <placeName ref="#haggerstonechurch"
               >Haggerstone Church Yard</placeName>. The spot where it was first seen was in Black
            Horse fields, close by the bone-house, which is at the side of the Church Yard; and the
            story of its appearance arose under the following circumstances. Two ladies, and a
            gentleman, were going along the foot-path, which crosses the fields, when they observed,
            (the time being about twelve o’clock) <rs ref="ghost">what at first appeared to be a shadow</rs>: on
            approaching they were bold enough to address it: but, as <rs ref="ghost">ghosts hold no communion with
            mortals</rs>, no answer was given: the conclusion was, <rs ref="ghost">as the being was wrapped all in white,
            that it was nothing less than a ghost</rs>. The party, therefore, prudently retired; and in
            seeing police constable 50 N, they informed him of what they had seen, and on the
            officer going to the place, he found his progress impeded by the same object, and which
            stood motionless as a tomb-stone. The officer addressed it: but whether <q><rs ref="ghost">a spirit from
               heaven, or goblin d—d</rs></q>—he obtained no reply: and as his orders were not to take
            ghosts to the station-house, nor to send them back <q>to that bourne from which no
               travellers return,</q> he was contented with not disturbing <rs ref="ghost">the hapless sprite</rs>, but
            he did hear, as he spread the report abroad, that a ghost paid a nocturnal visit to the
            spot: since the same unsightly object was there the following night. The effect was that
            the thoroughfare, which was much frequented, became deserted, and people went far round
            in preference to going along this unhallowed spot. The consternation, however, in
            Haggerstone was very great, and continually the inconvenience was found so great, that
            several men, who were able <q>to screw their courage to the sticking place,</q> resolved
            to remove this obstacle, and for this purpose, they collected in a body, arming
            themselves with sticks and brick-bats. But on information being communicated to
            Inspector Tong, at the <placeName ref="#robertstreet">Station-house in Robert
               Street</placeName>, Hoxton, he believing in neither <rs ref="ghost">ghosts nor hobgoblins</rs>, sent
            Sergeant Budnell to make inquiries, and who ascertained that the fears of the
            inhabitants had been stirred up by no other being than the good wife of some industrious
            mechanic; who being anxious about the return of her husband, took a stroll in her
            nightly habiliment, being anxious for his coming home. On the Inspector being made
            acquainted with these circumstances, and as he was aware that the courage of the valiant
            men of <placeName ref="#haggerstone">Haggerstone</placeName> was about to be put to the test, sent a policeman to her cottage in
            <placeName ref="unknown">Black Horse Fields</placeName>, warning her of her danger. She has, of course, not ventured forth
            again at that hour of the night. The foot-path is rather more frequented than it was:
            though the more cautious cannot avoid giving a suspicious look, toward the heretofore
            dreaded spot.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
