<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/hoax.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GH-19CUK-18380114">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The New Hammersmith Ghost</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Originally published by</resp>
                    <name>The Satirist; or Censor of the Times</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
                    <name>Gabi Keane</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>This project encoded newspaper and periodical articles on ghost hoaxes in the
                    Victorian period. This publication of the text serves as data in a collaborative
                    laboratory edition for the 2022 NEH Institute "Advanced digital editing:
                    modeling the text and making the edition" at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>Ghost hoaxes in 19th-century British news media</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>All texts in this collection were sourced from British periodical and newspaper
                    archives, transcribed,and encoded. The citation below was provided by the
                    archive and appears exactly as given.</p>
                <p>
                    <bibl>"The Ghost." <publisher rend="The">Satirist; or Censor of the
                            Times</publisher>, <date when="1838-01-14">14 Jan. 1838</date>, p. 14.
                        19th Century UK Periodicals, http://tinyurl.galegroup.com/tinyurl/6nPBr8.
                        Accessed 23 July 2018.</bibl>
                </p>
            </sourceDesc>

        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This document is part of a larger digital collection of stories of ghost hoaxes
                    from the 18th and 19th century London newspapers and periodicals. The project
                    explores the beginnings of mass print media in a metropolitan area at a time
                    when technology and education made reading increasingly common and
                    inexpensive.</p>
                <p>The corpus holds 36 individual documents, which reflect a diverse mix of
                    reporting on various hauntings in and around London between 1804 and 1889. The
                    PDF and JPEGs from online databases were transcribed using ABBYFineReader OCR,
                    then corrected and occasionally manually transcribed if document quality
                    necessitated it. After normalization in plain text, all documents were
                    upconverted to TEI XML.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Earlier texts have had some spelling normalization due to errors in OCR.
                        Typographic em dashes are longer than modern em dashes, so all dashes have
                        been normalized to modern em dash length.</p>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All extraneous white space used by printers to avoid overlapping with letters
                        has been removed. All quotes are simply tagged with the q tag.</p>
                </quotation>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p><q>Be thou <rs ref="ghost">a spirit of health</rs>, or <rs ref="ghost">goblin
                            damned</rs>?</q></p>
                <p><rs ref="rel public">It would certainly have been a pity if the Christmas had
                        passed over without something to occupy the public attention</rs>; and it
                    must be gratifying to the lovers of the awful to find a fire and a <rs
                        ref="ghost">ghost to enliven the winter evenings</rs>. We shall not,
                    however, speculate about the former, as that is a real calamity; but with regard
                    to the latter affair, we feel bound to tell all we know, which will be best
                    communicated by publishing some letters received by us from parties of eminence
                    and of undoubted veracity.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <opener>
                    <salute>Sir—</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>I have just seen the <rs ref="ghost">ghost walking on the water</rs> under
                    <placeName ref="#londonbridge">London-bridge</placeName>; <rs ref="ghost"
                        type="desc">its breath was fire, and when it opened its mouth wide, it had
                        all the appearance of a baker’s oven, red hot</rs>. I was terrified lest it
                    should set the Thames on fire, and I could not help exclaiming with Shakspeare—
                        <q>The fishes beginning to sweat, Cried, ‘Damn it, how hot we shall be!’</q>
                    I was determined, if possible, to give it into custody, when all of a sudden <rs
                        ref="ghost">I saw it was in the shape of an ass</rs>, and just as the moon
                    went behind a cloud it vanished. I have to request that you will give me your
                    opinion on this important matter.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>Faithfully your’s,</salute>
                    <persName>C. Hunter, Bart.</persName>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>[In reply we beg to observe, that in our opinion Sir Claudius merely saw his own
                    shadow.]</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <opener>
                    <salute>Sir—</salute>
                </opener>
                <p><rs ref="ghost">It is not true that I have been personating the ghost which has
                        thrown so many old ladies into fits</rs>; and it is to me quite inexplicable
                    that any one could discover aught in my appearance at all calculated to render
                    me a bugbear. I shall certainly bring the affair before the Parliament, as
                    superstitions feelings tend greatly to impede the march of intellect, and
                    particularly militate against any system of national education. <rs ref="ghost"
                        >The ubiquity of the ghost is truly marvellous</rs>, being seen at different
                    places at the same moment; and it is well known that I never was like Cerberus,
                    playing the part of three gentlemen at once. It is my intention to publish my
                    opinions on <rs ref="ghost">apparitions</rs> in the <q>Penny Magazine;</q> but
                    in the mean time I request you to publish my denial of the charge that I have
                    been playing either the fool or the devil with old ladies.</p>
                <closer><salute>I am, Sir, your’s, &amp;c.</salute>
                    <persName>Brougham and Vaux</persName>.</closer>
            </div>
            <div>
                <opener>
                    <salute>Sir—</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>As the story about the ghost is likely to injure my reputation considerably, I
                    entreat of you to undeceive the public mind. The only ghost worthy of attention
                    is the one I represent in the tragedy of Ham-let; mine is the only legitimate
                    ghost ex{}ant, and I consider the attempt which is made to impose upon the
                    world, as dictated by hatred and malice. I rely upon your candour and
                    impartiality to render me this act of justice, and beg to enclose an admission
                    to the shilling gallery, as I am seen to the best advantage at the greatest
                    possible distance.</p>
                <closer><salute>Your obedient servant,</salute>
                    <persName>John Cooter</persName>.</closer>
            </div>
            <div>
                <opener>
                    <salute>My dear Sir—</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>I am compelled to apply to you for consolation at this distressing moment: <rs
                        ref="ghost">my tabby has miscarried owing to her being frightened by the
                        ghost</rs>. Seven little dear kittens, and one a real tortoise-shell Tom,
                    deprived of existence so prematurely! My poor Tabby was gently caterwauling,
                    when <rs ref="ghost">the ghost came in the shape of a huge dog</rs>, and bitoff
                    half of her tail; her condition is deplorable, but I am in hopes that I shall be
                    able to restore that graceful appendage to its proper length. Do lay <rs
                        ref="ghost">the perturbed spirit</rs> if you possibly can, or the most
                    serious results may be expected. I have just heard of the following. An elderly
                    lady of my acquaintance was suddenly embraced by it in <rs ref="ghost">the shape
                        of a Life-guardsman</rs>, and her teeth chattered so much from fear that
                    they all dropped out. Her dentist declares that he must make her another new
                    set. A servant girl in my neighbourhood went out on an errand on Sunday night,
                    and did not return home till Monday morning, when she told a most lamentable
                    story about being <rs ref="ghost">carried off against her will by the ghost, and
                        how she was detained by it all the night, and how it seemed to oppress her
                        like the nightmare, but would not let her sleep</rs>. The girl further says,
                    that <rs ref="ghost">the ghost has a spell over her</rs>, and that it is likely
                    she shall see it again. I have sent a worthy divine, <q>a powerful preacher,</q>
                    to afford her truly spiritual consolation. I have heard of something else which
                    was told to my informant by a person who saw a little boy who had spoken to an
                    elderly woman that thought she had had <rs ref="ghost">a glimpse of the
                        ghost</rs>. I am making every inquiry possible, and if I meet with the
                    elderly woman, I will accompany her to communicate all she knows and thinks, and
                    thinks that she knows, I send you a present of one of my dear kittens
                    stuffed.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>Believe me your affectionate Herald Office.</salute>
                    <persName>Grandmama.</persName>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>We hasten to give a place to the following from the M-P-ric of
                    <placeName ref="#Finsbury">Finsbury</placeName>:—</p>
                <div>
                    <opener>
                        <salute>Dear Sat—</salute>
                    </opener>
                    <p>An absurd report having got abroad that I am <rs ref="ghost">the ghost, or
                            devil, monster, or whatever it may be</rs> died, by which the suburbs of
                        London are reported to be haunted, I shall feel obliged by your giving a
                        contradiction to the same. <rs ref="ghost">I am neither ghost nor
                        demon</rs>, although a devil of a fellow for moral and medical dissection;
                        nor have I been playing any pranks lately, except in the House of Common and
                        at <placeName ref="#WCHouse">White Conduit House</placeName>. I never wear a
                        bear-skin dress, nor array myself in a white sheet to frighten nursery girls
                        out of their senses; nor was I seen in
                            <soCalled><placeName ref="#CTLane">Cut-throat Lane</placeName></soCalled>
                        the other evening, clawing the clothes off the backs of several females, as
                        reported in the papers. It if true that many years back I cut off the head
                        of Thistlewood after his execution, having figured as <q>the man in the
                            mask</q> on the scaffold. But, my dear Sat, I submit that this trifling
                        circumstance forms no excuse for my being held up as the
                            <soCalled>monster</soCalled> who has frightened the suburbs from their
                        propriety. Pray set the public right on this point, as I am peculiarly nice
                        on matters that affect my character. I send you a box of <rs ref="rel"
                            >Lucifer</rs>, forgetting an instantaneous light, manufactured by
                        myself, and I think you will allow them to evince no small acquaintance with
                        the science of chemistry and combustion.</p>
                    <closer><salute>I am, dear Sat, everlastingly your admirer,</salute>
                        <persName>Thomas Wakley</persName>.</closer>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
