<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/hoax.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GH-GNCCO-18521030">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A <q>Ghost</q> at Hull</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Originally published by</resp>
               <name>The Leader</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
               <name>Gabi Keane</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This project encoded newspaper and periodical articles on ghost hoaxes in the Victorian period. This publication of the text serves as data in a collaborative laboratory edition for the 2022 NEH Institute "Advanced digital editing: modeling the text and making the edition" at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Ghost hoaxes in 19th-century British news media</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>All texts in this collection were sourced from British periodical and newspaper
               archives, transcribed,and encoded. The citation below was provided by the archive and
               appears exactly as given.</p>
            <p><bibl>"A 'Ghost' at Hull." <publisher rend="The">Leader</publisher>, <date when="1852-10-30">30 Oct. 1852</date>, p. 1034. Nineteenth Century Collections
               Online, tinyurl.galegroup.com/tinyurl/55Nxm6. Accessed 31 July 2017.</bibl></p>
         </sourceDesc>
         
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This document is part of a larger digital collection of stories of ghost hoaxes from
               the 18th and 19th century London newspapers and periodicals. The project explores the
               beginnings of mass print media in a metropolitan area at a time when technology and
               education made reading increasingly common and inexpensive.</p>
            <p>The corpus holds 36 individual documents, which reflect a diverse mix of reporting on
               various hauntings in and around London between 1804 and 1889. The PDF and JPEGs from
               online databases were transcribed using ABBYFineReader OCR, then corrected and
               occasionally manually transcribed if document quality necessitated it. After
               normalization in plain text, all documents were upconverted to TEI XML.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>Earlier texts have had some spelling normalization due to errors in OCR.
                  Typographic em dashes are longer than modern em dashes, so all dashes have been
                  normalized to modern em dash length.</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation>
               <p>All extraneous white space used by printers to avoid overlapping with letters has
                  been removed. All quotes are simply tagged with the q tag.</p>
            </quotation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>We find in the Hull Packet of Saturday one of those stories which <persName
               ref="#ccrowe">Mrs. Crowe</persName> would delight in. It is the account of <rs ref="ghost">a knocking
            ghost, who has afflicted a house at Hull with his presence, which must he anything but
            agreeable to the inmates</rs>:—</p>
         <div>
            <p>A marvellous sensation has been created in our town within the last few days, by the
               discovery that a ghost has taken up his quarters, evidently for the winter season, in
               a secluded dwelling on the <placeName ref="#anlabyrd">Anlaby-road</placeName>, where
               it is likely to obtain as great a notoriety as the <rs ref="ghost">celebrated Cock-lane ghost</rs>. Some little distance beyond the end of Walker-street and
               Great Thornton-street, on the lefthand side of the Anlaby-road, is <placeName
                  ref="#wellingtonln">a quiet, lonely lane, known by the name of
                  Wellington-lane</placeName>, at the bottom of which stands the <soCalled>haunted
                  house</soCalled> a respectable-looking tenement, occupied by an elderly bedridden
               dame, her son-in-law, and daughter, and a female domestic. It seems that about a
               month ago the inmates were startled in the stillness of night by a sharp, sudden <rs
                  ref="rapping">knocking on the walls of the room from some invisible hand</rs>. At
               first no notice was taken of this, but, to their great dismay, at irregular
               intervals, the same strange noise was repeated, a distinct knocking upon the wall
               being heard in the very apartment where they sat, and when no visible hand was raised
               to strike. For four successive weeks the noise was repeated, until the inmates grew
               seriously apprehensive that <rs ref="ghost">some supernatural agency was at work</rs>. Their fears were
               soon communicated to the neighbours, and speedily reached the public ear. The love of
               the marvellous is the most powerful and easily raised passion of the mind, and on
               Wednesday not fewer than 1000 persons visited the spot, lingering in the
               neighbourhood and straining their ears to catch the sound of <rs ref="ghost">the modest ghost, who
                  now and then indulges them with a solitary and muffled rap, tap, tap</rs>. For our own
               part, we are really apprehensive for <rs ref="ghost">his ghostship’s knuckles</rs>, which must suffer
               materially from such constant exercise. Yesterday night, although it was dull,
               drizzly, and cold, crowd upon crowd besieged the spot, standing, in spite of cold and
               wet, 100 yards from the haunted house, anxiously discussing the nature and object of
               the ghost’s visit, and patiently waiting to learn from the police, or those who were
               fortunate enough to get near the house, when it had knocked last. One or two
               policemen have been stationed in the house, with the view of detecting the cause;
               and, although it is seriously affirmed that the strange noise is still heard at
               intervals, it baffles all ingenuity, even on the part of the vigilant detectives, to
               discover whence it proceeds. A portion of the roof, we understand, has been removed,
               but without affording any clue. The noise is not confined to any one place, but
               alternately pervades different parts of the house. Sometimes it is a dull, heavy
               sound, and sometimes like a sort of scratch. Yesterday, 2000 or 3000 persons visited
                  <placeName ref="#wellingtonln">the spot</placeName>, many of whom lingered until
               nearly midnight, a detachment of police being present to preserve order. It is
               impossible to describe the sensation which has been created by the discovery of this
               affair, and credulity could hardly be carried further. The police declare that many
               would actually remain by the door of the house the whole of the night if they would
               only permit them.” This rivals <rs ref="squirrellghost">Miss Squirrell!</rs></p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
