<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/hoax.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GH-19CUK-18320115">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>A Ghost</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Originally published by</resp>
                    <name>The Age</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
                    <name>Gabi Keane</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>This project encoded newspaper and periodical articles on ghost hoaxes in the Victorian period. This publication of the text serves as data in a collaborative laboratory edition for the 2022 NEH Institute "Advanced digital editing: modeling the text and making the edition" at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>Ghost hoaxes in 19th-century British news media</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>All texts in this collection were sourced from British periodical and newspaper
                    archives, transcribed,and encoded. The citation below was provided by the
                    archive and appears exactly as given.</p>
                <p><bibl>"A Ghost." <publisher rend="The">Age</publisher>, <date when="1832-01-15">15 Jan. 1832</date>, p. 23. 19th Century UK Periodicals,
                    http://tinyurl.com/yaxzvbaf. Accessed 31 July 2017.</bibl></p>
            </sourceDesc>

        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This document is part of a larger digital collection of stories of ghost hoaxes
                    from the 18th and 19th century London newspapers and periodicals. The project
                    explores the beginnings of mass print media in a metropolitan area at a time
                    when technology and education made reading increasingly common and
                    inexpensive.</p>
                <p>The corpus holds 36 individual documents, which reflect a diverse mix of
                    reporting on various hauntings in and around London between 1804 and 1889. The
                    PDF and JPEGs from online databases were transcribed using ABBYFineReader OCR,
                    then corrected and occasionally manually transcribed if document quality
                    necessitated it. After normalization in plain text, all documents were
                    upconverted to TEI XML.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Earlier texts have had some spelling normalization due to errors in OCR.
                        Typographic em dashes are longer than modern em dashes, so all dashes have
                        been normalized to modern em dash length.</p>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All extraneous white space used by printers to avoid overlapping with letters
                        has been removed. All quotes are simply tagged with the q tag.</p>
                </quotation>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>There is one of the most remarkable personifications— if such a term may be allowed—
                of a <rs ref="ghost">Ghost</rs>, in the singular story of <q>The Robber,</q> which
                has just appeared from the pen of <name type="publication">Blackwood's</name>
                well-known contributor. The schemes of the Robber are most ingeniously and naturally
                contrived to depend, for their fulfillment, almost upon a miracle; and it is <rs
                    ref="hoax">the phantom-stratagem</rs> which he practices, that most marvelously
                works out his security, and eventually his doom.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
