<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/hoax.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GH-GNCCO-18361009">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Ghost</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Originally published by</resp>
               <name>The Weekly Times</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
               <name>Gabi Keane</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This project encoded newspaper and periodical articles on ghost hoaxes in the Victorian period. This publication of the text serves as data in a collaborative laboratory edition for the 2022 NEH Institute "Advanced digital editing: modeling the text and making the edition" at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Ghost hoaxes in 19th-century British news media</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>All texts in this collection were sourced from British periodical and newspaper
               archives, transcribed,and encoded. The citation below was provided by the
               archive and appears exactly as given.</p>
            <p><bibl>"A Ghost." <publisher rend="The">Weekly Times</publisher>, <date when="1836-10-09">9 Oct. 1836.</date> Nineteenth Century Collections Online,
               tinyurl.galegroup.com/tinyurl/54S2x9. Accessed 25 July 2017.</bibl></p>
         </sourceDesc>
         
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This document is part of a larger digital collection of stories of ghost hoaxes
               from the 18th and 19th century London newspapers and periodicals. The project
               explores the beginnings of mass print media in a metropolitan area at a time
               when technology and education made reading increasingly common and
               inexpensive.</p>
            <p>The corpus holds 36 individual documents, which reflect a diverse mix of
               reporting on various hauntings in and around London between 1804 and 1889. The
               PDF and JPEGs from online databases were transcribed using ABBYFineReader OCR,
               then corrected and occasionally manually transcribed if document quality
               necessitated it. After normalization in plain text, all documents were
               upconverted to TEI XML.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>Earlier texts have had some spelling normalization due to errors in OCR.
                  Typographic em dashes are longer than modern em dashes, so all dashes have
                  been normalized to modern em dash length.</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation>
               <p>All extraneous white space used by printers to avoid overlapping with letters
                  has been removed. All quotes are simply tagged with the q tag.</p>
            </quotation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>The inhabitants of the lonely portion of <placeName ref="#pentonville">Pentonville</placeName>, beyond Maiden-lane, called the
               <q><placeName ref="#frenchcolony">French Colony</placeName></q>, have for some weeks past been in a state of considerable
            excitement and alarm, in consequence of the reports of <rs ref="ghost">a ghost of collossal form</rs>,
            habited in <rs ref="ghost">the regular spectral costume of a white sheet, with a black mask on his face</rs>,
            having been seen stalking about the fields and lanes by several persons, to whom his
            formidable appearance gave great alarm; indeed, one of the <soCalled>ghost seers,</soCalled> a little girl
            about thirteen years of age, was so excessively frightened as to have been ever since
            entirely bereft of speech and reason. The police were apprised of the circumstance, and
            made several endeavours to apprehend him, but apprised by some means of their
            solicitude, he kept aloof for some nights. On the Wednesday evening of last week,
            however, as two men were returning across the fields from <placeName ref="#copenhouse">Copenhagen House</placeName>, they espied
            a tall figure start up from behind a cow, where it evidently had been couchant, and
            advance with rapid strides towards them, uttering the most awful groans. The men,
            however, had heard of <rs ref="ghost">his ghostship</rs> before, and waited his approach <q><emph>sans peur</emph></q>, till
            he got within range of their sticks, when they knocked him down, and continued
            belaboring him most unmercifully, till his screams convinced them it was flesh and blood
            upon which they were so vigorously exercising the <emph>argumentum baculinum</emph>, and brought
            the police to the spot. He was immediately carried to the station-house, where it was
            discovered, from his severe castigation, he had three ribs broken, besides the other
            parts of his corporeal person being terribly battered and bruised. The next morning he
            was taken before Mr. Laing, at <placeName ref="#hattonpol">Hatton-garden Police-office</placeName>, and by that magistrate
            sentenced to three months’ imprisonment in the House of Correction, which it is to be
            hoped will operate as a warning to him and to others not to play tricks of so injurious
            a tendency in future.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
