<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/hoax.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GH-GNCCO-18470904">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The New Hammersmith Ghost</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Originally published by</resp>
                    <name>Sunderland Herald, Douglas Jerrold's Weekly Newspaper</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
                    <name>Gabi Keane</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>This project encoded newspaper and periodical articles on ghost hoaxes in the Victorian period. This publication of the text serves as data in a collaborative laboratory edition for the 2022 NEH Institute "Advanced digital editing: modeling the text and making the edition" at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>Ghost hoaxes in 19th-century British news media</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>All texts in this collection were sourced from British periodical and newspaper
                    archives, transcribed,and encoded. The citation below was provided by the
                    archive and appears exactly as given.</p>
                <p><bibl>"A Ghost!" <publisher>Douglas Jerrold's Weekly Newspaper</publisher>, <date when="1847-09-04">4 Sept. 1847</date>, p. 1119.
                        Nineteenth Century Collections Online, tinyurl.galegroup.com/tinyurl/54Rtk8.
                        Accessed 25 July 2017.</bibl></p>
            </sourceDesc>

        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This document is part of a larger digital collection of stories of ghost hoaxes
                    from the 18th and 19th century London newspapers and periodicals. The project
                    explores the beginnings of mass print media in a metropolitan area at a time
                    when technology and education made reading increasingly common and
                    inexpensive.</p>
                <p>The corpus holds 36 individual documents, which reflect a diverse mix of
                    reporting on various hauntings in and around London between 1804 and 1889. The
                    PDF and JPEGs from online databases were transcribed using ABBYFineReader OCR,
                    then corrected and occasionally manually transcribed if document quality
                    necessitated it. After normalization in plain text, all documents were
                    upconverted to TEI XML.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Earlier texts have had some spelling normalization due to errors in OCR.
                        Typographic em dashes are longer than modern em dashes, so all dashes have
                        been normalized to modern em dash length.</p>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All extraneous white space used by printers to avoid overlapping with letters
                        has been removed. All quotes are simply tagged with the q tag.</p>
                </quotation>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>

        <body>
            <p>The other evening a young lady had occasion to go homewards down one of the lanes
                leading from the <placeName ref="unknown">Building-hill</placeName>. The night was moderately dark, and misses head was
                full of <rs ref="ghost">witches, ghosts, worrikows, bogles, and long-beaked
                    indescribables</rs>. At a particular point, <rs ref="ghost">she noted a
                    veritable ghost</rs>, and set up such a scream as awakened all the echoes in the
                neighbourhood, and very deaf ones they are, and fainted away.—Several parties,
                deeming murder had been committed, ran to the spot, and found miss prostrate, and
                the cause of her fright —<rs ref="ghost">a white ass, mumbling its scanty supper</rs>, drawn from the
                hedge. She is not yet convinced that she did not see a spirit, and has been very ill
                since. If young ladies fainted away at the sight of every ass frequenting these
                lanes, by day as well as by night, burnt feathers would be at a premium.—<title
                    type="publisher">Sunderland Herald</title>.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
