<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/hoax.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GH-GNCCO-18581204">

   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Ghost Caught</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Originally published by</resp>
               <name>The Cabinet Newspaper</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
               <name>Gabi Keane</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This project encoded newspaper and periodical articles on ghost hoaxes in the Victorian period. This publication of the text serves as data in a collaborative laboratory edition for the 2022 NEH Institute "Advanced digital editing: modeling the text and making the edition" at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Ghost hoaxes in 19th-century British news media</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>All texts in this collection were sourced from British periodical and newspaper
               archives, transcribed,and encoded. The citation below was provided by the archive and
               appears exactly as given.</p>
            <p><bibl>"A Ghost Caught." <publisher rend="The">Cabinet Newspaper</publisher>, <date when="1858-12-04">4 Dec. 1858</date>, p. 3. Nineteenth Century
                  Collections Online, tinyurl.galegroup.com/tinyurl/54SGP5. Accessed 25 July
                  2017.</bibl>
            </p>
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This document is part of a larger digital collection of stories of ghost hoaxes from
               the 18th and 19th century London newspapers and periodicals. The project explores the
               beginnings of mass print media in a metropolitan area at a time when technology and
               education made reading increasingly common and inexpensive.</p>
            <p>The corpus holds 36 individual documents, which reflect a diverse mix of reporting on
               various hauntings in and around London between 1804 and 1889. The PDF and JPEGs from
               online databases were transcribed using ABBYFineReader OCR, then corrected and
               occasionally manually transcribed if document quality necessitated it. After
               normalization in plain text, all documents were upconverted to TEI XML.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>Earlier texts have had some spelling normalization due to errors in OCR.
                  Typographic em dashes are longer than modern em dashes, so all dashes have been
                  normalized to modern em dash length.</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation>
               <p>All extraneous white space used by printers to avoid overlapping with letters has
                  been removed. All quotes are simply tagged with the q tag.</p>
            </quotation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>﻿The mystery of the ghost of an old house called <placeName ref="#drumhead"
               >Drumhead</placeName>, which has kept the village and neighbourhood of <placeName
               ref="#cardross">Cardross</placeName> in a state of great excitement for several weeks
            past, has at length been revealed. To such an extent had the rumours prevailed of the
            inexplicable sounds heard at night by the inhabitants of the house, and numbers having
            left it to reside in the village out of terror, that, in order to restore peace to the
            district, the constable stationed there determined to investigate into the cause of the
            affair. One night, between eleven and twelve o’clock, he proceeded to <placeName
               ref="#drumhead">Drumhead</placeName>, with three other young men belonging to
               <placeName ref="#cardross">Cardross</placeName> to assist him in his researches, the
            result of which was, as might have been expected, that the whole mystery was the work of
            some of the workmen lodging in the house, who had concocted the trick for the purpose of
            alarming the other inhabitants. A careful search was made. At last they opened a door in
            a dark passage leading from the kitchen to the room, and which concealed a recess
            beneath a staircase conducting to the second storey, and in a few minutes <rs ref="ghost">the mystery of
            the ghost was exploded</rs>. They found in the recess an old copper boiler, which had lain
            there apparently a number of years. A large square board was lying on the ground, like a
            trap-door to some vault below; but the machinery by which the <rs ref="rapping"
               >spirit-rapping</rs> had been applied was revealed. It consisted of a strong species
            of dried grass, capable of much resistance, which was conveyed beneath the floor to some
            distant apartment of the house. To this was attached two wands and the leg of a pair of
            tongs, so ingeniously constructed that by pulling the line the leg of the tongs was made
            to strike or rub against the copper boiler so as produce a variety of sounds. The wands
            and iron could be removed, and nothing would remain but the end of the line, which no
            one would readily notice. The discovery of the whole plot has exasperated <rs ref="ghost">the ghost
            party</rs> to such a degree that the constable believes there is some danger of a serious
            breach of the peace.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
