<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/hoax.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GH-19CUK-18380120-P">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>All the world...</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Originally published by</resp>
               <name>The Penny Satirist</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
               <name>Gabi Keane</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This project encoded newspaper and periodical articles on ghost hoaxes in the Victorian period. This publication of the text serves as data in a collaborative laboratory edition for the 2022 NEH Institute "Advanced digital editing: modeling the text and making the edition" at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Ghost hoaxes in 19th-century British news media</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>All texts in this collection were sourced from British periodical and newspaper
               archives, transcribed,and encoded. The citation below was provided by the archive and
               appears exactly as given.</p>
            <p><bibl>"All the world has by this time heard of the London Ghost, who is known in the
                  suburbs, by the name of 'Spring-heeled Jack,' who has been jumping Jim Crow in our
                  neighbourhood in rather a novel style." <publisher rend="The">Penny Satirist</publisher>, <date when="1838-01-20">20 Jan. 1838</date>, p. 2.
                  19th Century UK Periodicals, http://tinyurl.galegroup.com/tinyurl/9RpMs5. Accessed
                  11 Mar. 2019.</bibl></p>
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This document is part of a larger digital collection of stories of ghost hoaxes from
               the 18th and 19th century London newspapers and periodicals. The project explores the
               beginnings of mass print media in a metropolitan area at a time when technology and
               education made reading increasingly common and inexpensive.</p>
            <p>The corpus holds 36 individual documents, which reflect a diverse mix of reporting on
               various hauntings in and around London between 1804 and 1889. The PDF and JPEGs from
               online databases were transcribed using ABBYFineReader OCR, then corrected and
               occasionally manually transcribed if document quality necessitated it. After
               normalization in plain text, all documents were upconverted to TEI XML.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>Earlier texts have had some spelling normalization due to errors in OCR.
                  Typographic em dashes are longer than modern em dashes, so all dashes have been
                  normalized to modern em dash length.</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation>
               <p>All extraneous white space used by printers to avoid overlapping with letters has
                  been removed. All quotes are simply tagged with the q tag.</p>
            </quotation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>

   <text>
      <body>
         <p>All the world has by this time heard of <rs ref="ghost">the <placeName ref="london">London</placeName>
            Ghost, who is known in the suburbs, by the name of <q>Spring-heeled Jack,</q> who has
            been jumping Jim Crow in our neighbourhood in rather a novel style</rs>. Various conjectures
            are afloat respecting this <rs ref="ghost">solemn, grave looking personage</rs>. Some say it is Spring Rice,
            who has taken this opportunity of diverting the minds of the people from political
            scrutiny, and financial investigations. Others again say it is Jack Russell, on the <rs
               ref="pol">secret service of the Home Department</rs>; others, Lord Brougham, looking
            for glow-worms to enlighten the people. We cannot say we agree with any of these popular
            rumours. <rs ref="ghost just">We have too much faith in ghosts, to doubt the possibility of its being a
               <soCalled>genevine bony fidy</soCalled> spirit incarnate, <rs ref="rel">sent from Tartar-us to warn
            the sinful inhabitants of this land of the coming judgments of the Devil, for their
            awful selfishness and grasping greediness, by which they suck the blood of the poor, and
            fasten upon the produce of their industry, with their savage claws</rs>.</rs> The rumours that
            prevail about a wager between some wealthy scamps of aristocracy are much too
            imaginative and incredible for our sober minds. <note ana="generalized-fictional">Who
               the d—e could make hoots for a sham-apparition that would enable the wearer to jump
               over garden walls and fly over the tops of houses, to ride across the weathercocks of
               churches and to peep in at the back window of a house at the very moment he was
               knocking at the front door, and frightening the maid into her inward senses?</note>
            This is an age of discovery, truly; but science has not yet ascended to such an altitude
            as this amongst the honourable corporation of snobs, on whose shoulders <rs ref="ghost">the whole guilt
            of this wonderful apparition is very unjustly laid</rs>.</p>
         <p><rs ref="ghost">The ghost is generally about the size of a man, but it takes various forms. Sometimes it
            has the shape of a bear, sometimes it jumps like a kangaroo, and very frequently it is
               <rs ref="rel">dressed like one of the knights of Jerusalem</rs>, in shining bright
            armour, which gleams with a white light, like phosphorus.</rs> We saw a man who told us that,
            being at <placeName>Ilford</placeName> one day, he met a man who told him that he had
            fallen in with a woman who positively assured him that she knew <rs ref="ghost">a girl who had fairly
            lost her old wits by the sight of the ghost</rs>, and had been provided with a new set of
            wits so entirely different that it was hard to believe she was the same person. A
            servant girl in <placeName ref="#kensington">Kensington</placeName>, we are informed,
            has been so powerfully affected that her person has swelled so enormously that her
            mistress has dismissed her as unfit for household work.</p>
         <p>A gentleman in <placeName ref="#hammersmith">Hammersmith</placeName> has horns growing
            on his head, which are generally supposed to be produced by one of Springheeled Jack’s
            incantations. But the strangest rumour of all is this, that the present hard frost is
            owing to the immense consumption of heat by the apparition, which, having lately left
            the furnace underneath presented such an attraction to the fiery element above, that he
            has absorbed it all for his own private satisfaction, leaving us to experience the same
            shivering sensation which he felt himself when he came up amongst us.</p>
         <p>We have been privately informed that there are <rs ref="pol rel"><persName ref="#thug">Thugs
               in England</persName>; and several in Ireland; and that the <persName ref="#thug">Thugs in Ireland</persName> have joined the
               Trades’ Associations, and are privately proselytizing the sons of Erin to the worship
               of Kalee.</rs> This report, which is believed in certain circles, has probably given
            rise to the rumour, which we lately heard repeated by a respectable gentleman, that
            Springheeled Jack was a Thug. It is well known that the Thugs pride themselves in
            killing without shedding blood. The Irish do not understand this doctrine. <rs ref="or">It seems so unnatural. The Thugs have,
               therefore, experienced considerable difficulty in the Green Isle in propagating their
               principles.</rs> In this country it seemed impossible to pursue their favourite
            system of social amelioration, on account of the vigilance of the police. They,
            therefore, so says the report, have resorted to this ghostly method of sacrificing to
            their favourite Kalee, the goddess of bloodless death.</p>
         <p>We have no faith in this idle tale; but we can assure our readers that we have heard,
            from a respectable quarter, that a woman has brought forth a child with horns on its
            head, and sharp-pointed nails on its fingers. <rs ref="pol">The father
               swears it is not his, and the wife quotes the Poor Law Amendment Bill to prove that
               it is.</rs></p>
         <p><rs ref="pol">We hope the Bishop of London is exercising his ghostly jurisdiction in the
               diocese. Mayhap this Springheeled Jack is the doctor himself. Darkness is the natural
               element of a Bishop. No man burneth a candle in daylight. And as Bishops’ are
               candles, they are made only for dark times, and dark places, being entirely
               extinguished when the broad glare of the day-star beams upon them. Bishops were very
               luminous in the dark ages. Now-a-days one can scarcely see them. They are like fires
               which the sun-beams have played upon. It is natural enough that these men should
               desire to restore their ghostly influence over men’s minds. But it requires an
               original genius to discover and put in practice the true and only method.</rs>
            Blomfield is an enterprising <emph>spirited</emph> fellow, and has a large fraternity of
            ghostly attendants, whose services he can at all times command to carry out his
            <rs ref="rel pol">spiritual plans of ecclesiastical government</rs>. <rs ref="ghost">Now the ghost is evidently a combination
            of individuals.</rs> It is seen in Kensington, Hammersmith, Ilford, Pockham, Highgate, and
            Greenwich, at one and the same time. The most natural inference, therefore, is that it
            is a clerical manœuvre. <rs ref="rel">The churches, we understand, have been rather better attended
            on account of it</rs>, and we ourselves have heard of <rs ref="rel">one woman who was so frightened that
            she went to church on Sunday last to charm away the evil one from herself and children,
            who had not been in church for twelvemonths previous</rs>.</p>
         <p>But how to account for the <emph>springing</emph> is difficult. There is something
            beyond flesh and blood, and clerical manœuvring, in this. <rs ref="ghost">There must be a real ghost in
            pay somehow.</rs> This we are told is now not so difficult as it has been for a century or
            two. Astrology is reviving. We know several sorcerers in London, and one man assured us
            that he has raised hosts of devils, and made them sit till he drew their pictures. He
            also showed us the pictures of several, and amongst the rest <emph>Cashiel</emph> riding
            on a dragon, a fierce looking fellow. He brings them up in a glass, but he thinks it not
            impossible for a person to make them move about in the open air.</p>
         <p><rs ref="ghost">Now the girl at Ilford swears that she saw the moon through the ghost’s head.</rs></p>
         <p>The Lord Mayor has received several important letters on the subject, and promises to do
            his utmost to throw light upon it. But it ain’t arsenic candles, we can assure his
            Lordship, that will remove an evil so disastrous as this. The fact is, some people
            ascribe it wholly to the arsenic candles. One servant girl, on opening a door, had the
            flame of the candle blown in her face. She fainted, and fell on the floor; and when she
            recovered, she said she saw a man with an owl’s face, all covered with feathers, from
            head to foot. The doctor gave her a turn out, and she is as well as ever; but the candle
            being examined, it was found to be a wax-end— perhaps one of the Lord Mayor’s best. If
            the spirit of arsenic has actually been embodied and personified, it will be a heavy
            crime for the chandlers to answer for. The bar, in our opinion, is more suitable than
            the bench for such gentlemen.</p>
         <p>But two lawyers have kindly offered their services to lay this devil. The Lord Mayor is
            highly gratified with this promised aid. If a lawyer cannot lay the devil, he has little
            faith in a parson. <rs ref="rel">But his Lordship is no Christian to talk thus.</rs> <q>If satan cast out
            satan, how can his kingdom stand?</q> It is another manœuvre to inveigle the public.
            Better employ Joseph Ady at once to hunt it down—or to raise a subscription to lay it.
            We have no doubt that Joseph would make a good job of it, with the Lord Mayor’s forged
            seal attached to his Commission. But we must pause for want of space. Our friend
            M‘Dougal, is out after this son of the mist, and most probably will make important
            discoveries.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
