<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/hoax.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GH-BRITP-18640514"> 
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Science: A new <q>Ghost</q></title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Originally published by</resp>
               <name>The London Reader</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
               <name>Gabi Keane</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This project encoded newspaper and periodical articles on ghost hoaxes in the Victorian period. This publication of the text serves as data in a collaborative laboratory edition for the 2022 NEH Institute "Advanced digital editing: modeling the text and making the edition" at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Ghost hoaxes in 19th-century British news media</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>All texts in this collection were sourced from British periodical and newspaper
               archives, transcribed,and encoded. The citation below was provided by the archive and
               appears exactly as given.</p>
            <p><bibl>"Science: A new 'Ghost'." <publisher rend="The">London reader</publisher>: of literature, science, art and general information; <date when="1864-05-14">May 14,
               1864</date>; 3, 53; British Periodicals pg. 28.</bibl></p>
         </sourceDesc>
         
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This document is part of a larger digital collection of stories of ghost hoaxes from
               the 18th and 19th century London newspapers and periodicals. The project explores the
               beginnings of mass print media in a metropolitan area at a time when technology and
               education made reading increasingly common and inexpensive.</p>
            <p>The corpus holds 36 individual documents, which reflect a diverse mix of reporting on
               various hauntings in and around London between 1804 and 1889. The PDF and JPEGs from
               online databases were transcribed using ABBYFineReader OCR, then corrected and
               occasionally manually transcribed if document quality necessitated it. After
               normalization in plain text, all documents were upconverted to TEI XML.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>Earlier texts have had some spelling normalization due to errors in OCR.
                  Typographic em dashes are longer than modern em dashes, so all dashes have been
                  normalized to modern em dash length.</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation>
               <p>All extraneous white space used by printers to avoid overlapping with letters has
                  been removed. All quotes are simply tagged with the q tag.</p>
            </quotation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   
  <text>
   <body> 
   <p><name ref="#kinghn">Mr H. N. King</name>,
      photographer, of <placeName ref="#bath">Bath</placeName>, according to a correspondent, is the inventor and patentee of a
      marvellous <rs ref="ghost">ghost</rs>. In this new invention, <name ref="#kinghn">Mr. King</name> claims superiority in every respect over any
      <soCalled><rs ref="ghost">ghost</rs></soCalled> yet produced. Under his new arrangement he does away with the necessity of ceiling the
      stage, and can introduce any number of figures, each with perfect freedom of action, and
      without the least distortion. In addition to this, the <soCalled><rs ref="ghost">ghosts</rs></soCalled> of an entire set of furniture
      for a room can be shown at once on the stage, every object being clear and distinct. <name ref="#kinghn">Mr. King</name>,
      adds our authority, dispenses entirely with lenses as now used, and has reduced the whole to a
      formula so simple, that a child may with ease and safety work the machinery.</p></body>
  </text>
</TEI>
