<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/hoax.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GH-GNCCO-18640716">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Another Ghost Case: The Prestidigitateur</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Originally published by</resp>
               <name>The English Leader</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
               <name>Gabi Keane</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This project encoded newspaper and periodical articles on ghost hoaxes in the Victorian period. This publication of the text serves as data in a collaborative laboratory edition for the 2022 NEH Institute "Advanced digital editing: modeling the text and making the edition" at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Ghost hoaxes in 19th-century British news media</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>All texts in this collection were sourced from British periodical and newspaper
               archives, transcribed,and encoded. The citation below was provided by the archive and
               appears exactly as given.</p>
            <p><bibl>"Another Ghost Case." <publisher rend="The">English Leader</publisher>, <date when="1864-07-16">no. 7, 1864</date>. Nineteenth Century
                  Collections Online, tinyurl.galegroup.com/tinyurl/54Tbb1. Accessed 25 July
                  2017.</bibl></p>
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This document is part of a larger digital collection of stories of ghost hoaxes from
               the 18th and 19th century London newspapers and periodicals. The project explores the
               beginnings of mass print media in a metropolitan area at a time when technology and
               education made reading increasingly common and inexpensive.</p>
            <p>The corpus holds 36 individual documents, which reflect a diverse mix of reporting on
               various hauntings in and around London between 1804 and 1889. The PDF and JPEGs from
               online databases were transcribed using ABBYFineReader OCR, then corrected and
               occasionally manually transcribed if document quality necessitated it. After
               normalization in plain text, all documents were upconverted to TEI XML.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>Earlier texts have had some spelling normalization due to errors in OCR.
                  Typographic em dashes are longer than modern em dashes, so all dashes have been
                  normalized to modern em dash length.</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation>
               <p>All extraneous white space used by printers to avoid overlapping with letters has
                  been removed. All quotes are simply tagged with the q tag.</p>
            </quotation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>In the Court of Exchequer last week, an action for breach of agreement was brought by
            Mr. Hoffman for furnishing a conjuring apparatus to Professor Herman. Mr. Serjeant
            Simons and Mr. Peter Williams were counsel for the plaintiff. The defendant did not
            appear either in person or by counsel.</p>
         <p>The plaintiff, John William Hoffman, was the inventor of conjuring tricks and optical
            illusions, and the defendant, Professor Gompert Herman, otherwise known as the
               <q>Prestidigitateur,</q> who, some time ago, gave performances at the Princess’s
            Theatre. In September last Mr. Hoffman entered into an agreement in writing to furnish
            the professor with an entirely new trick, which was to produce a ghost, for a sum of 100
            guineas, and £150 additional for the expense of making the apparatus. The trick was of
            this nature. Professor Herman was to borrow a watch from one of the audience, and to
            accidentally smash it to pieces. While apologising for the mishap a hamper was brought
            in, and an inordinate number of bottles of champagne taken out of it. The audience were
            treated to some champagne, and while the bottles were being replaced, a young Bacchus,
            in a drunken state, jumped out of the hamper. The conjuror attempted to put him in
            again, but it proved far too small; and then came upon the scene the conjuror’s double,
            in the shape of a ghost, which was afterwards converted into a flame. At this flame he
            fired off a pistol containing the remains of the smashed watch, and then there suddenly
            reappeared Bacchus with a perfect watch, which the astonished victim of the trick at
            once recognised as his own. The plaintiff had been put to considerable expense in
            preparing the trick, including the engagement of a lad as a contortionist, who could
            double up his body in a much smaller compass than nature intended; but he had only
            received about £60. The plaintiff applied for the settlement of his claim when he had
            fulfilled his part of the agreement, but the defendant’s fortunes at the Princess’s
            having declined he neglected to pay the money. The present action was brought to recover
            £136 13s. 9d., for which the jury, under the direction of the learned judge, immediately
            found a verdict.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
