<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/hoax.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GH-GNCCO-18571121">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Another Stockwell Ghost Case</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Originally published by</resp>
               <name>The Leader</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
               <name>Gabi Keane</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This project encoded newspaper and periodical articles on ghost hoaxes in the Victorian period. This publication of the text serves as data in a collaborative laboratory edition for the 2022 NEH Institute "Advanced digital editing: modeling the text and making the edition" at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Ghost hoaxes in 19th-century British news media</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>All texts in this collection were sourced from British periodical and newspaper
               archives, transcribed,and encoded. The citation below was provided by the archive and
               appears exactly as given.</p>
            <p><bibl>"Another Stockwell Ghost Case." <publisher rend="The">Leader</publisher>, <date when="1857-11-21">21 Nov. 1857</date>, p. 1112+. Nineteenth
                  Century Collections Online, https://bit.ly/2ZRTPCK. Accessed 4 Jan.
               2020.</bibl></p>
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This document is part of a larger digital collection of stories of ghost hoaxes from
               the 18th and 19th century London newspapers and periodicals. The project explores the
               beginnings of mass print media in a metropolitan area at a time when technology and
               education made reading increasingly common and inexpensive.</p>
            <p>The corpus holds 36 individual documents, which reflect a diverse mix of reporting on
               various hauntings in and around London between 1804 and 1889. The PDF and JPEGs from
               online databases were transcribed using ABBYFineReader OCR, then corrected and
               occasionally manually transcribed if document quality necessitated it. After
               normalization in plain text, all documents were upconverted to TEI XML.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>Earlier texts have had some spelling normalization due to errors in OCR.
                  Typographic em dashes are longer than modern em dashes, so all dashes have been
                  normalized to modern em dash length.</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation>
               <p>All extraneous white space used by printers to avoid overlapping with letters has
                  been removed. All quotes are simply tagged with the q tag.</p>
            </quotation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>A case similar to that of the celebrated <rs ref="stockwellghost">Stockwell ghost</rs>
            has led to some proceedings at the Southwark police-court. A working man named Baker,
            and his wife and daughter, occupied a house in the neighbourhood of <placeName
               ref="londonstreet">London-street, Dockhead,</placeName> and for some time past the
            man and woman have been alarmed by singular noises occurring in various parts of the
            house, and by the breaking of crockery, glass, &amp;c., which were thrown about without
            any apparent cause. Baker and his wife were greatly scared by these mysteries, and at
            length spoke to a gentleman connected with the District Visiting Society, who instituted
            inquiries and soon found out the truth of the matter. The daughter, a girl of twelve,
            had fallen into bad habits, and, to prevent her wandering about the streets, she was
            confined to the house. She therefore revenged herself by breaking the crockery-ware; to
            effect which unperceived, she fastened thin hairs to the dishes, jugs, and glasses, and
            dexterously jerked them down. She would do this in the presence of her mother, who was
            so much the victim of superstitious fears, that she never perceived the cause of the
            effect. Baker himself, when giving evidence before the magistrate, said, that he and his
            wife had been frightened very much. The girl sullenly admitted what she had done, and
            said she intended to frighten her parents because they wouldn’t let her go out. She was
            sent to the House of Correction for fourteen days.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
