<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/hoax.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GH-TIMES-18040113">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Another Ghost</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Originally published by</resp>
               <name>The Times of London</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
               <name>Gabi Keane</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This project encoded newspaper and periodical articles on ghost hoaxes in the Victorian period. This publication of the text serves as data in a collaborative laboratory edition for the 2022 NEH Institute "Advanced digital editing: modeling the text and making the edition" at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Ghost hoaxes in 19th-century British news media</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>All texts in this collection were sourced from British periodical and newspaper
               archives, transcribed,and encoded. The citation below was provided by the archive and
               appears exactly as given.</p>
            <p><bibl><publisher rend="The">Times</publisher> (London, England), Friday, <date when="1804-01-13">Jan 13, 1804</date>; pg. 2; Issue 5918. (629
               words)</bibl></p>
         </sourceDesc>
         
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This document is part of a larger digital collection of stories of ghost hoaxes from
               the 18th and 19th century London newspapers and periodicals. The project explores the
               beginnings of mass print media in a metropolitan area at a time when technology and
               education made reading increasingly common and inexpensive.</p>
            <p>The corpus holds 36 individual documents, which reflect a diverse mix of reporting on
               various hauntings in and around London between 1804 and 1889. The PDF and JPEGs from
               online databases were transcribed using ABBYFineReader OCR, then corrected and
               occasionally manually transcribed if document quality necessitated it. After
               normalization in plain text, all documents were upconverted to TEI XML.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>Earlier texts have had some spelling normalization due to errors in OCR.
                  Typographic em dashes are longer than modern em dashes, so all dashes have been
                  normalized to modern em dash length.</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation>
               <p>All extraneous white space used by printers to avoid overlapping with letters has
                  been removed. All quotes are simply tagged with the q tag.</p>
            </quotation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>

   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Notwithstanding the sad catastrophe occasioned by the <rs ref="hammersmith_ghost"><placeName ref="#hammersmith">Hammersmith</placeName> Ghost</rs>,
            another apparition has appeared. This nightly wanderer has chosen <placeName ref="#stjamespark">St. James’s Park</placeName> for a
            place of rendezvous, where it has been regularly seen by the soldiers on guard for
            upwards of a week past, between the hours of one and two o’clock in the morning. A few
            nights ago, it was observed at a late hour by one of the Coldstream Regiment, whilst on
            duty <placeName ref="#cockpit">near the Royal Cockpit</placeName>. The poor fellow is ready to swear he saw pass by him a
            woman without a head. The more he reflected, the more terrified he became, as he knew
            all the Park-gates had been fastened for some hours, and therefore could not suppose it
            to be some one who had got into the Park set the purpose of frightening him. The Soldier
            is sure it was not a person dressed up in a white sheet, because he could plainly
            discern the arms; and notwithstanding his great alarm he observed that the shoulders of
            the <emph>Ghost</emph> were the highest part of it; he therefore concluded, whatever it might be,
            that it had got no head. This man was considered as one of the most resolute men in the
            regiment. He was, however, taken ill immediately on his leaving guard, and the next day
            sent to the hospital, where he still remains. On Tuesday one of his comrades having
            heard of the affair, and having to take the same watch that night, was resolved to look
            out for the Ghost, and to speak to it; accordingly, at the usual time, her Ghostship
            paid him a visit. She appeared again without a head and entered the Park <placeName ref="#stjamespark">from the end of
            Queen-street near to the Royal Cockpit</placeName>. This veteran, who had often braved a
            cannon-ball, was now panic-struck at a <emph>shadow</emph>. He described himself to have got a
            <emph>locked jaw</emph>, and when he wanted to cry, <q>Who comes there,</q> he could not utter a word.
            Although he was <emph>tongue-tied</emph>, it does not appear, however, he was <emph>leg-tied</emph>, for on
            the Ghost seeming inclined to be better acquainted with him, he quitted his post, and
            ran with all possible speed to the guard-room, where he had scarce recited the dismal
            story to the Serjeant, before he fell into strong fits, and continued so ill afterwards,
            that he was taken to the hospital on Wednesday, where he is now confined to his bed.
            Another night this <emph>headless ghost</emph> held its midnight revels in an empty house behind
            the Armoury Room, and amused itself for some time in opening and shutting the windows;
            but what is most remarkable of all, the apparition called out as lustily for a light, as
            if it had got a boatswain’s <emph>head</emph> upon its shoulders. Having finished its pranks in the
            empty dwelling, the soldier who was a witness to this novel scene, observed this
            dreadful spectre to pass by him at the distance of 50 yards, and <emph>walked</emph> over the <emph>park
            paling</emph> as easy as he could step over a <emph>straw</emph>; it then proceeded towards <placeName ref="#stjamesscanal">the Canal</placeName>,
            and vanished from his sight. There are several other stories current amongst the
            Coldstream Regiment respecting the nocturnal gambols of this <emph>Ghost</emph>, and it is said,
            that several soldiers besides those already mentioned, have seen, whilst on duty, what
            they suppose a supernatural phantom, which has so affected them, that they were taken
            ill immediately, and sent to the hospital; but, be that as it may, it is an undoubted
            fact, that two sentinels have been sent there from the effects of fright, whatever may
            have been the real cause of it.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
