<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/hoax.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GH-TIMES-18040119">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Another Ghost!</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Originally published by</resp>
               <name>The Times</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
               <name>Gabi Keane</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This project encoded newspaper and periodical articles on ghost hoaxes in the
               Victorian period. This publication of the text serves as data in a collaborative
               laboratory edition for the 2022 NEH Institute "Advanced digital editing: modeling the
               text and making the edition" at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Ghost hoaxes in 19th-century British news media</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>All texts in this collection were sourced from British periodical and newspaper
               archives, transcribed,and encoded. The citation below was provided by the archive and
               appears exactly as given.</p>
            <p>
               <bibl>ANOTHER GHOST!-A Gentleman of great respectability in the service of the East
                  India. <publisher rend="The">Times</publisher> (London, England), Thursday, <date
                     when="1804-01-19">Jan 19, 1804</date>; pg. 3; Issue 5923. (591 words)</bibl>
            </p>
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This document is part of a larger digital collection of stories of ghost hoaxes from
               the 18th and 19th century London newspapers and periodicals. The project explores the
               beginnings of mass print media in a metropolitan area at a time when technology and
               education made reading increasingly common and inexpensive.</p>
            <p>The corpus holds 36 individual documents, which reflect a diverse mix of reporting on
               various hauntings in and around London between 1804 and 1889. The PDF and JPEGs from
               online databases were transcribed using ABBYFineReader OCR, then corrected and
               occasionally manually transcribed if document quality necessitated it. After
               normalization in plain text, all documents were upconverted to TEI XML.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>Earlier texts have had some spelling normalization due to errors in OCR.
                  Typographic em dashes are longer than modern em dashes, so all dashes have been
                  normalized to modern em dash length.</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation>
               <p>All extraneous white space used by printers to avoid overlapping with letters has
                  been removed. All quotes are simply tagged with the q tag.</p>
            </quotation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>A Gentleman of great repeatability in the service of the East India Company, among other
            ingenious pursuits, applied himself to the study of anatomy. A human skull, which had
            been placed for sometime in his closet, was, during his absence on a summer excursion,
            observed frequently to move. Like the secret in the Agreeable Surprise, this alarming
            tale of mystery became <emph>secret pro bono publico</emph>. The servants told it to the
            neighbours, and the skull was attended by a croud of visitors. At length one of them,
            more bold than <q>his fellows,</q> made a desperate snatch at the head, when the
            visionary mountain brought forth a mouse, which had actually brought forth a litter of
            young ones in the <emph>caput mortuum !!!</emph></p>
         <p>Inspite of all the cunning of BONAPARTE, the rapture of his <emph>Sçuvans</emph> in
            India, proved that the knowing ones were be to taken in!</p>
         <p>The French, infantry destined for this country, have helmets with steel guards, reaching
            over their shoulders, to ward off the cuts of cavalry. We fancy, with all their
            precaution, they will in the end find themselves <emph>over-reached</emph>.</p>
         <p>The Newspapers are now become quite silent about <emph>Carlo</emph>. According to the
            vulgar proverb, <q>they have not one word to throw at a dog.</q></p>
         <p>At this time of the year, all our boarding school masters and mistresses advertise their
            respective seminaries. Among the number of the latter, we notice MRS. CROSS, and a MRS.
            CRUCIFIX.</p>
         <p>It was stated in a Morning Paper last week, that a duel had been fought between Lord B.
            and Lord R. in Ireland, which proved fatal to the latter. We can only say that Letters
            have been received in town from these Nobleinen, by which it appears they are both well,
            and that no duel has taken place.</p>
         <p>Dr. GISBORNE died yesterday at his house in Clifford-street.</p>
         <p>It is worth observing, that a Newspaper is about, to be published in Wales, in the
            course of the present month, which will be the first ever published in that
            principality. This circumstance, however, is not so surprising, when it is recollected,
            that the Cambro-Britons have received such constant supplies of the Bristol, Shrewsbury,
            Chester, and Liverpool Papers, not to speak of those from the Metropolis. As an
            historical fact, however, and a proof of the desire of increasing the means of
            circulating general knowledge (even during a time of war) it is deserving of public
            notice. Whatever may have been the nature or the value of the arguments, used by some
            persons, against the multiplicity of Newspapers, they have certainly become, in spite of
            any temporary or local evil, the great medium of communication, for the public, on every
            matter of public interest. A Newspaper is only a sort of epistolary correspondence,
            carried on almost as quick as conversation, between all the subjects of the empire, as
            well remote as near. Its uses too, in its circulation abroad, must be extensive, as it
            conveys to all nations, not only the important public occurrences of this country, but a
            picture of the Opinions, wishes, and principles of the greatest nation (in the true
            sense of that word) that exists on the face of the globe. We cannot help expressing our
            own satisfaction, in observing, that The Times maintains such a character on the
            Continent, that all the public matter contained in it, is translated into German, and
            published in that language.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
