<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/hoax.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GH-19CUK-18441005">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>A Pomeranian Ghost</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Originally published by</resp>
                    <name>The Penny Satirist</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
                    <name>Gabi Keane</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>This project encoded newspaper and periodical articles on ghost hoaxes in the Victorian period. This publication of the text serves as data in a collaborative laboratory edition for the 2022 NEH Institute "Advanced digital editing: modeling the text and making the edition" at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>Ghost hoaxes in 19th-century British news media</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>All texts in this collection were sourced from British periodical and newspaper
                    archives, transcribed,and encoded. The citation below was provided by the
                    archive and appears exactly as given.</p>
                <p><bibl>"A POMERANIAN GHOST." <publisher rend="The">Penny Satirist</publisher>, <date when="1844-10-05">5 Oct. 1844</date>, p. 4. 19th Century
                        UK Periodicals, http://tinyurl.galegroup.com/tinyurl/6qmuYX. Accessed 8 Aug.
                        2018.</bibl></p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This document is part of a larger digital collection of stories of ghost hoaxes
                    from the 18th and 19th century London newspapers and periodicals. The project
                    explores the beginnings of mass print media in a metropolitan area at a time
                    when technology and education made reading increasingly common and
                    inexpensive.</p>
                <p>The corpus holds 36 individual documents, which reflect a diverse mix of
                    reporting on various hauntings in and around London between 1804 and 1889. The
                    PDF and JPEGs from online databases were transcribed using ABBYFineReader OCR,
                    then corrected and occasionally manually transcribed if document quality
                    necessitated it. After normalization in plain text, all documents were
                    upconverted to TEI XML.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Earlier texts have had some spelling normalization due to errors in OCR.
                        Typographic em dashes are longer than modern em dashes, so all dashes have
                        been normalized to modern em dash length.</p>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All extraneous white space used by printers to avoid overlapping with letters
                        has been removed. All quotes are simply tagged with the q tag.</p>
                </quotation>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <p>A man had been broken on the wheel at <placeName ref="#gutskow">Gutskow</placeName>,
                because, <rs ref="rel">being tempted of Satan</rs>, he murdered a travelling
                workman. The man, however, straightway began to walk after so fearful a fashion,
                that in the evening and night season he sprang down from the wheel in his gallows
                dress whenever a cart passed by the gallows, which stands hard by the road to
                    <placeName ref="#wulgast">Wulgast</placeName>, and jumped up behind the people,
                who in horror and dismay flogged on their horses, and thereby made a great rattling
                on the log embankment which leads beside the gallows into a little wood called the
                Kraulin. <rs ref="mis">And it was a strange thing that on the same night the
                    travellers were almost always robbed or murdered on Strellin heath</rs>.
                Hereupon the magistrates had the rain taken down from the wheel end buried under the
                gallows, in hopes of laying his ghost. But it went on just as before, sitting at
                night, snow-white on the wheel, so that none durst any longer travel the road to
                Wolgast, until at last It happened that, at the time of the fair, young Rudiger von
                Nienkerken, of Mellenthin in <placeName ref="#usedom">Usedom</placeName>, who had
                been studying at Wittenberg and elsewhere, and was now on his way home, came this
                road by night with his carriage. Just before, at the inn, I myself had tried to
                persuade him to stop the night at <placeName ref="#gutskow">Gutskow</placeName>, on
                account of the <rs ref="ghost">ghost</rs>, and to go on his journey with me next
                morning, but he would not. Now as soon as this <rs ref="class">young lord</rs> drove
                along the road, he also espied <rs ref="ghost">the apparition</rs> sitting on the
                wheel, and scarcely had he passed the gallows when the ghost jumped down and ran
                after him. The driver was horribly afraid, and lashed on the horses as everybody
                else, had done before, and they, taking fright, galloped away over the log-road with
                a marvellous clatter. <rs ref="cert">Meanwhile, however, the <rs ref="class">young
                        nobleman</rs> saw by the light of the moon how that the apparition flattened
                    a ball of horse-dung whereupon it trod, and straightway felt sure within himself
                    that it was no ghost.</rs> Whereupon he called to the driver to stop; and, as
                the man would not hearken to him, he sprang out of his carriage, drew his rapier,
                and hastened to attack the ghost. When the ghost saw this he would have turned and
                fled; but the <rs ref="class">young nobleman</rs> gave him such a blow on the head
                with his fist that be fell upon the ground with a loud wailing. <emph>Summa:</emph>
                the <rs ref="class">young lord</rs>, having called back his driver, dragged the
                ghost into the town again, where he turned out to be a shoemaker called <persName
                    ref="#schweim">Schweim</persName>. I also, on seeing such a great crowd, ran
                thither with many others, to look at the fellow. He trembled like an aspen leaf; and
                when he was roughly told to make a clean breast, whereby he might, peradventure,
                save his own life, if it appeared that he had murdered no one, he confessed that he
                had got his wife to make him a gallows' dress, which he had put on, and had sat on
                the wheel before the dead man, when, from the darkness and the distance, no one
                could see that the two were sitting there together; and this he did more especially
                when he knew that a cart was going from the town to <placeName ref="#wolgast"
                    >Wolgast</placeName>. When the cart came by, and he jumped down and ran after
                it, all the people were so affrighted that they no longer kept their eyes upon the
                gallows, but only on him, flogged the horses and galloped with much noise and
                clatter over the log embankment. This was heard by his fellows in <placeName
                    ref="#strellin">Strellin</placeName> and <placeName ref="#dam"
                    >Dammbecke</placeName> (two villages which are about three fourths on the way),
                who held themselves ready to unyoke the horses and to plunder the travellers when
                they came up with them. That after the dead man was buried he could play the ghost
                more easily still, &amp;c. <rs ref="justice">That this was the whole truth, and that
                    he himself had never robbed, still less murdered, any one; wherefore be begged
                    to be forgiven: that all the robberies and murders which had happened had been
                    done by hit fellows alone. Ah, thou cunning knave! But I heard afterwards that
                    he and his fellows were broken on the wheel together, as was but fair.</rs></p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
