<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/hoax.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GH-GNCCO-18750703">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Substantial Ghost Story</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Originally published by</resp>
               <name>The People’s Advocate, Altrincham Guardian</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
               <name>Gabi Keane</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This project encoded newspaper and periodical articles on ghost hoaxes in the Victorian period. This publication of the text serves as data in a collaborative laboratory edition for the 2022 NEH Institute "Advanced digital editing: modeling the text and making the edition" at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Ghost hoaxes in 19th-century British news media</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>All texts in this collection were sourced from British periodical and newspaper
               archives, transcribed,and encoded. The citation below was provided by the archive and
               appears exactly as given.</p>
            <p><bibl>"A Substantial Ghost Story." <publisher rend="The">People's Advocate</publisher>, <date when="1875-07-03">3 July 1875</date>. Nineteenth Century
                  Collections Online, http://tinyurl.galegroup.com/tinyurl/7M6cU4. Accessed 10 Oct.
                  2018.</bibl></p>
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This document is part of a larger digital collection of stories of ghost hoaxes from
               the 18th and 19th century London newspapers and periodicals. The project explores the
               beginnings of mass print media in a metropolitan area at a time when technology and
               education made reading increasingly common and inexpensive.</p>
            <p>The corpus holds 36 individual documents, which reflect a diverse mix of reporting on
               various hauntings in and around London between 1804 and 1889. The PDF and JPEGs from
               online databases were transcribed using ABBYFineReader OCR, then corrected and
               occasionally manually transcribed if document quality necessitated it. After
               normalization in plain text, all documents were upconverted to TEI XML.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>Earlier texts have had some spelling normalization due to errors in OCR.
                  Typographic em dashes are longer than modern em dashes, so all dashes have been
                  normalized to modern em dash length.</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation>
               <p>All extraneous white space used by printers to avoid overlapping with letters has
                  been removed. All quotes are simply tagged with the q tag.</p>
            </quotation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>﻿A story reaches us from <placeName ref="#sale">Sale</placeName>, which for some days
            caused intense excitement; but owing to the confession of a half hearted <q>slavey</q>
            it is irrevocably consigned to the limbo of exploded deceptions. For some time past
               <placeName ref="amb">the occupants of a house in a certain road in Sale</placeName>
            have been alarmed by mysterious ringings of the front door bell at hours seasonable and
            unseasonable, by handwriting on the front door, by disturbances of the window frames,
            and the shattering of glass, from some unknown cause. Of all these so called phenomena
            the front door bell was the greatest offender, and when the inmates went to answer and
            welcome some thought-of visitor they were met by that lovely view of <placeName
               ref="#brooklands">Brooklands</placeName> and delightful scent from <placeName
               ref="#sale_canal">the canal bank</placeName> which the residents in that locality so
            well know and so little appreciate. At length the police were communicated with, but
            even the proverbial astuteness of the Cheshire Constabulary was thoroughly baffled. The
            bells rang, the writing wrote, and the window shuddered and shook as usual, and no one,
            as far as they could see, did it. A Manchester friend of the family set about to solve
            the mystery, and clear this haunted house from the stigma attaching to it. Stealthily
            did he lie in ambush in the front garden and patiently bide the issue. Strange to say,
            an active and intelligent officer—we will call him A 1 for the sake of distinction was
            of the same mind as King Cotton, and thought he would solve the mystery too. Precisely
            at midnight, when innumerable ghosts are supposed to promenade, the active and
            intelligent, in plain clothes, accompanied by his faithful dog (breed not stated)
            approached the house with stealthy steps. Cotton was wide awake. A 1 crept in and
            approached the window. Cotton sprang out the instant, and, seizing A 1 by the throat, a
            contest commenced which almost baffles description. Cotton was certain in his own mind
            he had got the culprit; A 1 was as equally certain that this was a mistake, and that he
            was an officer of which <placeName ref="#sale">Sale</placeName> might justly be proud.
            But there was no time for explanation. Cotton strengthened his grip —A 1 seized Cotton—
            the dog, Cotton’s unmentionables. The fray waxed fast and furious; the combatants roared
            and gripped, making night hideous with their roaring, and rousing the neighbourhood.
            After a quarter of an hour’s lugging a truce was called, the dog in the meantime having
            torn the aforesaid unmentionables into shreds; mutual explanations ensued—the police
            officer returned to duty and Cotton to <placeName ref="#manchester"
               >Manchester</placeName> with a keen appreciation of his first endeavours at
            ghost-laying. One would have thought after all this attention the ghost would have
            removed to more solitary and congenial quarters. But this was not the case. On the other
            hand, it worked away harder than ever, until it was past all bearing. A gentleman, who
            is exceedingly clever as an amateur detective, undertook to solve the mystery, and
            ultimately success was in this respect achieved. The first night’s experience tended to
            convince him that the <q>phenomena</q> were caused by a party inside the house;
            suspicion fell on the <q>slavey,</q> who, however, strongly denied any connection there
            with. The threat of immediate legal proceedings only tended to induce her to make a full
            confession, which she did, and also explained the way in which she had produced the
               <q>manifestations.</q> It is unnecessary to say that since her discharge the family
            have enjoyed perfect peace.—<placeName ref="#altrincham">Altrincham</placeName>
            Guardian.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
