<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/hoax.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GH-TIMES-18300708">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Bermondsey Ghost</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Originally published by</resp>
               <name>The Times</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
               <name>Gabi Keane</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This project encoded newspaper and periodical articles on ghost hoaxes in the Victorian period. This publication of the text serves as data in a collaborative laboratory edition for the 2022 NEH Institute "Advanced digital editing: modeling the text and making the edition" at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Ghost hoaxes in 19th-century British news media</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>All texts in this collection were sourced from British periodical and newspaper
               archives, transcribed,and encoded. The citation below was provided by the archive and
               appears exactly as given.</p>
            <p><bibl>The Bermondsey Ghost. <publisher rend="The">Times</publisher> (London, England), Thursday, <date when="1830-07-08">Jul 08, 1830</date>; pg.
                  6; Issue 14273. (780 words)</bibl></p>
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This document is part of a larger digital collection of stories of ghost hoaxes from
               the 18th and 19th century London newspapers and periodicals. The project explores the
               beginnings of mass print media in a metropolitan area at a time when technology and
               education made reading increasingly common and inexpensive.</p>
            <p>The corpus holds 36 individual documents, which reflect a diverse mix of reporting on
               various hauntings in and around London between 1804 and 1889. The PDF and JPEGs from
               online databases were transcribed using ABBYFineReader OCR, then corrected and
               occasionally manually transcribed if document quality necessitated it. After
               normalization in plain text, all documents were upconverted to TEI XML.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>Earlier texts have had some spelling normalization due to errors in OCR.
                  Typographic em dashes are longer than modern em dashes, so all dashes have been
                  normalized to modern em dash length.</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation>
               <p>All extraneous white space used by printers to avoid overlapping with letters has
                  been removed. All quotes are simply tagged with the q tag.</p>
            </quotation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>For some days past the <placeName ref="#grangeroad">Grange-road,
            Bermondsey</placeName>, has been the scene of much commotion, owing to a report, very
            generally circulated, that a ghost was in the habit of making its appearance nightly at
            the window of an uninhabited house in that neighbourhood. The dwelling in which this
            nocturnal vister was declared, and believed by many, to have been seen, was a few years
            ago the residence of a clergyman of very eccentric habits. He lived a very retired life,
            and for many years preceding his death was scarcely ever seen by his neighbours. On
            these occasions that he <sic>exhibted</sic> himself to the public gaze, he generally
            placed himself in one of the windows of the first floor, dressed in a very grotesque
            manner, and always made a point of appearing with a huge night-cap on his head and a
            pipe in his mouth. In consequence of his eccentricities he was believed by many of his
            neighbours to be mad, although he never displayed any more symptoms of insanity than
            those above described. Since his decease, which took place a short time ago, the house
            has been shut up, and it now appears that only a few days had been suffered to elapse
            from the time that he was removed from his dwelling to his grave when a report prevailed
            that his ghost was seen in the very window he was accustomed to take his nation
            previously to his decease. This report soon gained ground, and several persons who have
            lately watched the house, declare that they have seen the ghost of the old clergyman in
            his window, enjoying himself as he was usually in the habit of doing, with his pipe of
            tobacco. Several strange stories are in circulation about the Bermondsey ghost, which
            show, however, that it does not play half the pranks that the Cock lane or Hammersmith
            ghosts played in their time: for instance, there is no rattling or noises heard from
            within; no huge stones flung at people’s heads as they pass along, or windows smashed,
            or cries and lamentations heard from within the building. Although none of these
            vagaries have been played off by <rs ref="bermondseyghost">the Bermondsey ghost</rs>,
            yet it has been asserted by persons who have entered the house after nightfall, that
            they have witnessed not only the ghost of the late occupier, but also the ghosts of
            former landlords, and that upon one occasion they all vanished together in a blaze of
            fire up the chimney, without, however, putting these who witnessed the circumstance to
            any other inconvenience than the fright inspired in their minds by such an exit. Owing
            to the various rumours thus circulated on the subject, the inhabitants of the
            Grange-road particularly have been kept in a constant state of torment from the crowds
            of people who congregate there. Every night, during the last and present weeks, the read
            in front of the house alluded to has been blocked up by men, women, and children, many
            of whom remain all night on the watch in the expectation of seeing the ghost, and the
            clamour they make while there renders it impossible for those residing near the spot to
            get any rest. To such a height has this annoyance arisen, that application was made
               <placeName ref="unknown">at the Station-house</placeName> on Monday night for the
            assistance of the police to disperse the crowd, which amounted at one period of that
            evening to at least 2,000 persons. The whole force of the division was called into
            action, and it was with considerable trouble they cleared the road; so impressed were
            many of the spectators with the idea of seeing the ghost, many of them declaring they
            had come miles for the purpose of seeing it, and complaining of the hardship of being
            compelled to go away without having a sight of the ghost. After the crowd had dispersed,
            the inspector entered the house, conceiving that some person was within who did the part
            of the ghost, but no one was found on the premises. It is supposed the story was got up
            by some interested party, to prevent the letting of the house. Orders have been given to
            the police to strictly watch the house, and prevent the crowds in future from collecting
            opposite to it, and if any unfortunate wight happens to be discovered on the premises,
            playing the part of the ghost of the late occupier, there is a punishment awaits him
            which will in all probability have the effect of checking his nocturnal wanderings, and
            make him sick of such sport; there is a horse pond in the neighbourhood, a sousing in
            which would speedily bring him to his senses.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
