<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/hoax.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GH-BRITP-18521120">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Ghost of the Cock Lane Ghost</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Originally published by</resp>
          <name>Household Words</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
          <name>Gabi Keane</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>This project encoded newspaper and periodical articles on ghost hoaxes in the Victorian period. This publication of the text serves as data in a collaborative laboratory edition for the 2022 NEH Institute "Advanced digital editing: modeling the text and making the edition" at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title>Ghost hoaxes in 19th-century British news media</title>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>All texts in this collection were sourced from British periodical and newspaper archives,
          transcribed,and encoded. The citation below was provided by the archive and appears
          exactly as given.</p>
        <p><bibl>THE GHOST OF THE COCK LANE GHOST. <publisher>Household words</publisher> / conducted by Charles Dickens;
          Saturday, <date when="1852-11-20">Nov 20, 1852</date>; 6, 139; British Periodicals pg. 217.</bibl></p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>This document is part of a larger digital collection of stories of ghost hoaxes from the
          18th and 19th century London newspapers and periodicals. The project explores the
          beginnings of mass print media in a metropolitan area at a time when technology and
          education made reading increasingly common and inexpensive.</p>
        <p>The corpus holds 36 individual documents, which reflect a diverse mix of reporting on
          various hauntings in and around London between 1804 and 1889. The PDF and JPEGs from
          online databases were transcribed using ABBYFineReader OCR, then corrected and
          occasionally manually transcribed if document quality necessitated it. After normalization
          in plain text, all documents were upconverted to TEI XML.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <normalization>
          <p>Earlier texts have had some spelling normalization due to errors in OCR. Typographic em
            dashes are longer than modern em dashes, so all dashes have been normalized to modern em
            dash length.</p>
        </normalization>
        <quotation>
          <p>All extraneous white space used by printers to avoid overlapping with letters has been
            removed. All quotes are simply tagged with the q tag.</p>
        </quotation>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <p>We were recently invited into the company of the <rs ref="ghost">Ghost</rs> of the <rs
          ref="CLghost">Cock Lane <rs ref="ghost">Ghost</rs></rs>, by an advertisement in the Times
        Newspaper, in which a demonstrator or showman, <name ref="#stone">Mr. Stone</name>, begged
          <q who="#stonegw">leave to inform the nobility and gentry that he has just returned from
            <placeName ref="usa">the United States</placeName>, accompanied by <name
            ref="#haydenmb">Mrs. M. B. Hayden</name> for the purpose of Demonstrating the wonderful
          Phenomena known in that country as Spiritual Manifestations, and which have created the
          most intense excitement in all classes of society—<placeName ref="#r26seymour">Residence,
            Twenty-six, Upper Seymour Street, Portman Square</placeName>. Hours at home, from Eleven
          to Two and from Four to Six.</q> So the announcement ran. We had read something of the
        Rochester Rappers and of the mystery, if it be a mystery, called <soCalled><rs ref="spirit"
            >spirit</rs> knocking</soCalled> in the sentimental language of <placeName ref="usa"
          >America</placeName>. We resolved to visit Mrs. Hayden, and knock up an acquaintance with
        the <rs ref="ghost">ghosts</rs> who meet in her apartments, <placeName ref="#r26seymour">No.
          Twenty-six, Upper Seymour Street, Portman Square.</placeName> We ourselves happened to be
        out of <rs ref="spirit">spirits</rs>, therefore perhaps we made a wise resolve.</p>
      <p>Yet had we gone for mirth into such company, we should have fared as ill as he who for a
        midnight jest entered his father’s sepulchre to sup alone among the dead. If it be true, as
        the believers in the <soCalled><rs ref="spirit">spirit</rs> knockings</soCalled> tell us,
        that the <rs ref="spirit">spirits</rs> of beloved friends whom we have lost speak to us by a
        noise of rapping, then our most solemn feelings and our tenderest emotions are awakened by
        the act of positive communion with the dead.</p>
      <p>If it be otherwise—if that which is the <rs ref="religious">holiest ground within the human
          heart be through such exhibitions dug into for gold by coarse impostors—if the simple
          questioner who with trembling nerves believes that she is brought into the presence of an
          angel mother with whom it is a foretaste of Heaven to converse—if she be played upon by
          cheats who laugh under their sleeves at her credulity and turn her money in their
          pockets,—then such cheating is no matter for amusement.</rs> That is an impiety and
        wickedness far exceeding the measure of an ordinary fraud, which</p>
      <ab>
        <lb/>trades upon our solemn love towards the dead— <cit>
          <lb/>
          <quote>In slight of that forbearance and reserve <lb/>Which common human-heartedness
            inspires, <lb/>And mortal ignorance and frailty claim, <lb/>Upon this sacred ground, if
            nowhere else.</quote>
          <bibl
            source="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Page:The_Excursion,_Wordsworth,_1814.djvu/302"
              ><name ref="#wordsworth">William Wordsworth</name>, The Excursion, 1814.</bibl>
        </cit>
      </ab>
      <p>There have often been people impelled, out of the ignorance and coarseness of their
        natures, to the forging of clumsy tales, in which they themselves, together with the <name
          ref="rel">Supreme Being</name>, are the chief actors. Not many weeks ago two cowherd’s
        children in <placeName ref="france">France</placeName>—in consequence of information
        received direct from the <rs ref="rel">Virgin Mary</rs>—became accredited by Infallibility
        itself as new apostles. <ref
          source="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=njp.32101076875358;view=1up;seq=78">Not
          many months ago a girl in Suffolk dealt divine information through the neighbourhood,
          attesting her inspiration by total abstinence from food.</ref> We may read in pamphlets
        printed centuries ago, how in some parts of Switzerland and France a divine epidemic seized
        upon the children, how they preached powerfully in their sleep, and were attended at their
        bedsides by large congregations; or we may read of <q>the German Lazarus</q> who delivered a
        long list of messages from Heaven, and attested his mission by professing that he never
        slept. This Lazarus was constantly caught napping; hut he explained the fact to his own
        honour, by stating that his parents were so much distressed by his incessant wakefulness,
        that he found it necessary to feign sleep occasionally, for the comfort of their minds.</p>
      <p>Knocking or Rapping <rs ref="ghost">ghosts</rs> are no new imposition. In a relation of
        facts concerning <soCalled><rs ref="spirit">spirit</rs>-knockings</soCalled> written in an
        American pamphlet that is now before us, <q>by <name ref="#robinsonj">J.
          Robinson</name>,</q> we are told much, not only of the knockings of the unseen beings, but
        also of the imitations of evil <rs ref="spirit">spirits</rs>, which, <q who="#robinsonj"
          >resembled scratching produced with the fingernails.</q> Now, will any keeper of a
        knocking <rs ref="ghost">ghost</rs>, or any lady or gentleman who has taken up the trade of
        communicating between knocking <rs ref="spirit">spirits</rs> and the gullible portion of the
        public (which lady or gentleman is called in the trade a <rs ref="medium">Medium</rs>), turn
        to the <ref
          source="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=njp.32101076875358;view=1up;seq=78">Annual
          Register for the year 1762</ref>, and read what is there entitled <q>A summary account of
          the proceedings in regard to some strange noises<pb/> heard the beginning of the year at a
          house in <placeName ref="#cocklane">Cock Lane, West Smithfield</placeName>.</q> Having
        read the said account, let the said <rs ref="ghost">ghost</rs>-keeper or <rs ref="medium"
          >Medium</rs> answer to our catechism on the History of Knockers in a simple way. Q. Who
        was the first <rs ref="medium">Medium</rs>? A. <name ref="#parsonse">Little Miss
          Parsons</name>. Q. Who was she? A. The daughter of the clerk of <placeName
          ref="#stsepulchre">St. Sepulchre’s</placeName>. Q. How did the <rs ref="spirit"
          >spirit</rs>-knocking in her case begin? A. Her father, the clerk, had taken as lodgers a
        gentleman and lady, and in the absence of the gentleman, little <name ref="#parsone">Miss
          Parsons</name> slept with the lady, who was called <name ref="#lynesf">Miss Fanny</name>.
          <name ref="lynesf">Miss Fanny</name> complained one morning that she and her bedfellow had
        been disturbed all night by noises. The noises continued, and at length excited much
        attention, but the lady and gentleman removed into the neighbourhood of <placeName
          ref="#clerkenwell">Clerkenwell</placeName> (where <name ref="#lynesf">Miss Fanny</name>
        presently died), and then the noise in Parsons’ house was discontinued. Q. You have said
        that the first <rs ref="medium">medium</rs> was little <name ref="#parsonse">Miss
          Parsons</name>; in what way do you connect the story of the <rs ref="CLghost">Cock Lane
            <rs ref="ghost">Ghost</rs></rs> with her, and discover the resemblance that exists
        between that child and yourself? A. Eighteen months after <name ref="#lynesf">Miss
          Fanny</name> left the <name ref="#parsonsr #parsonse">Parsonses</name>, and in the
        beginning of the year <date>1762</date>, the noises recommenced, and it is recorded of
        little <name ref="#parsonse">Miss Parsons</name>, that the child, upon certain knockings and
        scratchings, which seemed to proceed from beneath her bedstead, was sometimes thrown into
        violent fits and agitations; and a woman attendant, or the father, <name ref="#parsonsr">Mr.
          Parsons</name>, put questions to the <rs ref="spirit">spirit</rs> or <rs ref="ghost"
          >ghost</rs>, as it was supposed by the credulous to be, and they had also dictated how
        many knocks should serve for an answer, either in the affirmative or negative. Now this
        plan, invented by little <name ref="parsonse">Miss Parsons</name>, differs in no material
        respect from my own. Q. What was the object of <name ref="#parsonse">Miss Parsons</name> and
        her friends? A. The <rs ref="ghost">ghost</rs> declared itself to be the <rs ref="ghost"
          >ghost</rs> of the deceased <name ref="#lynesf">Miss Fanny</name>, and its business was to
        accuse the gentleman of having <interp>poisoned her by giving to her arsenic in a glass of
          purl</interp> when she was ill of small-pox. Q. Was not that very wicked? A. It was very
        capitally done. Little <name ref="#parsonse">Miss Parsons</name> was removed from house to
        house, but the noises followed her, the <rs ref="ghost">ghost</rs> protesting that she would
        follow her wherever she went, and the exhibition was exceedingly attractive; for,as it is
        said in the Annual Register,<q>numbers of persons of fortune and character, and several
          clergymen, assisted at the vagaries of the invisible knocker and scratcher.</q> Q. Were
        the pretensions of this girl seriously tested? A. Yes, they were, she was tied up in a
        hammock with her feet and hands bound apart from one another, but the <rs ref="ghost"
          >ghost</rs> refused then to make its knockings audible. The <rs ref="spirit">spirit</rs>
        had also promised by an affirmative knock, that it would attend three gentlemen into the
        vault under St. John’s church, and knock in their presence upon the coffin (<name
          ref="#lynesf">Miss Fanny’s</name>) wherein lay her body. Q. I think I remember some lines
        by Churchill on the subject of this expedition to the vault. Can you repeat some of them? A.
        I can, for I have found them in <rs ref="paper?">the Register</rs>. They begin <q>Dark was
          the night,</q> and after exactly a hundred lines of exordium by which the expectation of
        the reader is prepared, they proceed in ten lines more to disclaim all straining after false
        effect, and then relate in a single couplet the adventure of the descent to the vault:</p>
      <p><q>Silent all three went in; about All three turn’d silent, and came out.</q></p>
      <p>Q. What was the end of the story of the <ref
          source="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=njp.32101076875358;view=1up;seq=498">Cock
          Lane <rs ref="ghost">Ghost</rs></ref>? A. The condemnation of poor Mr. Parsons to the
        pillory. Q. May you not conclude from this, that <rs ref="rap"><rs ref="spirit"
          >spirit</rs>-knocking</rs> is unsuited to the genius of this country? A. I do not know.
        The people pitied <name ref="#parsonsr">Mr. Parsons</name>, and no egg was lifted up against
        him.</p>
      <p>The <name ref="#fox">Fox</name> family, by whom this <rs ref="rap">ghostly rapping</rs> was
        revived in America not many years ago, were so successful in their venture —retiring very
        soon upon a little independence —that the <rs ref="spirit">spirit</rs> trade, as carried on
        by them, became at once an established business. A <rs ref="ghost">ghost</rs> in <placeName
          ref="#rhodeisland">Rhode Island</placeName>, improving upon the practice of his ancestor
        in <placeName ref="#cocklane">Cock Lane</placeName>, induced a young woman to give a dose of
        arsenic to her stepbrother. In Oneida County there sprang up an association of persons who
        had become, as they said, impressed by the intimacy which was springing up between the world
        of flesh and the world of <rs ref="spirit">spirits</rs>. These people, taking the coarse
        view of things that superstition favours, believed that we were on the point of realising
        that state of affairs of which we read in <ref
          source="http://www.gutenberg.org/cache/epub/8187/pg8187-images.html">Moore’s Loves of the
          Angels</ref>, or in <ref
          source="https://www.gutenberg.org/files/23475/23475-h/23475-h.htm#HEAVEN_AND_EARTH_TITLE"
          >Byron’s Heaven and Earth</ref>. <q><rs ref="spirit">Spirits</rs>,</q> they said, <q>are
          beginning to have power to form friendships and connexions with mortals,</q> and since, as
        they declared, it would be wicked to form contracts that might interfere with the rights,
        and defeat the unknown possible desires, of <rs ref="spirit">spirits</rs>, two hundred men
        and sixty women—having a few <rs ref="medium">mediums</rs>, no doubt, among their
        number—abolished marriages. Emboldened by the credulity of thousands who believed in the
        establishment of a direct communication with the <rs ref="spirit">spirit</rs> world, some
        blasphemous persons at <placeName ref="#auburn">Auburn</placeName>, in the State of
          <placeName ref="#newyork">New York</placeName>—determined that no dark recess of profanity,
        out of which gold could be taken, should be left unvisited— published a newspaper, conducted
        by <rs ref="rel">the Apostles and the Prophets, under the direction of the Lord
          Supreme!</rs> We quote from the prospectus, simply stating that the publication of the
        newspaper therein announced did really take place, and was, in fact, a very dreary sample of
        the lucubrations of the Rappers. <q>This publication,</q> the prospectus said, <q>is
          dictated by <rs ref="spirit">spirits</rs> out of the flesh, and by them edited,
          superintended, and controlled. Its object is, the disclosure of truth from Heaven, guiding
          mankind into<pb/> open visions of Paradise; open communication with <rs ref="spirit"
            >spirits</rs> redeemed; and proper and progressive understanding of the Holy Scriptures,
          and of the merits of Jesus Christ, from whom they originated in inspiration absolute, and
          of whom they teach, as the only Saviour of a dissevered and bewildered race. The circle of
          Apostles and Prophets are its conductors from the interior; holding control over its
          columns, and permitting no article to find place therein unless originated, dictated, or
          admitted by them; they acting under the direction of the Lord Supreme. <name>James
            Congdon</name>, <name>Charles Coventry</name>, <name>Andrew L. Wilson</name>, and
            <name>Lonson Bush</name> are its publishers and proprietor; they having become, in full
          confidence of mind, disciples of the Lord, and being present external agents of the circle
          apostolic and prophetic; acting under the direction, while faithful, as instruments for
          the distribution of truth.</q></p>
      <p>The <name ref="#fox">Fox</name> family, of Rochester, U.S., as we have already said, first
        revived in America the modern variations on the story of the <rs ref="CLghost">Cock Lane <rs
            ref="ghost">Ghost</rs></rs>. When tested fairly by a perfect stranger, their <rs
          ref="ghost">ghosts</rs> rapped out nothing but blunders: however, we are not left even to
        infer the dishonesty of their pretensions; we have clearer evidence, not only of their
        fraud, but of the way in which they practised it. <name ref="#culvern">Mrs. Norman
          Culver</name>, a relation of these <name ref="#fox">Foxes</name>, assisted in the
        depredations upon geese, and shared their secret; but was not so much a wonder of a woman as
        to keep it. She therefore made a formal deposition, certified by two respectable witnesses,
        at the town of <placeName ref="#arcadia">Arcadia</placeName>, in the province of <placeName
          ref="#newyork">New York</placeName>, in which, among other things she said, <q
          who="#haydenmb">I am, by marriage, a relation of the <name ref="#fox">Fox</name> girls;
            <rs ref="#fox">their brother</rs> married my husband’s sister. The girls have been a
          great deal at my house, and for about two years I was a very sincere believer in the <rs
            ref="rapping">rappings</rs>; but <rs ref="doubt">some things which I saw when I was
            visiting the girls at Rochester made me suspect that they were deceiving</rs>. I
          resolved to satisfy myself in some way; and some time afterwards I made a proposition to
            <name ref="#fox">Catherine</name> to assist her in producing the manifestations. I had a
          cousin visiting me from Michigan, who was going to consult the <rs ref="spirit"
            >spirits</rs>, and I told Catherine that if he intended to go to Detroit, it would be a
          great thing for them to convince him. I also told her that if I could do anything to help
          her, I would do it cheerfully. I should probably be able to answer all the questions he
          would ask, and I would do it if she would show me how to <rs ref="rap">make the raps</rs>.
          She said that as <name ref="#fox">Margaretta</name> was absent, she wanted somebody to
          help her, and that if I would become a <rs ref="medium">Medium</rs>, she would explain it
          all to me.</q> Mrs. Culver thus became an accomplice, and after she had assisted a few
        times in conveying hints that would suffice for the conquest of her sceptical cousin from
        Detroit, after a brief probation, she was admitted to a full participation in the
        mysteries.</p>
      <p>We call particular attention to her story. <q who="culvern"><rs ref="rapping">The
          raps</rs>,</q> deposed <name ref="#culvern">Mrs. Culver</name>, <q who="culvern">are
          produced with the toes. All the toes are used. After nearly a week’s practice, with
          Catherine showing me how, I could produce them perfectly myself. At first it was very hard
          work to do it. <rs ref="rap">Catherine told me to warm my feet, or put them in warm water,
            and it would then be easier work to rap; she said that she had sometimes to warm her
            feet three or four times in the course of an evening. I found that heating my feet did
            enable me to rap a great deal easier. I have sometimes produced a hundred and fifty raps
            in succession. I can rap with all the toes on both feet; it is most difficult to rap
            with the great toe.</rs> Catherine told me how to manage to answer the questions. She
          said it was generally easy enough to answer right, if the one who asked the questions
          called the alphabet.</q> And so forth, the rest of the details of trickery being all
        clumsy and common-place enough.</p>
      <p>This being the substance of our <rs ref="rapping">readings in the matter of knocking and
          rapping <rs ref="spirit">spirits</rs></rs>, we paid our visit to the London <rs
          ref="ghost">ghosts</rs> established in genteel apartments in <placeName ref="#r26seymour"
          >Upper Seymour Street, Portman Square</placeName>, very soon after we accidentally saw the
        advertisement we have set forth.</p>
      <p>We were two—<name ref="#brown">Brown</name> and <name ref="#thompson">Thompson</name>. We
        rapped at the door of the house in which the knocker lived, on a cloudy and warm evening in
        the beginning of this present November, which month began, as all the country knows, with
        days unusually dull and close. We do not idly talk about the weather, for it has a definite
        connection with our story. Having inquired whether Mr. Stone was at home, well knowing that
        he was—for he had advertised himself to be at home at that hour in the evening to all
        parties who desired an introduction to the world of <rs ref="spirit">spirits</rs> —and
        having replied to the question about our names by stating that our calling was <q
          who="#brown #thompson">in consequence of an advertisement,</q> we were conducted to a
        drawing-room, in which we found that the maid who preceded us had just lighted the fire.
          <name ref="#stonegw">Mr. Stone</name> presently appearing, solemn as became a man who knew
        his lodgings to be <rs ref="haunt">haunted</rs>, pointed courteously to the sticks that had
        begun to crackle in the grate over the lighted paper, and murmured <q who="#stonegw">We have
          had no fire here: we did not like to light it, for it is so very warm.</q> Truly no fire
        was needed, and we have a reason of our own for citing Mr. Stone’s corroboration of the
        fact.</p>
      <p>To <name ref="stonegw">Mr. Stone</name>, who <q who="#stonegw">had just returned from the
          United States</q> with <name ref="haydenm">Mrs. Hayden</name>, for the purpose of
        demonstrating those wonderful phenomena, which <q who="#stonegw">have created the most
          intense excitement in all classes or society,</q> we introduced ourselves by saying that
        we had called in consequence of an<pb/> advertisement; and we sat down before the man who
        was to bring us to the world of <rs ref="ghost">ghosts</rs>.</p>
      <p><q who="#stonegw">You are aware,</q> he said, <q who="#stonegw">that I have given a good
          deal of my attention to electro-biology?</q> We {were} aware. <q who="#stonegw"><rs
            ref="rapping">I have recently visited <placeName ref="usa">America</placeName>, where
            great sensation has been made by manifestations from the world of <rs ref="spirit"
              >spirits</rs>, made by means of a noise, like rapping. You have perhaps heard of the
            Rappers?</rs></q> Something; we came there to be informed. <q who="#stonegw">It is very
          curious,</q> said <name ref="#stonegw">Mr.Stone</name>. <q who="#stonegw">I have examined
          these manifestations with great industry, and I have arrived at the conviction that they
          are true, that they cannot be explained by human minds, that they really do emanate from
          the <rs ref="spirit">spirit</rs> world. The lady whom I have brought with me is decidedly
          the best <rs ref="medium">Medium</rs> I met with, and I, therefore, thought it well that
          the phenomena should be investigated in this country.</q> Mr. Stone here pausing and
        looking into the fire, we inquired what might be the theory of <rs ref="medium"
        >Mediums</rs>? <q who="#stonegw">It is very singular,</q> said <name ref="#stonegw">Mr.
          Stone</name>. <q who="#stonegw">There are some persons in whose sphere the <rs
            ref="spirit">spirits</rs> have more power. The grossness of matter commonly repels them,
          but there are some people whose nervous systems appear to act—you know how delicate the
          nervous system is—whose nervous systems appear to act as—we can only suppose, of course,
          we do not profess to account for these things—as conductors, as magnets, so to speak,
          whose bodies are surrounded by an atmosphere in which the <rs ref="spirit">spirits</rs>
          freely move. In the neighbourhood of such a person, <rs ref="spirit">spirits</rs> manifest
          themselves. Such a person is a <rs ref="medium">Medium</rs>.</q>
        <q who="#brown #thompson">Your <rs ref="medium">Medium</rs> sits at the table, and the <rs
            ref="ghost">ghosts</rs> rap on it?</q> we asked. <q who="#stonegw">She must sit near the
          table,</q> answered <name ref="#stonegw">Mr. Stone</name>, <q who="#stonegw">because—we
          cannot control or account for it—the <rs ref="spirit">spirits</rs> will not knock beyond
          her influence. That is the nature and the necessity of the <rs ref="medium">Medium</rs>,
          but sometimes the <rs ref="spirit">spirits</rs> will perform their promise to follow some
          person to a distant place and knock.</q> (The <rs ref="ghost">Ghost</rs> of Cock Lane, and
        the descent into the vault, to witness!) <q who="#stonegw">We were demonstrating the other
          evening at the house of a distinguished gentleman in the country, when a <rs ref="spirit"
            >spirit</rs> promised to be present to him in his library at a fixed hour. The gentleman
          listened, and, being very deaf, heard nothing; but, on holding his ear more attentively,
          he said that he distinctly thought he caught a rapping. It is very curious that the <rs
            ref="spirit">spirits</rs> accommodate themselves to deaf people. During the whole of the
          evening at this gentleman’s, the <rs ref="spirit">spirits</rs> knocked more loudly than
          usual.</q></p>
      <p>When Mr. Stone had further talked about distinguished patronage, and about the wonders that
        had been performed, one of us suggested to him, delicately, as unwilling to hurt his
        feelings by implying too roughly that a man who trembled on the confines of the other world
        could think of money, that <q who="#brown #thompson">Of<pb/> course we knew that his time
          was not wholly given to the public—that there was some honorarium,</q> the reply was
        prompt. <q who="#stonegw">One guinea each person, or five guineas for a party of ten.</q>
        This being understood, we felt our way to the inquiry, which we shaped as well as we could,
          <q who="#brown #thompson">When will the performance begin?</q> The reply being in effect
          <q who="#stonegw">We take in each party separately,</q> we signified our desire to be
        taken in as soon as possible.</p>
      <p>The door into the back drawing-room being then opened, we were introduced to Mr. and Mrs.
        Hayden, the <rs ref="medium">Medium’s</rs> husband, and the <rs ref="medium">Medium</rs>.
        Introduction having been promptly made, we were left—we, Messrs. Brown and Thompson—in the
        lady’s hands. She sat opposite to us on one side of the round table, firm as a rock.</p>
      <p>The <rs ref="medium">Medium</rs> sat not only opposite to us; but opposite to the fire. It
        had first occurred to us when we went into that back drawing-room, that the kitchen had come
        upstairs; there was such an enormous fire in the grate. Though it was so warm out of doors
        as Mr. Stone remarked, <q who="#stonegw">We did not like to light the fire</q> in the front
        drawing-room; in the back room the glowing coals were heaped into a red-hot mountain; and
        the whole atmosphere was feverish. What did <name ref="#fox">Catherine Fox</name> tell <name
          ref="#culvern">Mrs. Culver</name>? <q who="#culvern"><name ref="#fox">Catherine</name>
          told me to warm my feet, or put them in warm water, and it would then be easier work <rs
            ref="rapping">to rap</rs>: she said that she had sometimes to warm her feet three or
          four times in the course of an evening.</q></p>
      <p>As we sat in the hot room, with the table between us, opposite to the <rs ref="medium"
          >Medium</rs> who sat opposite to the fire, we had begun to ponder upon by-gone people, and
        to think how we could seize <q who="unclear">the vapoury phantoms of futurity</q> by
        questioning the <rs ref="ghost">ghosts</rs>. <q who="#brown #thompson">Can we call any <rs
            ref="spirit">spirit</rs>?</q>
        <q who="#haydenmb">You can speak only with <rs ref="spirit">spirits</rs> in the room; the
          room is full of <rs ref="spirit">spirits</rs>, and some one <rs ref="spirit">spirit</rs>
          that is present will often go out, if you wish it, to fetch you another with whom you
          desire to communicate. If you question one who is here, he will knock, or if you wait,
          some <rs ref="spirit">spirit</rs> that desires to communicate with one of us wall knock,
          and call attention to itself.</q>—<q who="#brown #thompson">How did you become a <rs
            ref="medium">Medium</rs>?</q>
        <q who="#haydenmb">I did not know what it meant when I used to hear the <rs ref="spirit"
            >spirits</rs> rapping about me in my bedroom, and following me wherever I went. They
          knocked so distinctly that my husband—who heard them also, when I was present—once got up
          and opened the parlour door, thinking that there was somebody who wanted to come in. Then
          I found out that they were <rs ref="spirit">spirits</rs> who desired to speak, and had no
          other way at present of communicating with us. If you ask them any question, and they
          answer yes, they rap; and if they answer no, they are silent. If we use letters of the
          alphabet, and point to them in succession, they will spell out sentences, and in that way
          tell what they wish.</q> This was the substance of the account given by the<pb/>
        <rs ref="medium">Medium</rs>, who added some examples of the care taken of herself by the
          <rs ref="spirit">spirits</rs>, and of a communication of importance made to her that
        morning by a deceased child; a story told to us already in the next room by Mr. Stone, whose
        version had, however, in one point, differed materially from the <rs ref="medium"
          >Medium’s</rs>.</p>
      <p>A large card lay before us on the table, upon which were printed in capitals, row after
        row, the letters of the alphabet, and in a last row the numerals 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9,
        0. There were also pencils with which we might point, and there was paper upon which we
        might write down the letters as the <rs ref="spirit">spirits</rs> I indicated them, and
        spell out the messages delivered from the other world.</p>
      <p>We were quite still. <name ref="#brown">Brown</name> was solemn; <name ref="#thompson"
          >Thompson</name> looked into vacancy; the <rs ref="medium">Medium</rs> looked down into
        the table: we were waiting for a communication from any kind <rs ref="ghost">ghost</rs> who
        would</p>
      <p><q who="#haydenmb">Be as a presence or a motion—one Among the many there.</q>—<rs ref="rap"
          >(Rap-tap.)</rs></p>
      <p><q who="#haydenmb"><rs ref="rapping">There is a rapping!</rs></q> said <name
          ref="#haydenmb">Mrs. Hayden</name> with an indistinct certainty about the expression of
        her voice, as though she really fancied that she heard <rs ref="rapping">a rapping</rs>, but
        might be in error. <q who="#haydenmb #brown #thompson"><rs ref="rap">Who knocks?</rs></q> we
        desired to know. <q who="#haydenmb">The <rs ref="spirit">spirit</rs></q> said <name
          ref="#haydenmb">Mrs. Hayden</name>, <q who="#haydenmb">desires to communicate with one of
          us.</q> Then, talking with her mouth near to the table, as though she were about to sip
        knowledge from <rs ref="spirit">spirits</rs> in the wood, she asked <q who="#haydenmb">Who
          do you speak to? Is it to me?</q>
        <rs ref="rap">(No rapping.)</rs>
        <q who="#haydenmb">Is it to this gentleman?</q>
        <rs ref="rap">(No rapping.)</rs>
        <q who="#haydenmb">Is it to that gentleman.</q>
        <rs ref="rap">(Rap-tap.)</rs> That gentleman was <name ref="#thompson">Mr. Thompson</name>,
        who was requested to converse with the <rs ref="spirit">spirit</rs>: it was probably that of
        a near relative.</p>
      <p>Says <name ref="#thompson">Thompson</name>, <q who="#thompson">Are you related to
        me?</q></p>
      <p><rs ref="rap">Rap-tap.</rs></p>
      <p><q who="#thompson">What is the relationship between us?</q></p>
      <p><name ref="#thompson">Thompson</name> is directed to take up the alphabet, begin at A, and
        point to all the letters in succession. When <name ref="#thompson">Thompson</name> points at
        M there is a <rs ref="rap">rap-tap</rs>. M is put down by his friend <name ref="#brown"
          >Brown</name> upon a piece of paper as the first letter of the word, and <name
          ref="#thompson">Thompson</name> travels through the alphabet again till he is stopped at
        O, which <name ref="#brown">Brown</name> puts down, while <name ref="#thompson"
          >Thompson</name> begins again and gets to T, where, being stopped, to save trouble, he
        says, <q who="#thompson">Is it Mother?</q>
        <rs ref="rap">Rap-tap</rs>. Mother; very good.</p>
      <p>But <name ref="#thompson">Thompson</name> does not laugh, for very dear to his heart is the
        thought of a mother who has been known to him from early childhood only as <rs ref="rel">an
          angel</rs>. Surely she would speak to her soul, if she had power, though she has been
        parted from him for so many years. What starlight musings of the boy who thought that
        guardian angels lived in stars, and looked up at the sky for hours, to dream which was the
        bright particular star in which his angel dwelt; what yearnings of the youth for a mother’s
        sympathy and guidance when all passions and affections were astir; what sacred mysteries
        belonging to the inmost thoughts of a whole life, so far as it has gone, were touched by the
        assertions that the <rs ref="spirit">spirit</rs> of the lost mother was first to speak.
        Truly then, if there were truth in Rapping, and if that <rs ref="spirit">spirit</rs> had
        addressed her son, she would have spoken not in vain.</p>
      <p><q>Have you anything to say to me?</q> asked <name ref="#thompson">Thompson</name>. <rs
          ref="rap">Rap-tap</rs>. <q who="#thompson">Will you say it?</q> Then, by the most tedious
        process of getting each letter in succession knocked out of the card, and with a few
        mistakes in spelling, which were corrected as they were made, but which consumed time, <rs
          ref="rap">the <rs ref="spirit">spirit</rs> rapped out this sentence</rs>: <q who="spirit"
          >Dear son, I am well pleased to see you. I watch over you and God blesses you.</q>
        Satisfactory, no doubt. A kind of sentence that might be regarded by any reasonable person
        as a sure proof of the <rs ref="ghost">ghost’s</rs> authenticity. But would she in the next
        place authenticate her claim to be the mother of <name ref="#thompson">Thompson</name>?
        Would she convince her son by telling him her Christian name? <name ref="#thompson"
          >Thompson</name> began the alphabet with an inscrutable face: but the light from the fire
        and window, although good enough for a <rs ref="ghost">ghost</rs>, or for a common purpose,
        was not good for a <rs ref="medium">Medium</rs>. The <rs ref="spirit">spirit</rs> rapped at
        T (wrong), at I (wrong), at M (wrong); finally made out Timok—truly an odd Christian name
        for an English lady; and having, in this instance, the curious peculiarity that it did not
        contain a single letter of the name that should have been communicated. But Timok might be
        something mystic. The <rs ref="medium">Medium</rs> said it was not mystic but mistake, and
        complained of the bad light. <rs ref="spirit">Spirits</rs>, perhaps, are forbidden,
        spectacles. No more must be done until a lamp was lighted.</p>
      <p>Then it was again distinctly intimated to the professed <rs ref="spirit">spirit</rs> of <rs
          ref="#thompsonmother"><name ref="#thompson">Thompson’s</name> mother</rs>, who had sought
        this conversation, that nothing mystical was wanted, only the Christian name she had before
        she died—<q who="#haydenmb">Went into the <rs ref="spirit">spirit</rs> world,</q> said the
          <rs ref="medium">Medium</rs>, <q who="#haydenmb">the <rs ref="spirit">spirits</rs> never
          talk of death.</q>—<q who="#thompson">Before you went into the <rs ref="spirit"
            >spirit</rs> world. Do you remember what that name was?</q>
        <rs ref="rap">Rap-tap.</rs>
        <q who="#thompson">Will you tell it me?</q> Rap-tap. <q who="#thompson">Do so then, now, if
          you please.</q> So again came the answer knocked up from the alphabet, this time,
        E-U-N-I-C-E—of course, ridiculously wrong—but, as Eunice means <q>a happy victory,</q> and
        it might be again said that the <rs ref="spirit">spirit</rs> was mystical, <name
          ref="#thompson">Thompson</name> said, <q who="#thompson">We will presume that there may be
          some hidden meaning.</q>
        <q who="#haydenmb">Hidden meaning, you think?</q> said <name ref="#haydenmb">Mrs.
          Hayden</name>, listlessly, as though the <rs ref="spirit">spirits</rs> and their sayings
        were rather affairs of ours, than others. <q who="#haydenmb">Shall we try again for the real
          name?</q>
        <q who="#thompson">No,</q> said Thompson, <q who="#thompson">it is not worth while; I will
          be satisfied with the first letter of it.</q> It was then most elaborately defined to the
          <rs ref="ghost">ghost</rs>, with almost legal periphrasis, what was required, and the <rs
          ref="ghost">ghost</rs> by rap-taps declared itself perfectly clear in its mind, and ready
        to oblige. <q who="#haydenmb">So <pb/>now for the initial of your Christian name in this
          world?</q>—T. <q who="#haydenmb">Is that right?</q> asked the <rs ref="medium"
        >Medium</rs>. <name ref="#thompson">Thompson</name> said no. <q who="#haydenmb">Then we had
          better try again, there may be some mistake.</q> The <rs ref="medium">Medium</rs>
        explained the matter in her own way to the table, and trying again, was again quite wrong,
        and the <rs ref="medium">Medium</rs> proposed to try again. Thompson had no doubt, that in
        not more than twenty-six trials, and, perhaps, in one or two less, the right letter could be
        hit upon: so declared himself content. He would now be glad if the supposed <rs ref="ghost"
          >ghost</rs> of his mother would condescend to name the year in which she passed into the
          <rs ref="spirit">spirit</rs> world. Did she remember it? <rs ref="rap">Rap-tap;</rs> Would
        she tell it? <rs ref="rap">Rap-tap.</rs> And what year was it? Figures being now touched on
        the card instead of letters, <rs ref="rap">there was a tap at one, a tap at eight, a tap at
          four (wrong, it should have been at two), and a last tap at nine, which the <rs
            ref="spirit">spirit</rs> recanted by refusing to ratify the whole number when asked at
          the end whether it was what she meant</rs>. The <rs ref="medium">Medium</rs> probably
        caught a smile on <name ref="#thompson">Thompson’s</name> face, and reserved to herself the
        advantage of another guess; she then settled upon the year 1846, which was by more than
        twenty years a blunder. <name ref="#thompson">Thompson</name> then ceased from his
        inquiries, and we all proposed to wait and try the powers of another <rs ref="spirit"
          >spirit</rs>.</p>
      <p>After the usual solemnities, there was <rs ref="rap">a rapid rat-tat-tat-tat</rs>. <q
          who="#brown">What does that mean?</q> asked Brown. The <rs ref="medium">Medium</rs>
        explained that <rs ref="rap">no two <rs ref="spirit">spirits</rs> have the same rap</rs>,
        and that by familiarity you know the rap of any <rs ref="spirit">spirit</rs> as distinctly
        as you know a voice. That <rs ref="spirit">spirits</rs> rapped according to their
        temperaments; those of nervous people tapping quickly, of quiet people almost inaudibly, and
        so on. <q who="#brown">Well, who is this?</q> asked Brown, and it turned out to be a
        repetition upon Brown of the dull guesses we had just gone through in the case of Thompson.
        It was the <rs ref="spirit">spirit</rs> of his mother. (Brown’s mother, he is happy to
        observe here, is alive and well.) Had this <rs ref="spirit">spirit</rs> of the
        dead-and-alive anything to say? Yes. A dead-and-alive <rs ref="ghost">ghost</rs> was the
        properest for the occasion. The most interminable game at beggar-my-neighbour is not half So
        dull and stupid as the knocking out of long and foolish sentences from the A. B. C. D. card
        of a Rapper. Brown must have been regarded as a suspicious character by the <rs ref="medium"
          >Medium</rs>. The <rs ref="ghost">ghost</rs> of the dead-and-alive, <rs ref="rap"
          >blundering over letters, tapping back; and, leaving, after all, her sentences in a broken
          down condition</rs>, said to <name ref="#brown">Brown</name>, <q who="#haydenmb">Be
          candid; investigate; be careful; for this is God’s Work, my son.</q></p>
      <p>God’s work!</p>
      <p>The <rs ref="spirit">spirit</rs> then informed <name ref="#brown">Brown</name> by <rs
          ref="rap">the usual slow process</rs> that his mother’s name was Mary; falling into a trap
        which <name ref="#brown">Brown</name> had laid, possibly by dwelling with the pencil over M
        and A and R and Y; also that she had been dead six years — all wrong.</p>
      <p><q who="#brown">I wish,</q> said <name ref="#brown">Brown</name>, <q who="#brown">to ask
          some questions concerning the future; can the <rs ref="spirit">spirits</rs> answer them
          without your knowing what they are?</q>
        <q who="#haydenmb">If they cannot, they will be speculated again unluckily upon M. That
          silent,</q> said the <rs ref="medium">Medium</rs>, <q who="#haydenmb">sometimes they do
          so. Try.</q> — <q who="#brown">As they are questions which I should not like to ask in
          public. Will they see them written on paper?</q></p>
      <p><q who="#haydenmb">O yes.</q>—Brown wrote down very clearly: ‘Shall I soon be married?’ <q
          who="#brown #haydenmb">Will the <rs ref="spirit">spirits</rs> answer this question?</q>
        <rs ref="rap">Rat-tat-tat.</rs>
        <q who="#haydenmb">Is Yes the answer?</q>
        <rs ref="rap">Rat-tat-tat</rs>. ‘How many children shall I have?’ was written next, <name
          ref="#brown">Brown</name> saying <q who="#brown">This is a question that must be answered
          in numbers. Does the <rs ref="spirit">spirit</rs> see it?</q>
        <rs ref="rap">Rat-tat-tat.</rs>
        <q who="#brown">Can it answer me?</q>
        <rs ref="rap">Rat-tat-tat.</rs> And so the <rs ref="spirit">spirit</rs> answered by the
        usual process, <q who="spirit">One Hundred and Thirty-Six.</q> When the 1 was obtained, and
        then 1 then 3 to go next to it, and then the 6 to go after that, the rapid growth of <rs
          ref="#brown">Brown’s family</rs> amused <name ref="#thompson">Thompson</name>, and the
        imminent carrying on of the sum into thousands was prevented by his ill-timed mirth. The
        production of children by <name ref="#brown">Brown</name> stopped therefore prematurely at
        the number of one hundred and thirty-six.</p>
      <p>The <rs ref="medium">Medium</rs>, who always asked whether the answers fitted, and who did
        not clearly know whether she might not be succeeding vastly, although she evidently felt a
        little puzzled by the sense that she was not doing so well as might be expected, was now
        re-assured by the reverent tone in which the too explosive Thompson asked whether the <rs
          ref="spirit">spirit</rs> of his sister were in the room. His only sister being in vigorous
        health, he did not expect her <rs ref="ghost">ghost</rs>; but it was there, and very prompt
        to answer him. How long had she been dead? Two years.</p>
      <p>So the dreary labour was continued; but we cannot fatigue our readers with the whole
        monotony of a sitting that was not enlivened by one happy guess. After two hours in the
        presence of the <rs ref="medium">Medium</rs> and the great fire, we passed into the front
        drawing-room again, and paid our money. <name ref="#stonegw">Mr. Stone</name> trusted that
        we had found the <rs ref="spirit">spirits</rs> answering satisfactorily. It appeared to us
        rather probable that they did answer very satisfactorily at a guinea a head. Nevertheless we
        grumbled not, and listened to the further wonders that he had to tell of <rs ref="rap"><rs
            ref="spirit">spirits</rs> that sometimes not only rapped, but moved heavy furniture
          about</rs>. He had seen a large loo table, he said, turned topsy turvy by the <rs
          ref="spirit">spirits</rs>. He told us more, and offered us gratuitously a fresh sitting,
        if we had not been satisfied with the first. We had seen enough. We asked for printed
        information, and brought home with us <rs ref="rap">a pamphlet upon <rs ref="spirit"
            >Spirit</rs> Knocking</rs>, which he recommended to our notice. It had the motto on the
        cover, <q>Behold, I stand at the door, and knock.</q><rs ref="mis"> Within the pamphlet<pb/>
          we have since read of a spit that flew up a chimney, of a stirrup-iron that followed a man
          through a wood, and other miserable nonsense.</rs></p>
      <p><rs ref="rel">Of the use of Holy Scripture in the writings of these people we abstain from
          saying much.</rs> We will give, however, from the pamphlet placed in our hands one
        example. The writer dwells, among other things, upon <rs ref="rel">the account of Peter’s
          coming after his delivery from prison and knocking at the door of Mary’s house, when his
          friends within, who would not at first believe the servant’s tidings that Peter stood at
          the gate, said afterwards ‘It is his angel.’</rs>
        <q>It is evident from this,</q> argues <rs ref="rap">the Rapper’s pamphlet</rs>, <q>that
          those who were gathered together praying, thought it possible for an angel to
        knock,</q>—we will quote no more of the stuff. <rs ref="mis">This miserable delusion</rs>,
        the <rs ref="ghost">ghost</rs> of a dead <rs ref="ghost">ghost</rs>, <rs ref="mis">this
          clumsiest of all the cheats</rs> that ever offered folly to be bolted by the greedy
        appetite of superstition without even the courtesy of cooking it a little, did for a short
        time turn the heads of thousands in America. <rs ref="pol">But, even in America—the Land of
          Promise to the Mormons, and to many other sects of fanatics</rs>—<rs ref="rap">the Rappers
          came at last to he generally understood after Mrs. Culver’s deposition had been
          published;</rs> the <q>intense excitement in all classes of society</q> died out; and now
        this <rs ref="ghost">ghost</rs> of the <rs ref="CLghost">Cock Lane <rs ref="ghost"
            >Ghost</rs></rs>, having been laid a second time, makes a third appearance, more faded
        than ever, and by advertisement invites <q>the nobility and gentry</q> during the present
        London season, to be present at its manifestations—<q>God’s work, my son;</q>—nothing of the
        Treadmill quality in it.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
