<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/hoax.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GH-BLNPS-18040106">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Fears of a Ghost, and the Fatal Catastrophe</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Originally published by</resp>
               <name>The Morning Chronicle</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
               <name>Gabi Keane</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This project encoded newspaper and periodical articles on ghost hoaxes in the Victorian period. This publication of the text serves as data in a collaborative laboratory edition for the 2022 NEH Institute "Advanced digital editing: modeling the text and making the edition" at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Ghost hoaxes in 19th-century British news media</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>All texts in this collection were sourced from British periodical and newspaper
               archives, transcribed,and encoded. The citation below was provided by the archive and
               appears exactly as given.</p>
            <p><bibl>"FEARS OF A GHOST, AND THE FATAL CATASTROPHE." <publisher rend="The">Morning Chronicle</publisher> [1801], <date when="1804-01-06">6 Jan. 1804</date>. British Library Newspapers, https://bit.ly/2T3nTtV. Accessed 4 Jan. 2020.
            </bibl></p>
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This document is part of a larger digital collection of stories of ghost hoaxes from
               the 18th and 19th century London newspapers and periodicals. The project explores the
               beginnings of mass print media in a metropolitan area at a time when technology and
               education made reading increasingly common and inexpensive.</p>
            <p>The corpus holds 36 individual documents, which reflect a diverse mix of reporting on
               various hauntings in and around London between 1804 and 1889. The PDF and JPEGs from
               online databases were transcribed using ABBYFineReader OCR, then corrected and
               occasionally manually transcribed if document quality necessitated it. After
               normalization in plain text, all documents were upconverted to TEI XML.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>Earlier texts have had some spelling normalization due to errors in OCR.
                  Typographic em dashes are longer than modern em dashes, so all dashes have been
                  normalized to modern em dash length.</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation>
               <p>All extraneous white space used by printers to avoid overlapping with letters has
                  been removed. All quotes are simply tagged with the q tag.</p>
            </quotation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>The <placeName ref="#hammersmith">neighbourhood of Hammersmith</placeName> has for some
            time been alarmed by a ridiculous rumour of a ghost, which is said to have paid its
            nocturnal visits to <placeName ref="#blacklionlane-fields">the fields adjacent to
               Black-Lion lane</placeName>. An attempt to investigate the cause of this visitation
            was on Tuesday night last productive of a most melancholy accident. Francis Smith, an
            officer of excise, having lain in wait for that purpose, armed with a loaded gun, the
            contens of which he seems to have discharged at Thomas Millwood, a young man of 22 years
            of age, who was then passing, and whom Smith seems to have taken for the Ghost. The
            unfortunate young man was killed on the spot. Yesterday forenoon a Coroner’s Inquest sat
            on the body, at <placeName ref="#blacklionpub">the Black Lion</placeName>, and the
            following is the substance of the evidence adduced. The sister of the deceased, a fine
            young woman, said that her brother was about 22 years of age, and was a bricklayer by
            profession. On the evening of Tuesday last he was in the house of his father in
               <placeName ref="#blacklionlane">Black-Lion-lane</placeName>, with whom the witness
            resides. He left the house between 10 and 11 o’clock, and <rs ref="premonition">the
               witness being almost immediately struck with a presentiment that some accident would
               befall him</rs>, she accordingly went to the door, and stood, on some bricks, in
            order to look out for him. She then heard a voice say, <q>Damn you, who are you? Stand,
               else I’ll shoot you.</q> And the report of a gun immediately succeeded. Her brother
            was dressed in a white flannel jacket and trowsers. He was perfectly sober. <placeName
               ref="#hammersmith">The neighbourhood</placeName> had for about two months been
            disturbed with the report of a Ghost, but she did not believe, nor had ever heard, that
            her brother had assumed such an appearance.</p>
         <p>Mr. John Lock, wine merchant, in <placeName ref="#blacklionlane">Black-Lion-lane,
               Hammersmith</placeName>, said, that as he was returning home from the Plough and
            Harrow on the evening of Tuesday last, about half past ten o’clock, in company with Mr.
            Stow, he was accosted by Francis Smith, one of his Majesty’s officers of excise, who
            asked to speak with him. Upon going aside, Smith informed him that he had shot a man,
            who he believed to be the ghost. The witness informed Mr. Stow of the circumstance, and
            they accompanied Smith to the place. They found the deceased lying in <placeName
               ref="#beaverlanecross">a cross lane leading from Beaver-lane to
               Black-Lion-lane</placeName>, upon his buck, apparently dead. The wound was under his
            left under jaw, and the skin of his face was exceedingly black. Smith did not appear
            sensible that he had done any thing wrong, till the witness warned him of the
            consequences of such a step. He then seemed much affected, and said that he had spoken
            twice but had received no answer, and that the night was very dark.</p>
         <p>William Girdler, a watchman, said, that he had a slight acquaintance of the deceased.
            That the neighbourhood had been much alarmed for two months past with the rumour of a
            ghost walking through <placeName ref="#blacklionlane">Black Lion-lane</placeName>. That
            he went his rounds as usual on Tuesday evening last. That he had appointed to meet with
            Francis Smith, in order to go in search of the ghost. They had exchanged a watchword
            which they were to use—<q>Friend, who comes there?</q> To which the other was to
               answer—<q>Advance Friend.</q> When the witness came near Mr. Stow’s house he heard
            the report of a gun, and a few minutes afterwards, as he was going to <placeName
               ref="irr">the White Hart public-house</placeName>, he met a young woman who told him
            that he was wanted. Having gone on a little way, he met Smith, and asked him what
            intelligence? Smith answered, very bad. They then met Mr. Stow, and went to <placeName
               ref="#beaverlanecross">the place where the deceased lay</placeName>. Smith said that
            he would deliver himself up; that he had spoken to the deceased twice before he fired,
            but he would give him no answer. On the Thursday preceding, the witness, while going his
            rounds about ten o’clock at night, saw a tall figure dressed in a sheet or table cloth.
            When the witness spoke to him he lifted up his hands, and the witness saw under the
            sheet the appearance of a dark coat and metal buttons. The Coroner summed up the
            evidence with great ability and humanity, when the Jury, after some deliberation,
            returned a verdict of <emph>Wilful Murder</emph>.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
