<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/hoax.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GH-BRITP-18890504-F">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ghost Cut Ghost</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Originally published by</resp>
               <name>Chambers's Journal</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
               <name>Gabi Keane</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This project encoded newspaper and periodical articles on ghost hoaxes in the
               Victorian period. This publication of the text serves as data in a collaborative
               laboratory edition for the 2022 NEH Institute "Advanced digital editing: modeling the
               text and making the edition" at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Ghost hoaxes in 19th-century British news media</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>All texts in this collection were sourced from British periodical and newspaper
               archives, transcribed,and encoded. The citation below was provided by the archive and
               appears exactly as given.</p>
            <p>
               <bibl>GHOST CUT GHOST. <publisher>Chambers's journal</publisher> of popular
                  literature, science and arts, Jan. 1854- Nov. 1897; <date when="1889-05-04">May 4,
                     1889</date>; 6, 279; British Periodicals pg. 285</bibl>
            </p>
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This document is part of a larger digital collection of stories of ghost hoaxes from
               the 18th and 19th century London newspapers and periodicals. The project explores the
               beginnings of mass print media in a metropolitan area at a time when technology and
               education made reading increasingly common and inexpensive.</p>
            <p>The corpus holds 36 individual documents, which reflect a diverse mix of reporting on
               various hauntings in and around London between 1804 and 1889. The PDF and JPEGs from
               online databases were transcribed using ABBYFineReader OCR, then corrected and
               occasionally manually transcribed if document quality necessitated it. After
               normalization in plain text, all documents were upconverted to TEI XML.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>Earlier texts have had some spelling normalization due to errors in OCR.
                  Typographic em dashes are longer than modern em dashes, so all dashes have been
                  normalized to modern em dash length.</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation>
               <p>All extraneous white space used by printers to avoid overlapping with letters has
                  been removed. All quotes are simply tagged with the q tag.</p>
            </quotation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>That cold-blooded demon which we call Science is killing romance from amongst us. Years
            ago everybody believed in the wonders of the invisible world, and <rs ref="ghost"
               >ghosts</rs> were among the regular inhabitants of every rural district. Now, we are
            so seldom suffered to see or hear of a <rs ref="ghost">ghost</rs>, that a visitation has
            the effect of novelty. So far as we know, the story of <rs ref="ghost">one ghost
               outwitting another</rs> is absolutely unique. The story which we purpose to tell is
            of this character. We tell it as it was told to us by the most noted detective in the
            Western States of America.</p>
         <p>You may imagine (said Nathan Dodge) that during my career as a detective I have had some
            singular jobs given me to work on. There was one little piece of business which I always
            look back upon with a good deal of professional pride, although the ending was a very
            sad one. It was a case of diamond cut diamond—<rs ref="ghost">ghost cut ghost</rs>, I
            call it—and it took up my time for the better part of six months.</p>
         <p>About <placeName ref="amb">ten miles outside the limits of San Francisco</placeName>—I’m
            speaking of about twenty years ago—stood a large farmhouse. This house had been vacant
            for three years before I saw it. The original owner had been murdered there, and the
            house and farm had passed into the hands of his brother, who was a New York gentleman.
            At that time, gold-mining was the staple industry of California, and San Francisco
            especially was under the spell of the gold fever. Little attention was paid to
            developing the agricultural wealth of the soil, which now promises to be so vast as to
            rival that of the gold-beds. So the New Yorker, being unable to find a tenant for the
            house and farm which had passed into his hands, left them to take care of themselves.
            Now, a wooden house left to take care of itself is in a very bad way, and though for a
            time the house was not altogether without tenants, they were not such as took upon
            themselves any responsibility for the necessary repairs. Parties of two or three miners
            occasionally stopped at the house all night: these were its only tenants. But by-and-by
            it was deserted by even those chance visitants; for it began to get about that the house
            was haunted. The panic caused by this report was such that for love or money you
            couldn’t have hired a carpenter to enter it even in the daytime. Of course I’d heard of
            the haunted house; but as detectives are never called upon to arrest <rs ref="ghost">ghosts</rs>, I felt no particular curiosity about it.</p>
         <p>One morning our chief put into my hands a case, against an absconding secretary named
            Coffin. Coffin was the secretary of the White Mountain Mining Company. All the funds had
            been under his control, and he had got away with some ten thousand dollars belonging to
            the shareholders. My business was to find him.</p>
         <p>It is always a very good plan to begin at the beginning. So the day I received my
            orders, I went to the Company’s office and overhauled everything. The only thing that I
            could find was a railroad ticket for New York. I went to the depot, and found that it
            had been issued to the defaulter the day before he absconded. Apparently, it had been
            left behind by mistake, and I did think of taking the next train to New York. But it
            occurred to me that if he had been going to New York he would have gone under another
            name, and would not have left behind so obvious a clue as to his whereabouts.</p>
         <p>A visit to his landlady convinced me that New York was the place he hadn’t gone to. He’d
            gone away without his trunks or clothes. The only things that were missing were a suit
            of clothes, a stout pair of boots, one or two clean shirts, some collars, a wide-awake
            hat, and a black valise. He had left the town at night. No one had witnessed his
            departure. Here was a good chance for a detective to work by the inductive process—from
            small beginnings to work on and on from clue to clue until he bagged his man.</p>
         <p>The only thing that I could do was to work all the roads leading out of the town. After
            about a week at this, I found a farm-hand who had seen a foot-passenger resembling my
            man the morning after he absconded. I followed this trail, and soon became positive that
            I was on the right track. Coffin was a shrewd fellow. He had planned the embezzlement
            and escape carefully, and had made elaborate preparations for playing what we call the
               <q>chameleon game,</q> that is, for changing his clothing, headgear, and face at
            every stage. To this end he had possessed himself of a change or two of clothing, a
            stock of hats, and any quantity of whiskers; and he rung the changes on these pretty
            frequently.</p>
         <p>The black bag was the only thing that I had to rely upon as a pointer. Fortunately, a
            man on tramp with a black bag was not in those days a common sight; and I had less
            difficulty in following Coffin’s trail than might be supposed. The first time I heard of
            him he was a smoothfaced gentleman dressed in shabby black, looking for all the world
            like a broken-down gambler going to retrieve his fortunes in some mining camp. The next
            he was a middle-aged doctor with a flowing beard and heavy moustache. Later on, he was
            playing the role of a Company promoter, offering to buy up mining claims on behalf of an
            English syndicate. He was then attired in a check suit, a light hat, and side whiskers.
            At this stage I obtained positive proof that I was following the right man.</p>
         <p>Entering a drinking saloon I saw upon the shelf a photograph of Coffin. The edges were
            slightly charred. It had evidently been burnt. I told the landlord that the owner of
            that face was a particular friend of mine, and asked him how the photograph came into
            his possession. He told me that his hired boy of colour had picked it out of some burnt
            papers which had been left in the room of one of his guests ; that the boy —not
            understanding what it was—had brought it to him, and that he was displaying it in ease
            the owner returned and wished to claim it. Was it like his guest ? Not in the least.</p>
         <p>I went into one of the outhouses to look for the coloured boy, and found him sitting oil
            a log singing:</p>
         <p><emph>Blow dat horn agin ; Bredren, fr’ends, companions dear, Blow dat horn agin.</emph></p>
         <p>I made a dollar the avenue to that boy’s confidence. and quite unwittingly he gave me
            the information for which I was seeking. The bright fastening of the bag had aroused his
            curiosity. One day, in its owner’s absence, whilst he was playing with the lock, the bag
            llew open, revealing <q>dead men’s whiskers.</q> The sight disconcerted him. He felt, as
            he expressed it, <q>in a hurry all over;</q> and whilst he stood over the bag, its owner
            returned, and rewarded him with a vicious kick.</p>
         <p>After that I thought I should have no difficulty in laying my hand on Coffin. My
            calculations deceived me. I found that he was <q>doubling,</q> and traced him almost as
            far as the suburbs of San Francisco. There I lost all trace of him as completely as if
            the earth had swallowed him up. Months afterwards, feeling vexed and disappointed, I
            dropped into a saloon at the outskirts of the town to get a <q>liquor.</q> I had had as
            pretty a dance after Coffin as any man need want; but the interest of the game supported
            me, and I was determined not to give it up. There were three or four miners in the bar,
            and one of them was evidently greatly excited. His companions seemed to be ridiculing
            him, and he was getting what we call <q>ugly.</q> I made my way towards the little knot
            of talkers, and overheard the following conversation.</p>
         <p><q>So, you didn’t think much of your lodgings in the haunted house, Bill ?</q>
            <q>No, I didn’t—no two ways about it.</q>
            <q>What did you hear?</q>
            <q>Twasn’t what I heard—’twas what I saw.</q>
            <q>What did you see, then?</q>
            <q>Why, the doors openin’ and shuttin’ without anybody touchin’ em.</q>
            <q>Nonsense, man!</q>
            <q>Nonsense be blowed ! I tell you they did. And when I drawed my six-shooter and fired
               half a dozen shots clean through the door—makin’ the allfiredest row you ever
               heard—the door kep’ openin’ and shuttin’ and playin’ tunes. I felt like a gone
               sucker, you bet. My heart began to bump so under my jacket that it’s a wonder it
               didn’t knock a button off. I wouldn’t go there agin for all the money in the State.
               But if anybody here thinks I’m a coward, he’s only got to say so.</q></p>
         <p>It suddenly occurred to me that I had located Coffin—that <rs ref="ghost">he was the
               ghost in the haunted house</rs>. A vague suspicion of this sort had, it is true,
            flitted through my mind before; but now, without being able to explain why, I felt
            assured that, however impossible it might seem, <rs ref="ghost">Coffin was the ghost in
               the haunted house</rs>. Beyond the facts that the fame of the haunted house was
            widespread, and that everybody knew of its existence, there was nothing to support my
            theory except the maxim of the most famous of all detectives—a maxim destined to assure
            his after-fame: <q>Always suspect that which seems probable; and begin by believing what
               appears incredible.</q></p>
         <p>I determined to call in the aid of another detective and visit the place next night. I
            chose for my companion George Webber, one of the most esteemed members of the force, a
            man who had proved his worth. Webber was a man of imperturbable calmness, and with great
            confidence in himself. He would have laid his hand upon the most dangerous criminal as
            tranquilly as if lie had been accosting a friend.</p>
         <p>The haunted farmhouse was situated about a hundred yards from the roadway. What once had
            been a garden was now a veritable jungle, given up to weeds and bushes. Fortunately,
            although it was ten o’clock, the night was clear. Innumerable stars lit up the flinty
            sky. There was no light in the house ; no sign of its being inhabited. The windows of
            the ground-floor were broken, and some of the doors were open. We entered at the rear. A
            place of more sinister aspect I never saw. The plastering had crumbled from the walls ;
            the flooring was rotten ; the ceiling looked as though it might fall at any time, the
            rafters being bent as if they supported a heavy weight.</p>
         <p>The sitting-room where <q>Bill</q> had taken up his quarters a few nights previously
            contained a rough table and a few stools, which had been overturned. I could see that
            the door which led from it to the staircase had been riddled by bullets. There was a
            doorway iu the passage, but the door was gone. The door which led into the parlour
            opened noiselessly. Our lanterns revealed the fact that the tables, glass, and chairs
            had been overturned, thrown in every direction, trodden upon, shivered into fragments.
            Everything denoted lhat this room had been the scene of a terrible struggle.</p>
         <p>The keyhole of the door which led into the cellar was sewn up with cobwebs. The cellar
            itself was full of dust and debris. Each of us had a lantern, and each inspected for
            himself. Running along the side-wall, I detected a wire, and following this I found that
            it disappeared in an old barrel. Without disturbing the wire, I removed the head of the
            barrel, and found that the wire was attached to an old saucepan lid. A thorough
            examination revealed nothing further ; so we returned to the sitting-room. I did not
            tell my companion what I had seen, and he had discovered nothing. We did not go
            up-stairs, because we thought it would be prudent to postpone further explorations until
            the next day. Meantime, we darkened our lanterns and deposited them in a corner. The
            room was semi-dark. Our eyes and ears were on the alert; but the house was as still as a
            tomb; we saw nothing, and heard no sound.</p>
         <p>I had merely told my companion that I expected to make an important discovery. Of its
            nature he knew nothing.</p>
         <p>We waited in the most acute degree of expectation and attention until nearly midnight.
            All of a sudden I heard faint notes of music, which lasted for a few minutes. By-and-by
            the music was accompanied by a voice. The sounds were as fine and soft as the voice of a
            child. I was satisfied that the music was the work of human hands and the voice a human
            voice ; but I was considerably startled. My companion looked very pale, and strove to
            rise from the place where he sat. I put my hand on his arm to prevent him. It was
            scarcely necessary, for he could barely muster strength to whisper, <q>Lets get.</q> The
            music was trailing away into feebleness, when the staircase door began to open and shut.
            I felt sure that the wire which I had seen downstairs had something to do with this. I
            made a great effort to rise. To my astonishment, I could not move a limb. I could only
            bend forward and gasp. A power which I could not resist made me motionless and
            speechless. Yet all the time I was burning to <q>go</q> for that door, but I hadn’t
            physical capacity to do so.</p>
         <p>My companion recovered first, and seizing both lanterns, dashed from the house and made
            for the roadway. I jumped to my feet and followed my companion. As I did so, I heard a
            tunk, tunk, tunk! down in the cellar.</p>
         <p>I found my mate in the highway, his face as white as a sheet.</p>
         <p><q>What in thunder ails you, man?</q> I asked, feeling that the most creditable way of
            drawing my companion’s attention from my condition was to heighten the absurdity of
            his.</p>
         <p><q><rs ref="ghost">The ghost!</rs></q> he gasped. <q>I wouldn’t go back to that house to
               save my life.</q></p>
         <p>There was nothing for it but to tell Webber what I’d seen and what I suspected. As I
            have said, my fellow-detective was as brave a man as ever took up a trail; and when I
            told him what I had seen, he became perfectly self-possessed. We spent the remainder of
            the night in laying our plans. In the early morning he rode back to San Francisco to get
            the necessary apparatus for carrying them out. I remained to <q>shadow</q> the
            house.</p>
         <p>Just as it was getting dusk, my companion returned, and we re-entered the house from the
            rear, noiselessly and with great caution. Removing my shoes, I made my way up-stairs,
            where I fancied I detected a slight noise overhead. There was no sign of this room
            having been inhabited. The old place was two stories high, with a garret at the top. The
            garret was evidently reached by a ladder, though none was visible. I surmised that the
               <rs ref="ghost">ghost</rs> was in this garret, and that any one showing his head
            above the scuttle would get it rapped, even if he didn’t get shot. There was a large
            cupboard facing the entrance to the garret, and in the door of it I bored —on a level
            with my eyes—a few small holes with a gimlet which I happened to have in my
            pocket-knife, first drawing it through my hair, to prevent its making the slightest
            noise. My plan was to play the <rs ref="ghost">ghost</rs> for the benefit of the
            occupant of the garret—<rs ref="ghost">ghost or no ghost</rs>. For this purpose Webber
            had brought with him an old fiddle. I removed all the strings except one, told my
            companion to allow me time to secrete myself above, and then to make a noise on that one
            string, accompanying it with a few groans and other muffled noises.</p>
         <p>I hadn’t been hid many minutes before I heard the darnedest row from below. It wasn’t
            like anything earthly. At first it seemed like one shrieking in pain, then it sounded
            like belligerent cats, and then it died away in a few complaining sighs. It was so
            -weird that, although I knew very well that my mate was causing it, I couldn’t help
            feeling a bit queer. Pretty soon I heard a movement overhead: the scuttle-top was being
            removed. Next a ladder was thrust down the scuttle. To help Webber to keep up the
            entertainment, I gave a few groans inside the cupboard. That brought a man down the
            ladder. He’d no sooner reached the foot of it than I collared him. It was Coffin.</p>
         <p>The moment I touched him lie sank down on the floor like—like an empty sack. He seemed
            as if he hadn’t got a bone in his body: he was as limp as a jelly-fish. Whilst I got him
            out into the open air, Webber searched the garret, and found all the missing dollars,
            bonds, &amp;c.</p>
         <p>We hurried Coffin back to San Francisco, intending to lock him up. He was still
            unconscious, and we were obliged to summon a doctor. Poor fellow! he never got over it.
            When he came out of his swoon, he was mad, and had to spend the rest of his days in an
            asylum. That’s the effect it has, sir, when a man really believes he has come in contact
            with the supernatural, as Coffin did.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
