<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/hoax.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GH-BLNPS-18040106-H">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Ghost of Hammersmith</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Originally published by</resp>
               <name>The Morning Post</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
               <name>Gabi Keane</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This project encoded newspaper and periodical articles on ghost hoaxes in the Victorian period. This publication of the text serves as data in a collaborative laboratory edition for the 2022 NEH Institute "Advanced digital editing: modeling the text and making the edition" at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Ghost hoaxes in 19th-century British news media</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>All texts in this collection were sourced from British periodical and newspaper
               archives, transcribed,and encoded. The citation below was provided by the archive and
               appears exactly as given.</p>
            <p><bibl>"THE GHOST OF HAMMERSMITH." <publisher rend="The">Morning Post</publisher>, <date when="1804-01-06">6 Jan. 1804</date>. British Library
                  Newspapers, http://tinyurl.galegroup.com/tinyurl/85e2v2. Accessed 20 Oct.
                  2018.</bibl></p>
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This document is part of a larger digital collection of stories of ghost hoaxes from
               the 18th and 19th century London newspapers and periodicals. The project explores the
               beginnings of mass print media in a metropolitan area at a time when technology and
               education made reading increasingly common and inexpensive.</p>
            <p>The corpus holds 36 individual documents, which reflect a diverse mix of reporting on
               various hauntings in and around London between 1804 and 1889. The PDF and JPEGs from
               online databases were transcribed using ABBYFineReader OCR, then corrected and
               occasionally manually transcribed if document quality necessitated it. After
               normalization in plain text, all documents were upconverted to TEI XML.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>Earlier texts have had some spelling normalization due to errors in OCR.
                  Typographic em dashes are longer than modern em dashes, so all dashes have been
                  normalized to modern em dash length.</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation>
               <p>All extraneous white space used by printers to avoid overlapping with letters has
                  been removed. All quotes are simply tagged with the q tag.</p>
            </quotation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>This attack upon the credulity of the inhabitants of <placeName ref="#hammersmith"
               >Hammersmith</placeName> and <placeName ref="#turnhamgreen">Turnham
            Green</placeName>, has for upwards of two months excited so much alarm, that every
            superstitious person in that neighbourhood has been filled with the most fearful
            apprehensions. So terror-struck are the minds of the women and children that not one
            will venture over the threshold after five o’clock in the evening; and indeed, if we may
            credit public report, this Ghost is a most mischievous spirit. Among his pranks,
            breaking windows, and even maiming several of the inhabitants, are mentioned. The
            following facts will best exemplify how far he is a welcome guest. On the 15th of
            December last, about ten in the evening, some servants belonging to <placeName ref="amb"
               >a brew-house in the neighbourhood</placeName> were returning with a friend from the
            outskirts into the town, when they were met by the Ghost, dressed in what they describe
            to resemble the hide of a calf, with a pair of enormously large horns and cloven feet.
            The men not altogether liking the appearance of the intruder turned about and ran off,
            but the Ghost was too nimble for the drayman whom he overtook, seized him by the throat,
            and nearly choaked him. The fright, together with the ill usage, threw the poor fellow
            into a fever from which he is but very lately recovered. About a week since the driver
            of one of the stages was proceeding down <placeName ref="amb">a lane near the <placeName
                  ref="#brandenburghhouse">Margrave of Anspach’s</placeName></placeName>, when he was
            alarmed by hearing an uncommon rustling noise. By a faint light from the moon he saw
            what he describes to be a strange creature, dressed in white, gliding over <placeName
               ref="amb">an adjoining meadow</placeName>. The phantom approached very near him, when
            he saw bladders affixed to his feet, shoulders, arms, body, and head; and the noise they
            made resembled the rattling of pease. The coachman was too much frightened to
            investigate the business any further; he got off his box and ran back to the town, where
            proceeded with him to the spot where the coach and horses were left, found the traces
            cut, and the horses grazing in an adjoining field. This Ghost has hitherto appeared
            every evening <placeName ref="amb">in the church yard, about half a mile from the town,
               adjoining to which is a public road</placeName>. He was seen on Monday evening last
            pursuing a young woman, who shrieked dreadfully. Although there were four male
            passengers in the stage coach, which passed at the time, not one durst venture to the
            rescue of the distressed female. We have a very melancholy circumstance to add, the wife
            a labourer in the town, far advanced in a state of pregnancy, saw this Ghost, and her
            fright was so great, that her life is despaired of.</p>
         <p>On this occasion we feel additional concern from the life of an unoffending individual
            being taken away who was quite unconnected with the affair. We hope a discovery of the
            ghostly offender will soon take place, the most active search being now making for him
            by Mr. Hatchett and Mr. Hill, both Magistrates for the county.</p>
         <div>
            <head>CORONER’S INQUEST.</head>
            <p>Yesterday, at eleven o’clock, an Inquisition was taken before George Hodgson, Esq.
               the Coroner for the county, at the <placeName ref="#blacklionpub">Black Lion Public
                  house, Hammersmith</placeName>, on the body of Thomas Millwood, deceased, who was
               shot on Tuesday evening in <placeName ref="#beaverlanecross">a lane leading from
                  Black Lion-lane</placeName>, by person who was in quest of the pretended Ghost
               above mentioned.</p>
            <p>Three witnesses were examined; the first of horn was Mr. John Lock, who stated, that
               he as returning from the Plough and Harrow to <placeName ref="amb">his own house,
                  which is situate the corner of Black Lion-lane</placeName>, in company with a Mr.
               Stow. They had got as far as <placeName ref="unknown">the end of Lime
                  Kiln-lane</placeName>, and were crossing the road, when Smith an officer of
               Excise, in company with William Girdler, the private watchman, appointed to guard the
               neighbourhood, accosted them. Smith informed him that he had shot a man, and he
               believed that it was the person who had for some time past gone about assuming the
               character of the Ghost. They all went to the spot, where Smith said, the unfortunate
               person was lying, <placeName ref="#beaverlanecross">which was in a lane leading cross
                  from Beaver-lane to Black Lion lane</placeName>. Upon examining the body they
               discovered a gun-shot wound on the left side of the face just under the jaw, the skin
               of the face was completely black from the effect of the powder. The body was removed
               at the request of Mr. Lock to <placeName ref="#blacklionpub">the Black Lion public
                  house</placeName>. Mr. Lock had some conversation with Smith, who did not appear
               perfectly aware of his situation until he represented it to him, upon which he seemed
               very much affected, and said, that he had spoken to the deceased twice, but could not
               get any answer. Mr. Lock, in his evidence stated, that <placeName ref="#hammersmith"
                  >the town and neighbourhood of Hammersmith</placeName> had been annoyed for some
               months past, by the appearance, at a certain hour of the night, of some person
               assuming the complexion of a Ghost. The whole of Tuesday, he said, was very dark.—He
               had never seen the deceased before that night.</p>
            <p>Ann Millwood gave similar evidence as to the annoyance in the neighbourhood for
               upwards of two months by the pretended Ghost. This young woman, who is sister to the
               deceased, stated, that he resided in a house occupied by her father, in the lane
               alluded to; that on Tuesday night he left the house about eleven o’clock to go into
               the town: she felt herself alarmed lest something might happen to him, and indeed was
               so much alarmed that she got immediately upon some bricks to look after him, when
               almost instantly she heard somebody call out <q>damn you, what are you, or who are
                  you, tell me, or I’ll shoot you.</q> Immediately she heard the report of a gun,
               and went out of the house, and within the distance of 30 yards discovered her brother
               lying on his back dead. He was dressed in a white flannel jacket, with trowsers of
               the same, was by trade a bricklayer, and was 22 years of age. On being asked as to
               the probability of her brother’s assuming the appearance of a Ghost, she replied, she
               had never heard or believed that he did assume such an appearance.</p>
            <p>William Girdler, the private watchman employed by the inhabitants to watch near the
               spot where the unfortunate affair happened, gave in evidence that the neighbourhood
               was much alarmed, for two months past, by this pretended supernatural agent; that in
               consequence he made in appointment with Francis Smith, the person alluded to, by
               which it was agreed that cacti of them should watch in separate directions, on
               Tuesday night, for its approach.— Accordingly, about half past ten o’clock, they met
               at the top of Beaver-lane, while the witness was going his rounds, and they agreed
               upon a private signal, in case they met afterwards, that either one was to say,
                  <q>Friend! who comes there?</q> The reply to be, <q>Advance friend.</q> This being
               settled, they parted, and the witness pursued his course; when he got near the house
               of Mr. Stow which was situated in <placeName ref="#blacklionlane">Black
                  Lion-lane</placeName>, he heard the report of a gun. Having finished his rounds he
               was proceeding, in the space of ten minutes after, to the <placeName
                  ref="#whitehartpub">White Hart public house</placeName>, when he was called to by
               a young woman, who informed him that he was wanted. Shortly after Smith came up to
               him, and desired him to come along. The witness, wished to know whether he had seen
               any thing, or what was the matter; to which Smith replied, something very bad was the
               matter. The evidence here was exactly in point with the statement of the two former
               witnesses. Smith was very much affected, and expressed his wish to deliver himself
               into the hands of justice. In reply to some questions which were put to him by Mr.
               Lock, he said that he had called out to the deceased before he fired to know who he
               was, but not receiving an answer, he fired. The witness said, that on the Thursday
               night before the accident, he was going his rounds as usual about ten o’clock, when
               he saw a tall whitish figure, which on approaching nearer he found had a sheet over
               his head. Upon his approach, the figure threw up his hands and turned back the sheet,
               and he clearly perceived the person had on a dark coat with metal buttons.</p>
            <p>This was the whole of the evidence as to the unfortunate transaction. After it had
               been gone through, which was not till past three o’clock, the Coroner, Mr. Hodgson,
               with great perspicuity and judgment, summed up and directed the Jury’s particular
               attention to the principal points.</p>
            <p>The Jury consulted a few minutes, and delivered in a verdict of <emph>Wilful
                  Murder</emph> against Francis Smith: who was committed by the Coroner to Newgate,
               to take his trial at the next sessions.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
