<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/hoax.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GH-19CUK-18260312">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Ghost Laid</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Originally published by</resp>
               <name>Bell’s Life in London and Sporting Chronicle</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
               <name>Gabi Keane</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This project encoded newspaper and periodical articles on ghost hoaxes in the Victorian period. This publication of the text serves as data in a collaborative laboratory edition for the 2022 NEH Institute "Advanced digital editing: modeling the text and making the edition" at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
          </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Ghost hoaxes in 19th-century British news media</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>All texts in this collection were sourced from British periodical and newspaper
               archives, transcribed,and encoded. The citation below was provided by the archive and
               appears exactly as given.</p>
            <p><bibl>"THE GHOST LAID." <publisher>Bell’s Life in London and Sporting Chronicle</publisher>, <date when="1826-03-12">12 Mar. 1826</date>,
                  p. 82. 19th Century UK Periodicals, http://tinyurl.galegroup.com/tinyurl/85cwG7.
                  Accessed 20 Oct. 2018.</bibl></p>
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This document is part of a larger digital collection of stories of ghost hoaxes from
               the 18th and 19th century London newspapers and periodicals. The project explores the
               beginnings of mass print media in a metropolitan area at a time when technology and
               education made reading increasingly common and inexpensive.</p>
            <p>The corpus holds 36 individual documents, which reflect a diverse mix of reporting on
               various hauntings in and around London between 1804 and 1889. The PDF and JPEGs from
               online databases were transcribed using ABBYFineReader OCR, then corrected and
               occasionally manually transcribed if document quality necessitated it. After
               normalization in plain text, all documents were upconverted to TEI XML.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>Earlier texts have had some spelling normalization due to errors in OCR.
                  Typographic em dashes are longer than modern em dashes, so all dashes have been
                  normalized to modern em dash length.</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation>
               <p>All extraneous white space used by printers to avoid overlapping with letters has
                  been removed. All quotes are simply tagged with the q tag.</p>
            </quotation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>A respectable old gentleman, residing <placeName ref="amb">not many miles from the New
               Church,in the Strand</placeName>, and certainly not very superstitious, was, in the
            course of the last week, alarmed by an extraordinary and mysterious noise in his house,
            for which he was, for some nights, unable to account, and which, at length, almost
            removed his scepticism on the subject of unearthly visitations to this world. While
            sitting reading, as was his practice, to a late hour, his attention was attracted by a
            noise, as he thought, of some person coming down stairs in slippers, conceiving it was
            his good lady, who had retired to rest, and who was coming to invite him to follow her
            example, or their servant, he called to know who was there? but received no answer. The
            noise being continued, and having actually passed his door, he rose, took the light, and
            renewed his enquiry on the landing place; but with as little success, No reply was made.
            He then mounted to his bed-chamber, awoke his wife, and in company with her and (the
            servant, &amp; armed with a brace of pistols, searched every part of the premises for
            the supposed intruder, but without making any discovery. The same noise was repeated on
            the following night, but he was still unable to ascertain the cause. At length,
            determined to be on the watch, he placed himself in his room with the latch of the door
            in one hand, and a candle in the other. At the usual time the noise was repeated) and
            with no small trepidation our old friend cautiously peeped forth, and looked up the
            first flight of stairs, down which <rs ref="ghost">the slip shod ghost</rs> seemed to be coming. At first he
            could see nothing—probably from the disorganized state of his vision in such an alarming
            state of things; but at last he distinctly saw something small, but white, come hopping
            from step to step. <rs ref="ghost">It certainly had no earthly shape, and yet appeared to be gifted with
            a power of motion</rs>, which, as it approached him, encreased his alarm. He wished to speak,
            but either from the sudden inactivity of his organs of speech, or from not knowing
            exactly what to say to so questionable a visitor, he could not utter a word—when, wound
            up to a pitch of extraordinary excitation, his doubts and his fears were at once allayed
            by observing that the cause of his alarm was nothing more than <rs ref="ghost">a cake of Windsor soap,
            which a most portly and respectable sized rat had purloined from his bed-room, and was
            thus conveying, with no small labour, to his haunts below</rs>. The sudden relief thus given
            to his mind, induced him to make a motion that alarmed <rs ref="ghost">the industrious ghost</rs>, which, at
            one spring, reached a place of safety, leaving his booty behind—thus solving a mystery
            which had often led to a severe scolding to the servant for having appropriated to her
            own use divers pieces of soap and candle. On the next night <rs ref="ghost">the unfortunate freebooter</rs>
            made another excursion in search of plunder, and was again bearing off his spoil; but,
            unluckily, a fine tom cat having been called into requisition, he put an end to the life
            of the extraordinary entruder,and thus left our friend to the peaceable pursuit of his
            labours, not a little pleased to find that his doubts in the existence of goblins were
            still unshaken.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
