<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/hoax.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GH-TIMES-18040106">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hammersmith Ghost</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Originally published by</resp>
               <name>The Times</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
               <name>Gabi Keane</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This project encoded newspaper and periodical articles on ghost hoaxes in the Victorian period. This publication of the text serves as data in a collaborative laboratory edition for the 2022 NEH Institute "Advanced digital editing: modeling the text and making the edition" at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Ghost hoaxes in 19th-century British news media</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>All texts in this collection were sourced from British periodical and newspaper
               archives, transcribed,and encoded. The citation below was provided by the archive and
               appears exactly as given.</p>
            <p><bibl>"Hammersmith-Ghost." <publisher rend="The">Times</publisher> [London, England] <date when="1804-01-06">6 Jan. 1804</date>: 3. The Times Digital
                  Archive. Web. 21 Oct. 2018.</bibl></p>  
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This document is part of a larger digital collection of stories of ghost hoaxes from
               the 18th and 19th century London newspapers and periodicals. The project explores the
               beginnings of mass print media in a metropolitan area at a time when technology and
               education made reading increasingly common and inexpensive.</p>
            <p>The corpus holds 36 individual documents, which reflect a diverse mix of reporting on
               various hauntings in and around London between 1804 and 1889. The PDF and JPEGs from
               online databases were transcribed using ABBYFineReader OCR, then corrected and
               occasionally manually transcribed if document quality necessitated it. After
               normalization in plain text, all documents were upconverted to TEI XML.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>Earlier texts have had some spelling normalization due to errors in OCR.
                  Typographic em dashes are longer than modern em dashes, so all dashes have been
                  normalized to modern em dash length.</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation>
               <p>All extraneous white space used by printers to avoid overlapping with letters has
                  been removed. All quotes are simply tagged with the q tag.</p>
            </quotation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>﻿The Christmas tricks of <rs ref="ghost">this goblin</rs> have terminated in two
            melancholy accidents.</p>
         <p>Yesterday morning at 11 o’clock, a Coroner’s Inquest was held at the <placeName
               ref="#blacklionpub">Black Lion public-house, Hammersmith</placeName>, on the body of
            a young man, named Milward, who had been shot on the preceding night, in <placeName
               ref="#beaverlanecross">Cross-lane</placeName>, <placeName ref="amb">within a few
               doors of the place</placeName>, by a young man, named Smith, an Officer of Excise;
            and after a very full investigation of the circumstances, the Jury returned a verdict of
                  <q><emph>Wilful Murder,</emph></q> against the said Smith.</p>
         <p>The circumstances which led to that unhappy catastrophe, and which we have been at some
            pains to investigate on the spot, are as follow:--</p>
         <p>For several nights past, some very silly and thoughtless person had been in the habit of
            walking about <placeName ref="amb">the more lonely vicinities of <placeName
                  ref="#hammersmith">Hammersmith</placeName></placeName>, attired in a white sheet,
            to frighten women and children; and so far succeeded in acquiring the character of a
               <emph>dreadful ghost</emph>, as to frighten several poor women almost out of their
            senses. One woman, the wife of a locksmith, has lost her life through the fright, and
            now lies dead at <placeName ref="irr">Brook Green</placeName>, and two others lie
            dangerously ill from the same cause. Much alarm and irritation had of course been
            excited by these circumstances; and Mr. Smith having spent part of his evening at the
               <placeName ref="#whitehartpub">White Hart public-house</placeName>, left it,
            perfectly sober, with a purpose of passing the remainder at a private party, to which he
            had been invited; but by some means or other his purpose was changed, and he returned to
               <placeName ref="#whitehartpub">the White Hart</placeName>, where, amongst other
            topics, a conversation about the Ghost took place, with the consequences already stated
            that had befallen several women, and the great terror and alarm it had excited in the
            neighbourhood; when Smith went for his fowling-piece, which he brought back to the
               <placeName ref="#whitehartpub">White Hart public-house</placeName>, loaded it there
            with powder and shot, said he would act this night, go and try to meet the Ghost, and
            certainly shoot it. It was past eleven o’clock; he preconcerted with a watchman at the
            place to go up one lane, while he, Mr. Smith, should go round by another, the reputed
            haunt of the ghost; and as he came through <placeName ref="#beaverlanecross">Cross-lane,
               at the end of <placeName ref="#blacklionlane"
            >Black-Lion-lane</placeName></placeName>, he saw a man dressed in white, whom he
            challenged, and asked who he was. This person made no answer. The night was very dark.
            After a minute or two, he challenged him again, and told the person in white, if he did
            not answer and tell who he was, he would certainly shoot him. The man made no answer,
            and Mr. Smith fired at him, when he immediately fell, and instantly died. Smith
            observing him fall, ran up to him alarmed; but seeing him with scarcely any signs of
            life, he immediately ran back to the public house, expressed his alarm and apprehension
            that he had killed a man, and his determination of immediately surrendering himself to
            some Magistrate to answer for his misfortune.</p>
         <p>Both parties lived in, and were well known to, the neighbourhood. The deceased was a
            journeyman bricklayer, who was returning from <placeName ref="amb">the house of his
               father</placeName> to <placeName ref="amb">that of his father-in-law, where he lived,
               at a few yards distance</placeName>. He was in his working-dress, which was a white
            smock and trowsers. His sister, who had opened the door to let him out in his way home,
            had heard the challenge of Smith to him, and the shot which immediately followed; and
            shortly afterwards saw him lie dead. The discharge must have been very close to the
            deceased, as his face and shoulder appeared to be much scorched and blackened by the
            explosion. The contents of the piece entered in a close body his jaw-bone, which it
            shattered very much, and lodged in the opposite side at the back of his neck. What
            renders the circumstance still more melancholy is, that the deceased does not appear to
            have been the person who had assumed the appearance of a ghost.</p>
         <p>Mr. Smith readily surrendered himself to justice, and at six o’clock yesterday evening
            was brought in custody of the Bow-street officers, from <placeName ref="whitehartpub"
               >the White Hart public-house</placeName>, where he had been since morning, to
               <placeName ref="amb">town</placeName>, and committed to prison.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
