<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/hoax.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GH-GNCCO-18361008">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Hampstead Ghost? Legal Proceedings against the Police</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Originally published by</resp>
               <name>The Weekly True Sun</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
               <name>Gabi Keane</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This project encoded newspaper and periodical articles on ghost hoaxes in the Victorian period. This publication of the text serves as data in a collaborative laboratory edition for the 2022 NEH Institute "Advanced digital editing: modeling the text and making the edition" at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Ghost hoaxes in 19th-century British news media</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>All texts in this collection were sourced from British periodical and newspaper
               archives, transcribed,and encoded. The citation below was provided by the archive and
               appears exactly as given.</p>
            <p><bibl>"The Hampstead Ghost? Legal Proceedings against the Police."<publisher rend="The">Weekly True Sun</publisher>, <date when="1836-10-08">20
                  Nov. 1836</date>, p. 1350. Nineteenth Century Collections Online,
                  tinyurl.galegroup.com/tinyurl/54d3N1. Accessed 26 July 2017.</bibl></p>
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This document is part of a larger digital collection of stories of ghost hoaxes from
               the 18th and 19th century London newspapers and periodicals. The project explores the
               beginnings of mass print media in a metropolitan area at a time when technology and
               education made reading increasingly common and inexpensive.</p>
            <p>The corpus holds 36 individual documents, which reflect a diverse mix of reporting on
               various hauntings in and around London between 1804 and 1889. The PDF and JPEGs from
               online databases were transcribed using ABBYFineReader OCR, then corrected and
               occasionally manually transcribed if document quality necessitated it. After
               normalization in plain text, all documents were upconverted to TEI XML.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>Earlier texts have had some spelling normalization due to errors in OCR.
                  Typographic em dashes are longer than modern em dashes, so all dashes have been
                  normalized to modern em dash length.</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation>
               <p>All extraneous white space used by printers to avoid overlapping with letters has
                  been removed. All quotes are simply tagged with the q tag.</p>
            </quotation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>﻿It will be recollected that about a fortnight since Mr. Sutton, a respectable solicitor
            residing at <placeName ref="#hampstead">Hampstead</placeName>, was brought to this
            office in custody of the S division of police, on a charge of having assaulted two of
            the constables, under the following curious circumstances:— It appeared that a tall
            figure in a white mantle had been seen to pop its head up night after night from
               <placeName ref="amb">behind Mr. Sutton’s garden wall</placeName>, to the great
            consternation of passengers along the road, especially of females. In consequence of
            this, an application was made to Mr. Aggs, one of the inspectors of the divisions, who
            proceeded about a quarter past ten at night, to Mr. Sutton’s house, to search for the
               <q>ghost,</q> accompanied by Serjeant Rymer and another constable. Mr. Sutton not
            being at home, they communicated the errand they had come upon to Mr. Warmsley, Mr.
            Sutton’s father-in-law, an elderly gentleman, who (as alleged) gave them permission to
            search the premises. Mr. Aggs then went away, leaving the constables to perform their
            duty; but while they were beating the bushes with their staves in the garden for the
            ghost, Mr. Sutton arrived, and was much displeased at their intrusion, and, as alleged,
            kicked out the lights and assaulted them both, in consequence of which he was taken
            prisoner to the station house. Mr. Sutton denied that the constables ever had permission
            to search his place, and asserted that they had assaulted him, and used him so ill that
            intended to take legal proceedings against them. Mr. Rawlinson, before whom the case was
            heard, dismissed it, without prejudice to either party, and the matter for the time
            ended.</p>
         <p>Mr. Sutton, in fulfilment of his declaration, a Judge’s warrant against the two
            constables, who were yesterday apprehended upon it and conveyed before Mr. Justice
            Littledale, and at the same time Mr. Aggs, the inspector, was served with two notices of
            action for a trespass—one from Mr. Warmsley, and the other from Mr. Sutton himself.</p>
         <p>Mr. Aggs communicated these facts to Mr. Rawlinson, the sitting magistrate, yesterday,
            and requested his advice upon the subject.</p>
         <p>Mr. Rawlinson said that, as far as he was concerned, he had done with the case.</p>
         <p>Mr. Aggs then asked if Mr. Sutton could demand notice of bail to be given, as in such a
            case it would be extremely inconvenient to have the constables from their duty. As they
            were provided with bail, he hoped they would he immediately liberated.</p>
         <p>Mr. Rawlinson told Mr. Aggs that he did not think such notice requisite.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
