<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/hoax.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GH-GNCCO-18530709">
    <!-- 2022-05-02 djb created and added @xml:id-->
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Nelson's Ghost</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Originally published by</resp>
               <name>The Leader</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
               <name>Gabi Keane</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This project encoded newspaper and periodical articles on ghost hoaxes in the Victorian period. This publication of the text serves as data in a collaborative laboratory edition for the 2022 NEH Institute "Advanced digital editing: modeling the text and making the edition" at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Ghost hoaxes in 19th-century British news media</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>All texts in this collection were sourced from British periodical and newspaper
               archives, transcribed,and encoded. The citation below was provided by the archive and
               appears exactly as given.</p>
            <p><bibl>"Nelson's Ghost." <publisher rend="The">Leader</publisher>, <date when="1853-07-09">9 July 1853</date>, p. 660. Nineteenth Century Collections
                  Online, tinyurl.galegroup.com/tinyurl/55AEu4. Accessed 29 July 2017.</bibl></p>
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This document is part of a larger digital collection of stories of ghost hoaxes from
               the 18th and 19th century London newspapers and periodicals. The project explores the
               beginnings of mass print media in a metropolitan area at a time when technology and
               education made reading increasingly common and inexpensive.</p>
            <p>The corpus holds 36 individual documents, which reflect a diverse mix of reporting on
               various hauntings in and around London between 1804 and 1889. The PDF and JPEGs from
               online databases were transcribed using ABBYFineReader OCR, then corrected and
               occasionally manually transcribed if document quality necessitated it. After
               normalization in plain text, all documents were upconverted to TEI XML.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>Earlier texts have had some spelling normalization due to errors in OCR.
                  Typographic em dashes are longer than modern em dashes, so all dashes have been
                  normalized to modern em dash length.</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation>
               <p>All extraneous white space used by printers to avoid overlapping with letters has
                  been removed. All quotes are simply tagged with the q tag.</p>
            </quotation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Just now, <rs ref="pol">while we are preparing to meet possible foes by land and water</rs>, if <persName ref="#horationnelson">Nelson’s</persName>
            Ghost were to appear amongst us, would he not be welcomed? Assuredly he would be
            preferred for the command of the Channel fleet even to <persName ref="#johnrussell">Lord John Russell</persName>. But what would
            be the first thing that would strike his eye? It would be an advertisement in the
            papers, declaring, that to this day, the daughter whom he left as a legacy to his
            country, is unprovided for; that even now, having reached the maturity of life, and
            struggled with difficulties, she is still a creditor of the country he served so
            faithfully!</p>
         <p>Her claim, indeed, has been recognised by the gift of a paltry place to one of her
            sons—a bare provision for the young man. It is a recognition enough to stamp the
            obligation of the state with the royal admission, but not to fulfil it.</p>
         <p>Would <persName ref="#horationelson">Nelson</persName> on that account refuse to take the command even at the risk of dying over
            again? Assuredly not. He would repeat his simple and immortal precept, <q>England
               expects every man to do his duty,</q> even though England has shown so disgracefully
            how little she can understand her own duty.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
