<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/hoax.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GH-19CUK-18250130">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The New Hammersmith Ghost</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Originally published by</resp>
               <name>Bell’s Life in London and Sporting Chronicle</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
               <name>Gabi Keane</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This project encoded newspaper and periodical articles on ghost hoaxes in the Victorian period. This publication of the text serves as data in a collaborative laboratory edition for the 2022 NEH Institute "Advanced digital editing: modeling the text and making the edition" at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Ghost hoaxes in 19th-century British news media</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>All texts in this collection were sourced from British periodical and newspaper
               archives, transcribed,and encoded. The citation below was provided by the archive and
               appears exactly as given.</p>
            <p><bibl>"The New Hammersmith Ghost." <publisher>Bell’s Life in London and Sporting Chronicle</publisher>, <date when="1825-01-30">30
                  Jan. 1825</date>. 19th Century UK Periodicals, http://tinyurl.com/yahgex6w. Accessed 31
                  July 2017.</bibl></p>
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This document is part of a larger digital collection of stories of ghost hoaxes from
               the 18th and 19th century London newspapers and periodicals. The project explores the
               beginnings of mass print media in a metropolitan area at a time when technology and
               education made reading increasingly common and inexpensive.</p>
            <p>The corpus holds 36 individual documents, which reflect a diverse mix of reporting on
               various hauntings in and around London between 1804 and 1889. The PDF and JPEGs from
               online databases were transcribed using ABBYFineReader OCR, then corrected and
               occasionally manually transcribed if document quality necessitated it. After
               normalization in plain text, all documents were upconverted to TEI XML.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>Earlier texts have had some spelling normalization due to errors in OCR.
                  Typographic em dashes are longer than modern em dashes, so all dashes have been
                  normalized to modern em dash length.</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation>
               <p>All extraneous white space used by printers to avoid overlapping with letters has
                  been removed. All quotes are simply tagged with the q tag.</p>
            </quotation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>This personage, who has been styled the<q>Monster,</q> in consequence of his having
            torn as well as frightened divers females, resumed his manly visitations during the
            recent dark nights; but with one exception, he appears to have most carefully avoided
            his old haunts; for the hint was taken, and many persons, attired like women, were on
            the watch. A purse of twenty pounds is stated to have been subscribed for any person who
            shall bring in the ghostly monster dead or alive, of course. On one occasion, the ghost
            knocked at an old woman’s cottage, <placeName ref="#starchgreen amb">near Starch green,
               leading to Acton</placeName>. She opened the door, when the white-sheeted gentleman
            presented himself in all the mock horrors of his amiable amusement. She fainted away, in
            consequence, and has since been very ill. On another night, he attacked an old woman,
            passing up <placeName ref="#angellane">Angel-lane</placeName>, where the servant of the
               <placeName ref="#angelpub">Angel public-house</placeName> was so repeatedly attacked,
            and which servant is even now constantly the victim of fits. The old lady had a lantern
            with her. The ghost came behind her, made a groaning noise, tapped at the lantern,
            &amp;.c.; but she had the presence of mind to avoid expressing any fear, pursuing her
            course, without looking ot the right or to the left, and only observing— <q>You would
               not be base enough to hurt an old woman, would you?</q> The ghost continued his
            tricks, but dame was firm; and when she approached <placeName ref="amb">some houses at
               the end of the lane</placeName>, the fellow retired. A few nights since the
            apprentice of Mr. Hammond, smith, &amp; c., residing <placeName ref="unknown amb">near
               Webb’s-lane</placeName>, Hammersmith, was passing up a lane, <placeName
               ref="unknown amb">near some newly built houses, leading to the Hammersmith
               Waterworks</placeName>, close by where <emph>Ghosty</emph> jumped upon an old man’s
            back, and broke his leg, and there the apprentice met with the ghost. The apprentice is
            a spirited lad. The ghost appeared to him<q>to rise out of the ground,</q> as he says;
            but having his thoughts directed to the glory of the transaction, and, perhaps, the
            reward, he boldly attacked the ghost, threw at him first the basket of tin goods which
            he had on his arm, and then seized hold of the mantle which the lad says had a silky
            feel. There was much tugging between them— at last Ghosty gave the lad a violent blow on
            the back of the neck, and laid him sprawling in the road, thus disengaging himself, and
            then hastily decamped. The lad was soon afterwards picked up by some neighbouring
            people, and conveyed home; but he has since shown no disposition to go out at night,
            lest he should again encounter the ghost’s strong arm. A man residing in <placeName
               ref="#hammersmith">Hammersmith</placeName> also came in contact with Ghosty one
            night, and they got struggling for mastery, when Ghosty settled it by giving the man a
            blow which levelled him with the earth, after which the nocturnal agitator was enabled
            to escape. It was rumoured that he had been seized one night at <placeName
               ref="#kensington">Kensington</placeName>— that he was discovered to be a Nobleman’s
            son, whereupon the matter was<q>hushed up,</q> and that he was playing these pranks for
            a bet, having wagered that he would<q>walk as a ghost</q> for a certain number of nights
            without being taken or <q>laid.</q> If this were true, the capture would decide the
            wager; but unfortunately for its truth, he has since appeared.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
