<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/hoax.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GH-GNCCO-18361016">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Not Dead, or No Ghost</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Originally published by</resp>
               <name>The Weekly Times</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
               <name>Gabi Keane</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This project encoded newspaper and periodical articles on ghost hoaxes in the Victorian period. This publication of the text serves as data in a collaborative laboratory edition for the 2022 NEH Institute "Advanced digital editing: modeling the text and making the edition" at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Ghost hoaxes in 19th-century British news media</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>All texts in this collection were sourced from British periodical and newspaper
               archives, transcribed,and encoded. The citation below was provided by the archive and
               appears exactly as given.</p>
            <p><bibl>"Not Dead, or No Ghost." <publisher rend="The">Weekly Times</publisher>, <date when="1836-10-16">16 Oct. 1836</date>. Nineteenth Century
                  Collections Online, tinyurl.galegroup.com/tinyurl/55AP33. Accessed 29 July
                  2017.</bibl></p>
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This document is part of a larger digital collection of stories of ghost hoaxes from
               the 18th and 19th century London newspapers and periodicals. The project explores the
               beginnings of mass print media in a metropolitan area at a time when technology and
               education made reading increasingly common and inexpensive.</p>
            <p>The corpus holds 36 individual documents, which reflect a diverse mix of reporting on
               various hauntings in and around London between 1804 and 1889. The PDF and JPEGs from
               online databases were transcribed using ABBYFineReader OCR, then corrected and
               occasionally manually transcribed if document quality necessitated it. After
               normalization in plain text, all documents were upconverted to TEI XML.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>Earlier texts have had some spelling normalization due to errors in OCR.
                  Typographic em dashes are longer than modern em dashes, so all dashes have been
                  normalized to modern em dash length.</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation>
               <p>All extraneous white space used by printers to avoid overlapping with letters has
                  been removed. All quotes are simply tagged with the q tag.</p>
            </quotation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>﻿ On Saturday the following extraordinary circumstance was communicated at <placeName
               ref="#hattongarden">Hatton Garden</placeName>:— About six weeks ago a young woman
            drowned herself in the canal, and the body was owned by a Mrs. Edwards, of
               <placeName ref="unknown">Nelson’s Passage, Goswell Street</placeName>, as that of her missing
            sister. After the inquest the deceased was conveyed in a shell to the residence of Mrs.
            Edwards, when the usual preparations were made for the funeral. The whole of the family
            went into mourning and followed the body to the grave, deeply deploring the untimely
            fate of their relative. On Friday, however, as Mrs. Edwards was passing through <placeName ref="unknown">Goswell
            Street Road</placeName>, she was almost petrified at beholding what she conceived to be the ghost of
            her deceased sister. She started back, and after staring at the form for a short time,
            she ran off, when the <soCalled>apparation</soCalled> pursued her, calling out. <q>Mary,
               stop; Mary, stop;</q> but this had the effect of increasing her alarm so much, that
            the poor woman fell down in strong hysterics. When she recovered it was soon proved to
            her that it was no ghost but her real and living sister. The mystery was then
            unravelled, it appearing that Mr. Edwards’s sister, had, in consequence of a quarrel
            with her husband, determined on going into the country, and living with him no longer.
            The clothes of the deceased have been forwarded to the police. It has not yet been
            ascertained who the deceased was.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
