<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/hoax.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GH-TIMES-18040118">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Notwithstanding our repeated publications...</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Originally published by</resp>
               <name>The Times</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
               <name>Gabi Keane</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This project encoded newspaper and periodical articles on ghost hoaxes in the Victorian period. This publication of the text serves as data in a collaborative laboratory edition for the 2022 NEH Institute "Advanced digital editing: modeling the text and making the edition" at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Ghost hoaxes in 19th-century British news media</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>All texts in this collection were sourced from British periodical and newspaper
               archives, transcribed,and encoded. The citation below was provided by the archive and
               appears exactly as given.</p>
            <p><bibl>Notwithstanding our repeated publications of the documents upon which our
               details respecting the. <publisher rend="The">Times</publisher> (London, England), Wednesday, <date when="1804-01-18">Jan 18, 1804</date>; pg.
                  2; Issue 5922. (614 words)</bibl></p>
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This document is part of a larger digital collection of stories of ghost hoaxes from
               the 18th and 19th century London newspapers and periodicals. The project explores the
               beginnings of mass print media in a metropolitan area at a time when technology and
               education made reading increasingly common and inexpensive.</p>
            <p>The corpus holds 36 individual documents, which reflect a diverse mix of reporting on
               various hauntings in and around London between 1804 and 1889. The PDF and JPEGs from
               online databases were transcribed using ABBYFineReader OCR, then corrected and
               occasionally manually transcribed if document quality necessitated it. After
               normalization in plain text, all documents were upconverted to TEI XML.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>Earlier texts have had some spelling normalization due to errors in OCR.
                  Typographic em dashes are longer than modern em dashes, so all dashes have been
                  normalized to modern em dash length.</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation>
               <p>All extraneous white space used by printers to avoid overlapping with letters has
                  been removed. All quotes are simply tagged with the q tag.</p>
            </quotation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>﻿Notwithstanding our repeated publications of the documents upon which our details
            respecting the <rs ref="ghost">St. James’s Park Ghost</rs> were founded, <rs ref="mis">still
            certain Prints continue to charge us with having fabricated the story</rs>. We do not pretend
            to <q>take the Ghost’s word</q> against reason and philosophy, <rs ref="public">at the same time we
            thought it our duty to enquire into the foundation of the rumours, which had for so many
            days played upon the public credulity</rs>, and to state the result of our enquiries on the
            subject, which, we flatter ourselves, have proved as satisfactory as the nature of the
            business would admit.</p>
         <p>A Morning Print asserts, <q>that some papers</q> (we confess we are at a loss to know
            which) <q>very candidly confess, that the abilities of their employers are not above the
               common level; but they still continue to assert their integrity and good
               intention.</q> Of the <emph>employers</emph> of the Paper in question, we believe, no
            person will be mad enough to assert, that they have either <emph>good abilities</emph>,
            or good <emph>intentions</emph>.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
