<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/hoax.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GH-TIMES-18380109">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Police Column: Yesterday The Lord Mayor...</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Originally published by</resp>
               <name>The Times</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
               <name>Gabi Keane</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This project encoded newspaper and periodical articles on ghost hoaxes in the Victorian period. This publication of the text serves as data in a collaborative laboratory edition for the 2022 NEH Institute "Advanced digital editing: modeling the text and making the edition" at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Ghost hoaxes in 19th-century British news media</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>All texts in this collection were sourced from British periodical and newspaper
               archives, transcribed,and encoded. The citation below was provided by the archive and
               appears exactly as given.</p>
            <p><bibl>"Police." <publisher rend="The">Times</publisher>, <date when="1838-01-09">9 Jan. 1838</date>, p. 4. The Times Digital Archive,
                  http://tinyurl.galegroup.com/tinyurl/8tRZH4. Accessed 25 Jan. 2019.</bibl></p>
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This document is part of a larger digital collection of stories of ghost hoaxes from
               the 18th and 19th century London newspapers and periodicals. The project explores the
               beginnings of mass print media in a metropolitan area at a time when technology and
               education made reading increasingly common and inexpensive.</p>
            <p>The corpus holds 36 individual documents, which reflect a diverse mix of reporting on
               various hauntings in and around London between 1804 and 1889. The PDF and JPEGs from
               online databases were transcribed using ABBYFineReader OCR, then corrected and
               occasionally manually transcribed if document quality necessitated it. After
               normalization in plain text, all documents were upconverted to TEI XML.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>Earlier texts have had some spelling normalization due to errors in OCR.
                  Typographic em dashes are longer than modern em dashes, so all dashes have been
                  normalized to modern em dash length.</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation>
               <p>All extraneous white space used by printers to avoid overlapping with letters has
                  been removed. All quotes are simply tagged with the q tag.</p>
            </quotation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p><placeName ref="#mansionhouse">Mansion House</placeName>.— Yesterday the Lord Mayor said
            that he had received a letter upon a subject, the odd nature of which had induced him to
            withhold it from the public for some days, in the expectation that some statement might
            be made through a source of indisputable authority relative to the matter of which it
            treated.</p>
         <p>The following is the letter:—</p>
         <p><q/>To the right Hon. the Lord Mayor.</p>
         <p><q/>My Lord,— the writer presumes that your Lordship will kindly overlook the liberty he
            has taken in addressing a few lines on a subject which within the last few weeks has
            caused much alarming sensation in the neighbouring villages within three or four miles
            of London.</p>
         <p><q/>It appears that some individuals (of, as the writer believes, the higher ranks of
            life) have laid a wager with a mischievous and foolhardy companion <rs ref="springheeledjack">(name as yet
            unknown)</rs>, that he durst not take upon himself the task of visiting many of <placeName
               ref="rel amb">the villages near London</placeName> in three different disguises— a
            ghost, a bear, and a devil; and, moreover, that he will not dare to enter gentlemen’s
            gardens for the purpose of alarming the inmates of the house. The wager has, however,
            been accepted, and the unmanly villain has succeeded in depriving seven ladies of their
            senses. <placeName ref="amb">At one house</placeName> he rung the bell, and on the
            servant coming to open the door, this worse than brute stood in a no less dreadful
            figure than a spectre clad most perfectly. The consequence was that, the poor girl
            immediately swooned, and has never from that moment been in her senses, but, on seeing
            any man, screams out most violently <q>Take him away!</q> There are two ladies (which
            your Lordship will regret to hear), who have husbands and children, and who are not
            expected to recover, but likely to become burdens to their families.</p>
         <p><q/>For fear that your Lordship might imagine that the writer exaggerates, he will
            refrain from mentioning other cases, if any thing, more melancholy than those he has
            already related.</p>
         <p><q/>This affair has now been going on for some time, and, strange to say, the papers are
            still silent on the subject. The writer is very unwilling to be unjust towards any man,
            but he was reason to believe that they have the whole history at their finger ends, but,
            through interested motives, are induced to remain silent. <rs ref="justice">It is, however, high time that
            such detestable nuisance should be put a stop to, and the writer feels assured that your
            Lordship, as the chief magistrate of London, will take great pleasure in exerting your
            power to bring the villain to justice.</rs></p>
         <p><q/>Hoping your Lordship will pardon the liberty I have taken in writing, I remain your
            Lordship’s most humble servant, <q>A Resident of <placeName ref="#peckham"
                  >Peckham</placeName>.</q></p>
         <p><rs ref="mis">The Lord Mayor on reading the account observed that, as our friends on the other side of
            the Atlantic were in the habit of saying, it was <q>extraordinary if true.</q></rs> In his
            opinion it was not calculated for the meridian of London, but if any trick had been
            practised by fools, he had no doubt that the vigilance of the police might be depended
            upon to of the Lord Mayor, but as the terrible vision had not entered the city, he could
            not take cognizance of its iniquities.</p>
         <p>A gentleman stated to his Lordship that the servant girls about <placeName
               ref="#kensington">Kensington</placeName>, and <placeName ref="#hammersmith"
               >Hammersmith</placeName>, and <placeName ref="#ealing">Ealing</placeName>, told
            dreadful stories of the ghost or devil, who, on one occasion, was said to have beaten a
            blacksmith, and torn his flesh with iron claws, and in others to tear the clothes from
            the backs of females. Not one of the injured people had been known to tell the story;
            perhaps they didn’t like to tell it.</p>
         <p>The Lord Mayor believed that one of the ladies who had lost their seven senses was his
            correspondent. He hoped she would do him the favour of a call, and he would have an
            opportunity of getting from her such a description of the demon as would enable him to
            catch him, in spite of the paid press and police.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
