<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/hoax.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GH-GNCCO-18331215">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Resuscitation of The Hammersmith Ghost</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Originally published by</resp>
               <name>The Weekly True Sun</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
               <name>Gabi Keane</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This project encoded newspaper and periodical articles on ghost hoaxes in the Victorian period. This publication of the text serves as data in a collaborative laboratory edition for the 2022 NEH Institute "Advanced digital editing: modeling the text and making the edition" at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Ghost hoaxes in 19th-century British news media</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>All texts in this collection were sourced from British periodical and newspaper
               archives, transcribed,and encoded. The citation below was provided by the archive and
               appears exactly as given.</p>
            <p><bibl>"Resuscitation of the Hammersmith Ghost." <publisher rend="The">Weekly True Sun</publisher>, <date when="1833-12-15">15 Dec. 1833</date>, p.
                  123. Nineteenth Century Collections Online,
                  http://tinyurl.galegroup.com/tinyurl/8wMqL7. Accessed 30 Jan. 2019.</bibl></p>
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This document is part of a larger digital collection of stories of ghost hoaxes from
               the 18th and 19th century London newspapers and periodicals. The project explores the
               beginnings of mass print media in a metropolitan area at a time when technology and
               education made reading increasingly common and inexpensive.</p>
            <p>The corpus holds 36 individual documents, which reflect a diverse mix of reporting on
               various hauntings in and around London between 1804 and 1889. The PDF and JPEGs from
               online databases were transcribed using ABBYFineReader OCR, then corrected and
               occasionally manually transcribed if document quality necessitated it. After
               normalization in plain text, all documents were upconverted to TEI XML.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>Earlier texts have had some spelling normalization due to errors in OCR.
                  Typographic em dashes are longer than modern em dashes, so all dashes have been
                  normalized to modern em dash length.</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation>
               <p>All extraneous white space used by printers to avoid overlapping with letters has
                  been removed. All quotes are simply tagged with the q tag.</p>
            </quotation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>It is in the recollection of most of our readers that about eight years since much
            excitement was created by a report that a ghost had appeared to a number of persons in
            the neighbourhood of <placeName ref="#hammersmith">Hammersmith</placeName>, <placeName
               ref="#fulham">Fulham</placeName>, <placeName ref="amb">&amp;c.</placeName>, several
            of whom, more particularly females, against whom he appeared to have a great animosity,
            had been much frightened and ill-treated by him. After continuing his freaks for some
            time, he became so troublesome that the parochial authorities adopted measures for his
            apprehension, and after watching for him for some nights he was taken in one of the
            lanes attired in full ghostly costume, and <rs ref="justice">was sent by the magistrates to the House of
            Correction to undergo a little wholesome discipline for his pranks</rs>. Since that time
            nothing has been heard of his ghostship until about six weeks ago, when he re-appeared
            in <placeName ref="#north-end">a lane at North-end</placeName>, and it is reported that
            he has been seen subsequently in <placeName ref="#webbslane">Webb’s-lane,
               Hammersmith</placeName>, and <placeName ref="#acton">Acton</placeName>; but the
            principal scene of his adventures is stated to be the mad hats in <placeName
               ref="#chiswick-lane">Chiswick-lane</placeName>, and that the servant of a Mr. Scott
            was attacked by him there, his assaults, as before, being directed against females. On a
            Saturday night last it was currently reported that he had been taken by the police at
               <placeName ref="#acton">Acton</placeName>, attired in a large white dress, with long
            nails or claws, by which he was enabled to scale walls and hedges for the purpose of
            making himself scarce, when requisite, and that when brought to the station-house he
            proved to be a celebrated Captain of sporting notoreity. Several of the inhabitants
            attended the <placeName ref="#hammersmith">Hammersmith</placeName>, &amp;c., Petty Sessions, on Monday, in the hope of obtaining
            an audience of the spiritual <emph>incognito</emph>, when it was found that the
            statement of his apprehension was premature. Another report states him to be dressed in
            armour, and that he has laid a wager that he will strip the clothes off a certain number
            of females in a given time, and that he has now only one more to strip to win the bet.
            <rs ref="justice">It is to be hoped that the police will put a stop to the pranks of his ghostship
            previous to his completing his task, that he may receive a proper reward for his
            exertions.</rs></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
