<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/hoax.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GH-TIMES-18040117">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Park Ghost</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Originally published by</resp>
                    <name>The Times</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
                    <name>Gabi Keane</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>This project encoded newspaper and periodical articles on ghost hoaxes in the Victorian period. This publication of the text serves as data in a collaborative laboratory edition for the 2022 NEH Institute "Advanced digital editing: modeling the text and making the edition" at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>Ghost hoaxes in 19th-century British news media</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>All texts in this collection were sourced from British periodical and newspaper
                    archives, transcribed,and encoded. The citation below was provided by the
                    archive and appears exactly as given.</p>
                <p><bibl>"Park Ghost." <publisher rend="The">Times</publisher> [London, England] <date when="1804-01-17">17 Jan. 1804</date>: 3. The Times Digital
                        Archive. Web. 30 Oct. 2018.</bibl></p>
            </sourceDesc>

        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This document is part of a larger digital collection of stories of ghost hoaxes
                    from the 18th and 19th century London newspapers and periodicals. The project
                    explores the beginnings of mass print media in a metropolitan area at a time
                    when technology and education made reading increasingly common and
                    inexpensive.</p>
                <p>The corpus holds 36 individual documents, which reflect a diverse mix of
                    reporting on various hauntings in and around London between 1804 and 1889. The
                    PDF and JPEGs from online databases were transcribed using ABBYFineReader OCR,
                    then corrected and occasionally manually transcribed if document quality
                    necessitated it. After normalization in plain text, all documents were
                    upconverted to TEI XML.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Earlier texts have had some spelling normalization due to errors in OCR.
                        Typographic em dashes are longer than modern em dashes, so all dashes have
                        been normalized to modern em dash length.</p>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All extraneous white space used by printers to avoid overlapping with letters
                        has been removed. All quotes are simply tagged with the q tag.</p>
                </quotation>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>It was not our intention to have said any thing more respecting this
                        <rs ref="ghost"><emph>ghost</emph></rs>, had we not been in some measure urged to renew the
                    subject in our own vindication. <rs ref="mis">One of our fellow-journalists, on Saturday,
                    charged us with being <q>conjurors, and that, by our <emph>magic spells</emph>,
                        we had <emph>conjured</emph> up <rs ref="ghost">a <emph>ghost</emph> without a head, and
                        stationed its haunts in <placeName ref="#stjamespark">St. James’s
                            Park</placeName></rs>, but that it was only known to ourselves.</q></rs> Now, we
                    shall satisfactorily prove, that there were grounds for our statement.</p>
                <p>The story of the appearance of <rs ref="ghost">an <emph>uncouth figure</emph>, in <placeName ref="#stjamespark">St. James’s
                    Park</placeName>, in the dead of the night</rs>, had occasioned much conversation amongst the
                    Guards for some time past; and so generally was the fact believed, that, at a
                    late hour on Saturday night, a clergyman entered the Bird Cage Walk, and
                    patroled it for several hours, in the hope that he might meet <rs ref="ghost">the figure</rs>, when,
                    he trusted, he should detect some person, who, through wantonness, was
                    endeavouring to alarm the neighbourhood. The whole night, however, passed away,
                    without his being able to make any discovery. Indeed, it would appear, that the
                    result of the trial of <emph>Smith,</emph> arising from the melancholy affair of
                    the <emph><rs ref="ghost hammersmith">Hammersmith ghost,</rs></emph> had reached
                    <rs ref="ghost">the <emph>ears</emph> of the <emph>headless woman</emph> in the Park</rs>, and that
                    she had, in consequence, bade adieu to her nightly visits in that quarter.</p>
                <p>The last time, it is said, that this <rs ref="ghost"><emph>phantom</emph></rs> was seen, was upwards
                    of a week ago, when it was observed, about one o’clock in the morning, to walk
                    with solemn gait, <placeName ref="#cockpit">from the Cockpit door to the
                        Canal</placeName>; but whether it afterwards vanished in the air, or sunk
                    into the water, the informant cannot say. It was not until the other day, that
                    the old women about <placeName ref="#stjamespark">the Park</placeName> were able
                    to account for the <rs ref="ghost"><emph>ghost</emph>'s appearance</rs>, and they now recollect,
                    that, about sixteen years ago, a serjeant murdered his wife <placeName
                        ref="#stjamespark">in the Park</placeName>, by cutting off her head, and they
                    therefore attributed the phantom's appearance to that circumstance.</p>
                <p>The officers of the Guards did not think it worth while to investigate this tale
                    of horror, till they had reason to believe that the story had made some
                    impression on the minds of some of the soldiers. Accordingly, yesterday at one
                    o’clock, the Adjutant of the Coldstream Regiment went to the orderly-room, at
                    the Horse Guards, and sent for George Jones, of the 16th Company, for the
                    purpose of interrogating him respecting the <rs ref="ghost"><emph>ghost</emph></rs>, as it was said
                    that he was one of the men who had seen it, and had been considerably affected
                    by the sight. The man accordingly attended, and declared his readiness to make
                    oath of the truth of what he had already stated.</p>
                <p>The following is a copy of a declaration which he afterwards made and signed
                    before an Officer:</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <q>I do solemnly declare, that, whilst on guard at <placeName ref="unknown">the
                        Recruit House</placeName>, on or about the 3d instant, about half past one
                    o’clock in the morning, I perceived <rs ref="ghost">the figure of a woman, without a head, rise
                    from the earth, at the distance of about three feet before me</rs>. I was so alarmed
                    at the circumstance, that I had not power to speak to it, which was my wish to
                    have done; but I distinctly observed that <rs ref="ghost">the figure was dressed in a red
                    striped gown with red spots between each stripe, and that part of the dress and
                    figure apeared to me to be enveloped in a cloud.</rs></q>
                <q>In about the space of two seconds, <rs ref="ghost">whilst my eyes were fixed on the object, it
                    vanished from my sight</rs>. I was perfectly sober and collected at the time, and,
                    being in great trepidation, called to the next sentinel, who met me about half
                    way, and to whom I communicated the strange sight I had seen.</q>
                <closer>(Signed) <signed><q><persName ref="#georgejones">George Jones</persName>, of Lieutenant-Colonel Taylor's Company of
                            Coldstream Guards</q></signed>
                    <placeName ref="#westminster">Westminster</placeName>, <date>Jan. 15,
                        1804</date></closer>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>To the declaration of Jones we have to add another, connected with the subject,
                    and which is equally genuine:—</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <q>I do hereby declare, that whilst on guard <placeName ref="rel unknown">behind the
                        Armoury-house</placeName>, (to the best of my recollection about three weeks
                    ago) I heard, at twelve o’clock at night, a tremendous noise, which proceeded
                    from the window of an uninhabited house, near to the spot where I was upon duty.
                    At the same time, I heard a voice cry out. <q>Bring me a light! bring me a
                        light!</q> The last sentence was uttered in so feeble and so changeable a
                    tone of voice, that I concluded some person was ill, and consequently offered
                    them my assistance to procure a light. I could, however, obtain no answer to my
                    proposal, although I repeated it several times, and as often heard the voice use
                    the same terms. I endeavoured to see the person who called out, but in vain. On
                    a sudden the violent noise was renewed, which appeared to me to resemble sashes
                    of windows lifted hastily up and down, but then they were moved in such quick
                    succession, and at different parts of the house nearly at the same time, that it
                    seemed impossible to me that one person could accomplish the whole business. I
                    heard several of the regiment say they have heard similar noises and
                    proceedings, but I have never heard the cause accounted for.</q>
                <closer>(Signed) <signed><persName ref="richarddonkin">Richard Donkin</persName>, 12th Company of Coldstream Guards</signed>
                    <placeName ref="#whitehall">Whitehall</placeName>, <date>Jan. 15, 1804</date>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>After furnishing the above documents, <rs ref="mis">we shall hardly be again accused of having
                    framed the account in Friday’s Paper</rs>, from a circumstance which occurred ten
                    years ago.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
