<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/hoax.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GH-19CUK-18380127">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ghost</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Originally published by</resp>
                    <name>The Penny Satirist</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
                    <name>Emma Schwarz</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>This project encoded newspaper and periodical articles on ghost hoaxes in the
                    Victorian period. This publication of the text serves as data in a collaborative
                    laboratory edition for the 2022 NEH Institute "Advanced digital editing:
                    modeling the text and making the edition" at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>Ghost hoaxes in 19th-century British news media</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>All texts in this collection were sourced from British periodical and newspaper
                    archives, transcribed,and encoded. The citation below was provided by the
                    archive and appears exactly as given.</p>
                <p>
                    <bibl>"The Ghost." <publisher rend="The">Penny Satirist</publisher>, <date
                            when="1838-01-27">27 Jan. 1838</date>, p. 2. 19th Century UK
                        Periodicals, https://tinyurl.com/yejmuju9. Accessed 21 June 2022.</bibl>
                </p>
            </sourceDesc>

        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This document is part of a larger digital collection of stories of ghost hoaxes
                    from the 18th and 19th century London newspapers and periodicals. The project
                    explores the beginnings of mass print media in a metropolitan area at a time
                    when technology and education made reading increasingly common and
                    inexpensive.</p>
                <p>The corpus holds 36 individual documents, which reflect a diverse mix of
                    reporting on various hauntings in and around London between 1804 and 1889. The
                    PDF and JPEGs from online databases were transcribed using ABBYFineReader OCR,
                    then corrected and occasionally manually transcribed if document quality
                    necessitated it. After normalization in plain text, all documents were
                    upconverted to TEI XML.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Earlier texts have had some spelling normalization due to errors in OCR.
                        Typographic em dashes are longer than modern em dashes, so all dashes have
                        been normalized to modern em dash length.</p>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All extraneous white space used by printers to avoid overlapping with letters
                        has been removed. All quotes are simply tagged with the q tag.</p>
                </quotation>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <p>The canny Scot has been wilily hunting the <rs ref="ghost">canny ghost</rs> for
                several days. The zeal of our friend, which was somewhat cool at first, and animated
                alone by his patriotism, or public spirit, which is at all times but a niggardly
                paymaster, was increased as he proceeded by the interesting particulars which he
                learned by the way concerning this <rs ref="ghost">man of the mist</rs>. At
                    <placeName ref="peckham">Peckham</placeName>, a young woman came running along,
                as if for life, and threw herself into Macdougal's arms, screaming for protection.
                It was with the greatest difficulty he could get rid of her. It was only by
                proposing to rouse a Justice of the Peace, and give information of the spring-heeled
                visitor's arrival, that the girl, whose delicacy prevented her from appearing in
                such a public capacity, silently withdrew, and Sandy was left alone to brave the
                pricipalities and <rs ref="ghost">the powers of the spiritual world</rs>.</p>
            <p>After this, he went out of the highway a little, to see if Chance would direct him
                to <rs ref="ghost">the monster against which he had previously well secured
                    himself</rs>, by putting a horse shoe into his pocket, and eating an adder
                boiled in ewe's milk, and there he really did see <rs ref="ghost">a fearful image
                    coming right up to him</rs>. There were <rs ref="ghost">two huge eyes gleaming
                    fire and flame about the middle of its body, and a man's head above, strongly
                    illuminated, and sending forth a glare of light for many yards around it</rs>.
                Sandy held the horse shoe fast in his left hand, and rubbed his knees with the other
                as he proceeded. Honour alone gave him resolution to go on, for he declares he had
                very little faith in the horseshoe. At last <rs ref="ghost">the monster</rs>
                approached him, <q>Avaunt thee, wraith</q>, said Sandy, horror-struck, and giving
                way to let <rs ref="ghost">the deserter from the tomb</rs> have a free passage. <rs
                    ref="ghost">The monster</rs> replied, <q>fine evening</q>, in a very mild tone.
                Sandy resumed courage immediately, and looking up, saw a donkey with a lantern fixed
                to each side of its head, and a stout, happy looking country lass sitting on its
                back, with a lantern in one hand, and a basket in the other. <q>Fine evening</q>,
                said Sandy, whose heart was immediately disburdened. But afraid to proceed any
                further, he turned round, and proceeded towards the highway with the ass and its
                fair pilot, who, however, seemed not to relish his company, for his sudden change of
                resolution seemed somewhat suspicious. Just, then, an inspector of police rode up.
                The girl stopped and spoke to him, and Sandy walked on. He was soon overtaken by the
                police officer, who asked him where he had been, and whither he was going. Sandy did
                not well know what to say. He was therefore suspected, taken to the station-house,
                and when he ingeniously told his examiners that he had come from <placeName
                    ref="london">London</placeName> upon a mission to lay <rs ref="ghost">the
                    ghost</rs>, he raised a roar of laughter, but by no means tended to lay the
                suspicions of the blues. He was kept in the station-house all night, and came home
                in a deuce of a plight the next morning.</p>
            <p>Not deterred, however, by this unfortunate termination to his first adventure, he
                determined to make another attempt, and the Major himself proposed, for friendship
                and a lark, to accompany him. The Major is an opium eater on important occasions,
                and before he set out he administered to himself an unusual dose, and persuaded
                Sandy to join him in the prescription. They proceeded towards <placeName
                    ref="kensington">Kensington Gardens</placeName>, and their courage mounted as
                they went. Their very eyes emitted rays of light, and their two sticks, which they
                wielded with extraordinary vigour, so alarmed the minds of all they met, that there
                can be no doubt that they were taken for <rs ref="ghost">the ghost itself</rs>, but
                their good fortune, and the fears of the spectators, prevented them from being
                apprehended. Being fatigued at last, they sat down on a seat in the garden, and the
                Major fell fast asleep. Sandy was half dozing himself, but being afraid of the cold,
                resolved to rouse the Major, and move; but just as he was about to stir, he heard
                    <rs ref="ghost">a voice in the tree above</rs>, which at once electrified him,
                and compelled him to listen to the following song, part of which he has forgotten,
                and part is made up from a partial recollection:—</p>
            <said><head><emph rend="italic">Noo Toon—James Crow.</emph></head>
                <lg>
                    <l>I came from Pandemonium,</l>
                    <l>If they lay me I'll go back;</l>
                    <l>Meanwhile around the town I'll jump</l>
                    <l><rs ref="ghost">Spring-heeled Jack</rs>.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l><rs ref="ghost" type="desc">White, and green, and flaming blue</rs>,</l>
                    <l><rs ref="ghost" type="desc">Sometimes dull black</rs>.</l>
                    <l>Fling your feet around your head,</l>
                    <l><rs ref="ghost">Spring-heeled Jack</rs>.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l><rs ref="ghost" type="desc">Some say I am a Marquis</rs>,</l>
                    <l>A-larking for a boast,</l>
                    <l>And they lay their bets I'll soon be duck'd:</l>
                    <l>But they never lay <rs ref="ghost">the ghost</rs>.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l><rs ref="ghost" type="desc">Some say its Dan O'Connell</rs>,</l>
                    <l>They feel so agitated;</l>
                    <l><rs ref="ghost" type="desc">But others swear my step's too light</rs>,</l>
                    <l>For Dan to imitate it.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l><rs ref="ghost" type="desc">'Tis Baron Brougham, some maintain</rs>,</l>
                    <l>On a soul-er expedition,</l>
                    <l>To see if people's minds have yet</l>
                    <l>Got rid of superstition.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>Ah, ah! its funny now to see</l>
                    <l>Their scientific airs;</l>
                    <l>I made an Infidel to-day</l>
                    <l>Devoutly say his prayers.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>The fellow swore I was a hoax,</l>
                    <l>And that he would me seize;</l>
                    <l>I peeped in his face when strolling home,</l>
                    <l>And left him on his knees.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>A bold inspector strutted up</l>
                    <l>To take me to the station,</l>
                    <l><q>Mary, come up</q>, says I, and he</l>
                    <l>Soon fled in consternation.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>They set a watch-dog on me, too,</l>
                    <l>To save themselves a fright,</l>
                    <l>The watch-dog growled, and barked, and ran,</l>
                    <l>But never dared to bite.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>With all the scientific skill</l>
                    <l>And learning of the age,</l>
                    <l>It's pleasing to see how safely still</l>
                    <l><rs ref="ghost">A ghost</rs> can walk the stage.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>I'll back to Pandemonium</l>
                    <l><rs ref="ghost">And bring a legion here</rs>;</l>
                    <l>For I see that spite of gas and steam,</l>
                    <l>The coast's still clear.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>The ghostly fathers of the church</l>
                    <l>Are getting out of date,</l>
                    <l>I'll bring <rs ref="ghost">another ghostly tribe</rs></l>
                    <l>To pension on the State.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>There's nothing more poetical</l>
                    <l>Than mystery, I ween,</l>
                    <l>For truth without is stale as beer,</l>
                    <l>That in the light has been.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>'Tis light that makes the Radicals</l>
                    <l>So stale and common place;</l>
                    <l>Destroying night, they've spoiled the rest</l>
                    <l>Of all the human race.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>They'll never let their servants take</l>
                    <l>A comfortable nap,</l>
                    <l>For fearing this, and dreading that,</l>
                    <l>Disastrous mishap.</l>
                </lg>
            </said>
            <p>The spell was on Sandy as long as the song continued, and looking up he saw <rs
                    ref="ghost">a huge green figure, very luminous and transparent, dancing Jim Crow
                    on a large branch of the tree</rs>; how to proceed he knew not, he had never
                studied magic, and could not draw the ring nor repeat the incantation, he had
                forgotten to settle these necessary preliminaries before he set out; he therefore
                determined to reserve the laying to another opportunity; accordingly, he roused the
                Major, who was snoring loud, and would, most probably, have snored himself at last
                out of time and space if he had not been thus forcibly dragged from the brink of
                eternity—Sandy whispered in his ears, <q>there it is</q>, and pointed to the tree;
                the Major hurriedly pulled out a pistol and fired right up, but <rs ref="ghost">the
                    ghost swallowed up both the flash and the smoke, and the bullet whizzed right
                    through its under jaw, and cerebellum, without doing it a bit of mischief</rs>.
                They therefore solemnly concluded, that nothing but an adjuration in due form with
                all the enchantments of frankincence and tripod, pentacle, chrystal and ring, would
                prove effectual.</p>
            <p>As this will be attended with considerable expence, it is proposed to institute a
                subscription for the purpose, which we have no doubt the piety, and the public
                spirit, and the patriotism of our readers, will meet with a ready and a cordial
                reply. Subscribers' names will be regularly published. Those who subscribe one
                sovereign and upwards, will have their names in capitals. Five shillings and
                upwards, in Long Primer. One shilling, etc., in Brevier; and pence
                in Nonpareil. Subscriptions will be received by all agents and venders of the <emph
                    rend="italic">Penny Satirist</emph> in town and country.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
