<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/hoax.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GH-GNCCO-18410227">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thoughts On Seeing Ghosts</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Originally published by</resp>
               <name>The Odd Fellow, Yankee Notions</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
               <name>Gabi Keane</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This project encoded newspaper and periodical articles on ghost hoaxes in the Victorian period. This publication of the text serves as data in a collaborative laboratory edition for the 2022 NEH Institute "Advanced digital editing: modeling the text and making the edition" at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Ghost hoaxes in 19th-century British news media</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>All texts in this collection were sourced from British periodical and newspaper
               archives, transcribed,and encoded. The citation below was provided by the archive and
               appears exactly as given.</p>
            <p><bibl>"Thoughts on Seeing Ghosts." <publisher rend="The">Odd Fellow</publisher>, <date when="1841-02-27">27 Feb. 1841</date>, p. 35. Nineteenth
                  Century Collections Online, http://tinyurl.galegroup.com/tinyurl/6jHRW2. Accessed
                  9 July 2018.</bibl></p>
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This document is part of a larger digital collection of stories of ghost hoaxes from
               the 18th and 19th century London newspapers and periodicals. The project explores the
               beginnings of mass print media in a metropolitan area at a time when technology and
               education made reading increasingly common and inexpensive.</p>
            <p>The corpus holds 36 individual documents, which reflect a diverse mix of reporting on
               various hauntings in and around London between 1804 and 1889. The PDF and JPEGs from
               online databases were transcribed using ABBYFineReader OCR, then corrected and
               occasionally manually transcribed if document quality necessitated it. After
               normalization in plain text, all documents were upconverted to TEI XML.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>Earlier texts have had some spelling normalization due to errors in OCR.
                  Typographic em dashes are longer than modern em dashes, so all dashes have been
                  normalized to modern em dash length.</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation>
               <p>All extraneous white space used by printers to avoid overlapping with letters has
                  been removed. All quotes are simply tagged with the q tag.</p>
            </quotation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Believing in <rs ref="ghost">ghosts</rs>, somebody remarks, is like the sea-sickness when it first comes on.
            Nobody will confess, but everybody has misgivings. I must make myself an exception; for
            <rs ref="ghost">I am willing to confess both ghosts and sea-sickness</rs>. Beyond a certain point, however, I
            am not disposed to place the two phenomena upon an equality, for I am bound to confess
            that I should prefer seeing <rs ref="ghost">twenty ghosts</rs> to being sea-sick once. <rs ref="ghost">Ghosts, indeed, are
            favourites with me</rs>; and having enjoyed the advantage of seeing a great number, I can
            speak with some confidence about them. A great many people talk sheer nonsense on the
            subject; <rs ref="ghost">indeed, not one in ten, ever speaks of a ghost in a becoming style</rs>. All this
            has led to many mistaking notions in demonology. The long and the short of it is, that
            <rs ref="ghost">ghosts have been very badly treated</rs> by people in general, and if we do not turn over a
            new leaf, I am under some apprehensions that the whole army of spirits will discontinue
            their visits, in resentment of these affronts, so that before long, there will not be a
            ghost to be seen for love, money, or murder. This catastrophe, I grieve to say, seems to
            be approaching already, for <rs ref="ghost">ghosts are not half so common as they were in the days of my
            grandmother</rs>.</p>
         <p>Strict justice, however, compels me to say, that the <rs ref="ghost">ghosts themselves are somewhat to
            blame in this matter, their behaviour at times being a little antic and anomalous</rs>. There
            are faults on both sides; which, hoping I may remedy, I offer the following suggestions
            for the considerations of both parties, and let ghosts and ghost-seers lay them to
            heart.</p>
         <p>In the first place, <rs ref="ghost">a ghost should never wear a night-cap</rs>. Some readers may doubt
            whether the thing has ever been done, but the fact is unquestionable; <rs ref="ghost">ghosts in
            night-caps have been seen by too many credible persons</rs> to allow of any doubt upon this
            point. I protest, however, against any such head-dress for a member of the Tartarean
            regions; it is unghostly, and ought to be abandoned. <rs ref="ghost">If a ghost has any sense of
            propriety, let him appear with a bare sconce</rs>—it is much more respectable. Some
            indulgence may perhaps be claimed for a <rs ref="ghost">bald ghost</rs>, especially considering the coldness
            of the night air. My great-grandfather, who was a ghost-seer of some talent, used to
            recommend a wig; but this, I think, would never be endured: <rs ref="ghost">a ghost in a wig!</rs> what an
            unspiritual costume. No,—wigs will never do. A white handkerchief might serve every
            purpose, provided it was not tied on, for that would look night-cappish again.</p>
         <p>Secondly, <rs ref="ghost">a ghost should never pull a man by the nose</rs>. Here again I may be asked,
                  <rs ref="ghost"><q><emph>Have</emph> ghosts ever been addicted to nose-pulling?</q></rs> I am not
            certain; but the story goes that they have. I pronounce it wrong <emph>in toto</emph>;
            it is undignified and improper. <rs ref="ghost">If a ghost wishes to give any person so sensible a token
            of his presence, let him bestow a sound bang upon his noddle</rs>: this would be emphatic and
            decisive; there would be no mistake about it. But as to our noses,—hands off! No ghost
            that has any regard for his character, will clap his digits to your olfactory
            projection. This suggests another thought, <rs ref="ghost">Ought a ghost to be allowed to take snuff?</rs> My
            aunt Grizzel says, yes, if he can keep from sneezing. On mature consideration, I say no,
            <rs ref="ghost">unless it be the ghost of a tobacconist</rs>.</p>
         <p>Thirdly, <rs ref="ghost">a ghost should be nice in his eating</rs>: he should not eat too much, nor of the
            wrong dishes. <rs ref="ghost">Some kinds of victuals are unfit for a ghost to eat</rs>, and sound very oddly
            when they are mentioned in connexion with a visitor from the invisible world. An old
            lady of my acquaintance knew <rs ref="ghost">a ghost that came one Saturday night into her kitchen and
            ate half a dozen pigs’ trotters and a plate of minced fish</rs>. <rs ref="ghost">Another drank a quart of
            sour cider</rs>, but was observed to make a horrible wry face at it. <rs ref="ghost">These ghosts might plead
            their appetite, having travelled probably a good distance; but I think they ought to
            have gone further and fared worse</rs>. In fact, I object to eating altogether; but if it
            must be done, let them help themselves to light food, and by all means join the
            Temperance Society.</p>
         <p><rs ref="ghost">Fourthly, a ghost, when he appears in metamorphosis, should come in a shape befitting
            the sublimity of his character.</rs> <rs ref="ghost">I knew a ghost once that came in the shape of a teapot</rs>,
            and <rs ref="ghost">another that took the form of a leg of mutton</rs>? These are unghostly shapes; for what
            have legs of mutton and tea-pots to do in the invisible world? My uncle Tim saw <rs ref="ghost">one in
            the shape of a militia colonel: it is a pity that any ghost should ever have made such a
            fool of himself</rs>. A justice of peace once told me that he saw <rs ref="ghost">a ghost in the shape of a
            great jackass</rs>; but it was probably nothing more than his own shadow.</p>
         <p>Fifthly, there are various points of behaviour in ghosts, to which we may reasonably
            object. <rs ref="ghost">Ghosts may walk or run as fast as they please, but they ought not to cut capers.</rs>
            Some may say it is difficult for them to avoid this, considering how light they are; but
            that is their affair and not ours. <rs ref="ghost">A ghost, I maintain, ought to behave with sobriety,
            and not play fantastic tricks</rs>. My aunt Grizzel for instance, <rs ref="ghost">saw a ghost jump over a
            broomstick, and another grinding coffee: now any body could do these things, therefore a
            ghost ought not to do them</rs>. <rs ref="ghost">A ghost was seen once, that jumped over a dining-table,
            flung three summersets in the air, and made sixteen pirouttes on the tip of his right
            toe, without putting himself out of breath: I have no doubt this was the ghost of a
            Frenchman.</rs></p>
         <p>Sixthly, besides the rules I have laid down on the subject of night-caps, <rs ref="ghost">ghosts ought
            to be particular in their dress</rs>. <rs ref="ghost">Some ghosts dress so absurdly that they are not worth
            looking at when the lights burn blue, as enough such figures may be seen by broad
            daylight.</rs> <rs ref="ghost">Ghosts have been known to wear snuff-coloured breeches!</rs> and <rs ref="ghost">I have even known
            a ghost in cow-hide boots</rs>. Is this fit costume for a hobgoblin? Really, <rs ref="ghost">such ghosts
            ought to be taught better</rs>. Habiliments like these can never inspire a ghostly dread in
            any spectator, even in a church-yard by the light of the moon, or when the clock strikes
            midnight: they are entirely out of keeping. <rs ref="ghost">I have heard of a ghost that always came in
            a new coat, smartly buttoned up, and a spandy clean dickey. This must have been the
            ghost of a tailor.</rs> <rs ref="ghost">A tolerably good colour for a ghost is black; pepper-and-salt will
            hardly do; though I should not have much objection to that sort of homespun called
            thunder-and-lightning.</rs> But, after all that can be said in favour of fancy colours,
            <rs ref="ghost">nothing is equal to a white sheet; for, when gracefully thrown on, there is nothing
            becomes a ghost so well.</rs></p>
         <p>Seventhly, <rs ref="ghost">ghosts should talk good English, and by all means avoid poetry, for most of
            the ghost-rhymes current are as bad as any stuff I ever saw in the newspapers</rs>. <rs ref="ghost">Ghosts
            ought to maintain a certain tone of loftiness and dignity in their conversation</rs>, and not
            gabble like so many tinkers. <rs ref="ghost">What could a ghost be thinking of, who talked in this
            manner:</rs>—Then says the man to the ghost, <q>Who are you?</q>
            <rs ref="ghost"><q>I am the ghost of old Slouch, the red-nosed tallow-chandler,</q></rs> says he. <q>What do
               you want here?</q> says the man. <q>I'm only haunting this soap-barrel,</q> says the
            ghost. <q>I smell brimstone,</q> says the man. <q>Merely candle-snuff,</q> says the
            ghost. <q>Know of any money buried here?</q> says the man. <q>Only five shillings in the
               toe of a stocking,</q> says the ghost. <q>Well,</q> says the man, <q>in all my life,
               <rs ref="ghost">I never heard a ghost talk as you do</rs>,</q> &amp;c. &amp;c. Yet this conversation
            actually passed as related. My great-grandmother's second cousin knew the man perfectly
            well, and he was a person of undoubted veracity. This ghost certainly did not maintain
            the majesty of his character; and it is a mark of improvement in demonology, that <rs ref="ghost">ghosts
            stand more upon their dignity now-a-days</rs>.</p>
         <p><rs ref="ghost">People who are troubled with ghosts may be anxious to know the best means of laying
            them, and whether they ought to be sent to the infernal regions, or the Red Sea.</rs> On the
            latter point I may remark that I consider the Red Sea the safest, because, if sent to
            the first-mentioned place, some people might find themselves under a necessity of
            renewing acquaintance with them another day. <rs ref="ghost">Some ghosts are more difficult to lay than
            others.</rs> <rs ref="ghost">The hardest of all is the ghost of a deputy sheriff.</rs> When once a man is haunted
            by such an apparition, his case is desperate. No sprite or hobgoblin sticks closer to a
            man than this. He walks by day as well as by night, and his spectral form glides up and
            down ’change, as well as the churchyard. The phantom stares you in the face at the
            turning of every corner, and lucky will you be if you feel not the magic influence of
            his touch, which is able to communicate a more disagreeable shock than a torpedo or a
            galvanic battery. This spirit can flit through key-holes and under the crack of a door,
            and if be once taps you on the shoulder, you are fixed by enchantment to the
               spot.—<emph>From Yankee Notions.</emph></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
