<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/hoax.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GH-19CUK-18320318">   
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tom Paine's Ghost</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Originally published by</resp>
               <name>The Age</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed and encoded by</resp>
               <name>Gabi Keane</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This project encoded newspaper and periodical articles on ghost hoaxes in the Victorian period. This publication of the text serves as data in a collaborative laboratory edition for the 2022 NEH Institute "Advanced digital editing: modeling the text and making the edition" at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Ghost hoaxes in 19th-century British news media</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>All texts in this collection were sourced from British periodical and newspaper
               archives, transcribed,and encoded. The citation below was provided by the archive and
               appears exactly as given.</p>
            <p><bibl>
               "Tom Paine's Ghost." <publisher rend="The">Age</publisher>, <date when="1832-03-18">18 Mar. 1832</date>, p. 93.  19th Century UK Periodicals, http://tinyurl.com/ycw3hetk.  Accessed 31 July 2017.
            </bibl></p>
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This document is part of a larger digital collection of stories of ghost hoaxes from
               the 18th and 19th century London newspapers and periodicals. The project explores the
               beginnings of mass print media in a metropolitan area at a time when technology and
               education made reading increasingly common and inexpensive.</p>
            <p>The corpus holds 36 individual documents, which reflect a diverse mix of reporting on
               various hauntings in and around London between 1804 and 1889. The PDF and JPEGs from
               online databases were transcribed using ABBYFineReader OCR, then corrected and
               occasionally manually transcribed if document quality necessitated it. After
               normalization in plain text, all documents were upconverted to TEI XML.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>Earlier texts have had some spelling normalization due to errors in OCR.
                  Typographic em dashes are longer than modern em dashes, so all dashes have been
                  normalized to modern em dash length.</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation>
               <p>All extraneous white space used by printers to avoid overlapping with letters has
                  been removed. All quotes are simply tagged with the q tag.</p>
            </quotation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>A few nights since the bellowing wind with a hollow roar marched up <placeName
               ref="#fetter-lane">Fetter-lane</placeName>, convulsing the casements of each second
            floor! Not a light was seen, except the gas; the stars were fast asleep and covered over
            with the clothes of heaven! the dark thick fog had put out the moon, and quite obscured
            that varied nothing some call sky! <placeName ref="#stpauls">St. Paul’s</placeName> was snoring twelve, the helpless guardians
            tried locks, bolts, and bars, yawning the hour as they had it from their tall fat
            friend, and Somnus had just walked his drowsy cap over the evil eyes of <q>a labourer in
                  <placeName ref="#stdunstans">St. Dunstan’s</placeName>,</q> when lo! a sprite
            appeared! <rs ref="ghost">the ghost of <persName ref="#thomaspaine">Tommy Paine</persName></rs>! <q><rs ref="pol">Spirit of radicalism, arise!</rs></q> said Grimmy.
               <q>Avaunt!</q> cried Twopenny Trash, seizing a gridiron, <q>quit my sight! thy bones
               are marrowless, for I had the boiling of ’em and ought to know, but,</q> added he,
            recollecting his sacrilege in America, <q>What would your gracious
               figure?</q>—<q>Unhallowed grubber of dead men’s bones,</q> quoth Grimmy, <q>author of
               all that is rank and nasty! lend me thine cars! Mark me! instantly arise, doff thy
               red night cap, and fix fast in thine artificial ivories! List! but soft, methinks I
               scent thy hopeful heir; brief let me be. Thou knowest that in Canada thy corn is
               never planted, therefore never reaped; thy writings too arc by all emigrants
               contemned, therefore keep the rebels here; <rs ref="pol">petition the House against this
               emigration</rs>; draw it up this very night: and as you did the man when Mayor, some good,
               why put it in the hands of <persName ref="#matthewwood">Matthew Wood</persName>!</q> Up rose the lecturer, on went his
            breeks, inspired by the spirit lie groped about for his lucifers in order to find
            himself, which done, he set to work, completed his task, sent it to Wood, who presented
            it from the <q>wonderful and astonishing</q> writer! It was rejected! and yesterday on
            the <q>gridiron</q> ’twas cooked, and garnished with peculiar spleen!</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
